>> KEELAN. LET COUNCIL
PRESIDENT KNOW THAT I'M ON THAT
I'M ON LIVE.
>> I'LL DO IT. I'LL RESIGN FROM
COUNCIL.
>> GOOD MORNING. I AM CALLING
TO ORDER THIS MEETING OF THE
PORTLAND CITY COUNCIL. IT IS
WEDNESDAY, SEPTEMBER 9TH.
KEELAN. CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL?
>> GOOD MORNING. KOYAMA LANE
HERE.
>> MORILLO. HERE.
>> NOVICK. HERE.
>> CLERK.
>> GREEN HERE.
>> ZIMMERMAN. AVALOS.
>> PRESENT.
>> SMITH.
>> HERE.
>> KANAL. HERE. PIRTLE-GUINEY.
HERE. RYAN. HERE.
>> DUNPHY HERE. AND CAN WE
PLEASE READ THE RULES OF
DECORUM FOR THE CHAMBER?
>> GOOD MORNING. WELCOME TO
PORTLAND CITY COUNCIL. TO
TESTIFY BEFORE COUNCIL IN
PERSON OR VIRTUALLY. YOU MUST
SIGN UP IN ADVANCE ON THE
COUNCIL AGENDA AT
WWW.PORTLAND.GOV/COUNCIL/AGENDA.
INFORMATION ON ENGAGING WITH
THE COUNCIL CAN BE FOUND ON THE
COUNCIL CLERK'S WEB PAGE.
INDIVIDUALS MAY TESTIFY FOR
THREE MINUTES UNLESS THE
PRESIDING OFFICER STATES.
OTHERWISE, YOUR MICROPHONE WILL
BE MUTED. WHEN YOUR TIME IS
OVER, THE PRESIDING OFFICER
PRESERVES ORDER DISRUPTIVE
CONDUCT SUCH AS SHOUTING,
REFUSING TO CONCLUDE YOUR
TESTIMONY WHEN YOUR TIME IS UP,
OR INTERRUPTING OTHERS
TESTIMONY OR COUNCIL
DELIBERATIONS WILL NOT BE
ALLOWED. IF YOU CAUSE A
DISRUPTION, A WARNING WILL BE
GIVEN. FURTHER DISRUPTION WILL
RESULT IN EJECTION FROM THE
MEETING. ANYONE WHO FAILS TO
LEAVE ONCE REJECTED IS SUBJECT
TO ARREST FOR TRESPASS.
ADDITIONALLY, COUNCIL MAY TAKE
A SHORT RECESS AND RECONVENE
VIRTUALLY. YOUR TESTIMONY
SHOULD ADDRESS THE MATTER BEING
CONSIDERED WHEN TESTIFYING,
STATE YOUR NAME FOR THE RECORD.
YOUR ADDRESS IS NOT NECESSARY.
IF YOU ARE A LOBBYIST, IDENTIFY
THE ORGANIZATION YOU REPRESENT
AND VIRTUAL TESTIFIERS SHOULD
UNMUTE THEMSELVES WHEN THE
COUNCIL CLERK CALLS YOUR NAME.
THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH,
COLLEAGUES. WE HAVE A JAM
PACKED AGENDA, AND
UNFORTUNATELY, IT LOOKS LIKE WE
ARE GOING TO HAVE JAM PACKED
AGENDAS FOR THE REMAINDER OF
THIS YEAR. LAST YEAR OR LAST
WEEK. LAST WEEK WE WENT FOUR
HOURS LONG AND MULTIPLE
COUNCILORS SPOKE INDIVIDUALLY
FOR MORE THAN 30 MINUTES. I
WILL BE LIMITING DEBATE TODAY
TO FIVE MINUTES PER COUNCILOR
PER ITEM. YOU'RE WELCOME TO GET
BACK INTO THE QUEUE, BUT WE
HAVE TO GET THROUGH A LOT OF
STUFF TODAY. FIRST ITEM ON OUR
AGENDA IS ALWAYS THE APPROVAL
OF THE AGENDA. HOWEVER, THE
FOLLOWING ITEMS WERE PULLED
FROM THE CONSENT AGENDA THIS
WEEK. A COMMUNITY MEMBER WITH A
FIDUCIARY INTEREST IN THE
PROPERTY UP FOR FORECLOSURE
PULLED ITEM 16, WHICH IS
REGARDING 27, 34 AND 2738
NORTHEAST ALBERTA STREET, TO
GIVE TESTIMONY. THAT REQUEST
CAME IN BEFORE THE AGENDA
PUBLICATION, AND THE ITEM IS
PLACED FIRST ON THE REGULAR
AGENDA. THE ADMINISTRATION CAME
TO ARRANGEMENTS WITH THE
PROPERTY OWNERS OF PROPERTIES
IN FORECLOSURE RELATED TO
DOCUMENTS TWO FIVE, TWO, 257
AND 258, AND HAS ASKED THAT
THEY BE PULLED AND REFERRED
BACK TO THE MAYOR AND COUNCILOR
SMITH PULLED DOCUMENT 306
RELATED TO THE COUNCIL PUBLIC
INFORMATION OFFICER
CLASSIFICATION DOCUMENTS
247248250253260 AND 261. ALL
FORECLOSURES FOR FURTHER
DISCUSSION. THAT CERTAINLY
MEANS THAT WE WILL NOT GET TO
ITEM 21 ADVERTISING ON ON BUS
BENCHES OR ITEM 22 DATA CENTER
NDA'S TODAY. IF ANYONE IS HERE
FOR THAT, I APOLOGIZE. WE WILL
NOT HEAR THAT TODAY. I'D LIKE
TO MOVE TO POSTPONE BOTH OF
THESE ITEMS, MOST LIKELY DATA
CENTERS TO NEXT WEEK AND BUS
BENCHES TO THE FOLLOWING
PENDING FEEDBACK FROM THE
SPONSORS. MAY I HAVE UNANIMOUS
CONSENT TO RESCHEDULE THESE
ITEMS? OKAY. THANK YOU. THOSE
ITEMS ARE RESCHEDULED. AND FOR
TODAY, THE ITEMS THAT HAVE BEEN
PULLED FROM CONSENT HAVE BEEN
PLACED AT THE END OF THE AGENDA
IN ORDER. AS IS STANDARD
PRACTICE, I'D LIKE TO PLACE AT
THE BEGINNING OF THE REGULAR
AGENDA DOCUMENTS TWO, FIVE, TWO,
TWO, FIVE SEVEN, AND TWO, FIVE,
EIGHT, THE FORECLOSURES THAT
ARE GOING TO BE SENT BACK TO
THE MAYOR AS A PACKAGE,
FOLLOWED IMMEDIATELY BY
DOCUMENT 306. THE COUNCIL PIO
POSITION WILL LEAVE THE REST OF
THE FORECLOSURES AT THE END OF
THE AGENDA. MAY I HAVE
UNANIMOUS CONSENT TO DO SO?
THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THE ITEMS
ARE REORDERED. ARE THERE ANY
OTHER REQUESTS TO AMEND THE
AGENDA TO REORDER ITEMS OR
RESCHEDULE AN ITEM FOR A FUTURE
MEETING DATE?
>> COUNCIL PRESIDENT, I'M JUST
CURIOUS. ITEMS 18, 19 AND 20.
THEY'VE BEEN READ PREVIOUSLY
SOME MULTIPLE TIMES, AND WE'VE
HAD PEOPLE COME TO THE COUNCIL
MULTIPLE TIMES. AND I, I DON'T
WANT TO SIT THROUGH ANOTHER
MEETING WHERE WE DON'T GET TO
ITEMS 19 AND 20, FOR EXAMPLE.
>> YEAH, I AS IS STANDARD
PRACTICE, WE WILL NOT BE HAVING
A STAFF PRESENTATION ON THE
ITEMS THAT WERE PULLED FROM
CONSENT. I'LL BE TURNING TO THE
COUNSELOR WHO SPECIFICALLY
PULLED THEM AND ASK IF THERE'S
SPECIFIC QUESTIONS ABOUT THEM.
AND I BELIEVE THAT THE
COUNSELOR SMITH MAY BE AMENABLE
TO CALLING ITEMS 15 THROUGH 20
AS AN AS AN.
>> I DON'T WANT TO TAKE UP MORE
TIME, BUT I WOULD BE VERY UPSET
IF WE DON'T GET THROUGH ITEM 20
TODAY, BECAUSE IT'S BECOMING
QUITE CONCERNING WHY WE'RE
DRAGGING THIS OUT SO LONG. YEP.
THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU SIR. COUNCILOR
KANAL THAT'S UNDERSTOOD.
>> THANK YOU. COLLEAGUES, DO I
HAVE UNANIMOUS CONSENT TO
APPROVE THE AGENDA? THE AGENDA
IS APPROVED. THANK YOU VERY
MUCH. KEELAN, CAN WE PLEASE
CALL PUBLIC COMMUNICATIONS?
>> FIRST UP, TODAY WE HAVE CAT
INEZ. CAN YOU HEAR US? CAT.
YOU'RE MUTED.
>> CAN YOU HEAR ME?
>> YES. WE SEE YOU AND HEAR YOU.
>> AWESOME. GOOD MORNING. MY
NAME IS CAT INES. I LIVE IN
BEAVERTON AND REGULARLY TRAVEL
TO PORTLAND TO SPEND MONEY AT
PORTLAND BUSINESSES AND PRODUCE
EVENTS HERE. I'M HERE TO TALK
ABOUT ODOT'S FIVE WEEK CLOSURE
ON SOUTHBOUND I-5. I WANT TO BE
CLEAR I SUPPORT REPAIRING THIS
INFRASTRUCTURE. I SUPPORT DOING
IT IN A WAY THAT MAKE SURE THAT
WORKERS ARE SAFE. I WANT THE
ROAD FIXED. WHAT I'M
QUESTIONING IS HOW ODOT
DETERMINED THAT THE FIVE WEEK
CONTINUOUS CLOSURE WAS THE MOST
COST EFFECTIVE WAY, AND WHOSE
COSTS WERE INCLUDED IN THAT
CALCULATION. A PROJECT DOESN'T
SIMPLY BECOME CHEAPER BECAUSE
THE COSTS MOVE OFF ODOT'S
BALANCE SHEETS. I'M ALREADY
EXPERIENCED THIS ON BOTH SIDES.
AS A CUSTOMER, I REGULARLY
DRIVE FROM BEAVERTON TO A SMALL
FITNESS STUDIO IN PORTLAND, AND
DURING THIS CLOSURE, I'M
CHOOSING NOT TO MAKE THAT TRIP.
THAT'S MONEY I WOULD NORMALLY
SPEND IN PORTLAND BUSINESSES
THAT'S NOT REACHING THE
BUSINESS DURING THOSE FIVE
WEEKS. I'M ALSO A SMALL EVENT
PRODUCER WITH AN EVENT IN
OCTOBER AT THE STAR. DURING
THIS CLOSURE, I DON'T KNOW HOW
MANY PEOPLE WON'T DECIDE TO BUY
A TICKET BECAUSE THEY'RE
WORRIED ABOUT TRAFFIC. I DON'T
KNOW HOW THE CLOSURE MIGHT
AFFECT MY PERFORMERS, CREW,
AUDIENCE AND EVERYONE TRAVELING
TO THE VENUE, AND THAT'S PART
OF WHY I'M HERE. MY QUESTION
WHEN ODOT SAYS CONSTRUCTION
ALTERNATIVES CHEAPER THAN
ANOTHER IS ANYONE MEASURING
COSTS LIKE MINE? I'M ONLY ONE
PERSON. BUT MULTIPLY THAT
IMPACT ACROSS THE REGION,
BUSINESSES WILL LOSE CUSTOMERS
AND REVENUE. WORKERS WILL SPEND
MORE TIME, ADDITIONAL TIME AND
COMMUTE, AND FUEL FREIGHT AND
DELIVERY WILL ENCOUNTER
CONGESTION, DRIVING UP THE COST
OF GOODS, AND PORTLAND STREETS
WILL ABSORB TRAFFIC DISPLACED
FROM I-5. THOSE ARE REAL COSTS
EVEN WHEN THEY DON'T APPEAR ON
ODOT'S BUDGET SHEET. I
UNDERSTAND THIS CLOSURE BEGINS
IN TWO DAYS. I'M NOT ASKING FOR
IT TO STOP. I'M ASKING YOU TO
LEARN FROM IT. THIS WON'T BE
THE LAST MAJOR TRANSPORTATION
DISRUPTION PORTLAND FACES. WE
HAVE ADDITIONAL WORK NEEDED ON
I-5 AND A MUCH BIGGER
INTERSTATE BRIDGE REPLACEMENT
PROJECT AHEAD OF US. I ASK THE
COUNCIL TO DOCUMENT THE
ECONOMIC AND TRANSPORTATION
IMPACTS DURING THESE FIVE WEEKS,
AND ASK ODOT TO PUBLICLY SHOW
WHAT'S INCLUDED WHEN COMPARING
ALTERNATIVES. DID IT ASSIGN A
VALUE TO FREIGHT DELAYS? ROAD
TIME, USER LOSS OF BUSINESS
ACTIVITY, ADDITIONAL FUEL
CONSUMPTION? I FOUND ALL THIS
INFORMATION DIFFICULT TO FIND.
IF THOSE COSTS WERE INCLUDED,
PLEASE SHOW US THE ANALYSIS. IF
THEY WEREN'T, WE SHOULD ASK WHY
AND MAKE AND MAKE SURE THEY
CONSIDER IT BEFORE THE MAJOR
NEXT PROJECT. BECAUSE OREGON
HAS ENORMOUS TRANSPORTATION
INVESTMENTS IN FRONT OF US,
OREGONIANS DESERVE GOOD
STEWARDSHIP OF BOTH OUR
TRANSPORTATION SYSTEM AND OUR
PUBLIC DOLLARS THAT SUPPORT IT.
GOOD STEWARDSHIP ISN'T SIMPLY
FINDING THE LEAST EXPENSIVE WAY
TO COMPLETE A PROJECT, IT'S
UNDERSTANDING THE TOTAL COST OF
THE CHOICES WE MAKE, INCLUDING
BORNE BY THE PUBLIC. OREGON
RESIDENTS AND BUSINESSES HAVE
THEIR TIME TO. OR OREGON
RESIDENTS TIME AND BUSINESSES
HAVE VALUE TOO. THANK YOU SO
MUCH TODAY.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THANK
YOU VERY MUCH.
>> NEXT UP WE HAVE DAVID DYSART.
>> GOOD MORNING.
>> MY NAME IS DAVID. I LIVE IN
THE DOWNTOWN AREA FOR NEARLY 20
YEARS AND IN PORTLAND ON BOTH
SIDES OF THE RIVER FOR THE
BETTER PART OF 37 YEARS.
PORTLAND'S GROWN SIGNIFICANTLY
DURING THAT TIME, BUT THE
CITY'S LEADERSHIP HAS FAILED TO
ADDRESS MANY OF THE CHALLENGES
OF CRISES THAT FOLLOWED. WE'RE
LIVING WITH THE CONSEQUENCES OF
SMALL THINKING, NAIVE
ASSUMPTIONS, AND BUREAUCRATIC
FINGER POINTING. WE CAN'T SOLVE
OUR BIG PROBLEMS IF WE CARE
MORE ABOUT PROCESS THAN
OUTCOMES. TOO OFTEN WE'VE MADE
THE PERFECT THE ENEMY OF THE
GOOD. BUT BEING SURPRISED 200
PEOPLE COULDN'T AGREE ON A
SOBERING SENTENCE, SO THEY JUST
GAVE UP. BUT AT LEAST EVERY
CONCEIVABLE INTEREST GROUP GOT
A VOICE IN DOING ENOUGH. AND
TOO OFTEN WE'RE MORE FOCUSED ON
VIRTUE SIGNALING TO OUR TRIBES
THAN HELPING THE MOST
VULNERABLE AMONG US, MORE
CONCERNED ABOUT IDEOLOGY THAN
INDIVIDUALS IN NEED. OUR
DOWNTOWN AND ADJACENT
NEIGHBORHOODS ARE AT THE CENTER
OF THESE CHALLENGES.
>> SORRY. PAUSE FOR A QUICK
SECOND. YOUR MICROPHONE IS OFF.
STAFF, ARE WE ABLE TO GET THE
MICROPHONE TURNED ON AT THE
DESK THERE? THERE WE GO. I SEE
THE LITTLE GREEN LIGHT. SORRY,
SORRY TO INTERRUPT. PLEASE GO
AHEAD.
>> DO I NEED TO BEGIN AGAIN?
>> YEAH. WHY DON'T YOU GO AHEAD
AND START OVER? I DON'T THINK
ANYBODY HEAR YOU AT HOME.
>> THANKS FOR THE TRIAL RUN.
THAT'S GREAT. GOOD MORNING. MY
NAME IS DAVID DICER. I'VE LIVED
IN THE DOWNTOWN AREA FOR NEARLY
20 YEARS. AND IN PORTLAND ON
BOTH SIDES OF THE RIVER. FOR
THE BETTER PART OF 37 YEARS.
PORTLAND'S GROWN SIGNIFICANTLY
DURING THAT TIME, BUT THE
CITY'S LEADERSHIP HAS FAILED TO
ADDRESS MANY OF THE CHALLENGES
AND CRISES THAT FOLLOWED. WE'RE
LIVING WITH THE CONSEQUENCES OF
SMALL THINKING, NAIVE
ASSUMPTIONS, AND BUREAUCRATIC
FINGER POINTING. WE CAN'T SOLVE
OUR BIG PROBLEMS IF WE CARE
MORE ABOUT PROCESS THAN
OUTCOMES. TOO OFTEN WE'VE MADE
THE PERFECT THE ENEMY OF THE
GOOD. LIKE BEING SURPRISED 200
PEOPLE COULDN'T AGREE ON THE
PERFECT, SOBERING CENTER, SO
THEY JUST GAVE UP. BUT AT LEAST
EVERY CONCEIVABLE INTEREST
GROUP GOT A VOICE IN DOING
NOTHING. AND TOO OFTEN WE'RE
MORE FOCUSED ON VIRTUE
SIGNALING TO OUR TRIBES THAN
HELPING THE MOST VULNERABLE
AMONG US, MORE CONCERNED ABOUT
IDEOLOGY THAN INDIVIDUALS IN
NEED. OUR DOWNTOWN AND ADJACENT
NEIGHBORHOODS ARE AT THE CENTER
OF THESE CHALLENGES. THEY BEAR
THE BRUNT OF THEM. DOWNTOWN
ISN'T JUST ANOTHER NEIGHBORHOOD.
IT'S OUR HEART. AND IT'S ON
LIFE SUPPORT. PORTLANDERS HAVE
LOST CONFIDENCE IN THIS COUNCIL,
TAKING UP IDEOLOGICALLY DRIVEN
AGENDAS FROM SPECIAL INTERESTS
SENDS A MESSAGE YOU'RE NOT
FOCUSED ON THE CRITICAL
CHALLENGES WE FACE. PERCEPTION
IS REALITY IN POLITICS, AND
YOU'RE SQUANDERING THE PRECIOUS
BANDWIDTH YOU HAVE TO WIN
HEARTS AND MINDS. WE NEED TO
CARE MORE ABOUT WHO'S ON OUR
STREETS THAN WHO'S IN THE WHITE
HOUSE. WE NEED TO CARE MORE
ABOUT WHO'S ON OUR STREETS THAN
WHO'S IN THE WHITE HOUSE. TRIPS
TO EUROPE FOR SOCIAL HOUSING
IDEAS, BANNING NICHE FOOD AND
RENAMING ALREADY RENAMED
STREETS. OUR HOUSE IS ON FIRE
AND WE'RE PICKING OUT CURTAINS.
IF YOU'RE NOT FOCUSED ON
ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT, PEOPLE IN
CRISIS ON OUR STREETS AND
PUBLIC SAFETY, YOU'RE NOT
MEETING THE MOMENT YOU'RE IN
ACTION IS DOING THE TALKING.
WE'RE HEMORRHAGING OUR TAX BASE,
DRIVING OUT THE VERY PEOPLE AND
BUSINESSES WE NEED TO FUND
BASIC SERVICES. IT USED TO BE A
NO BRAINER TO BE IN PORTLAND.
NOW IT'S A CHALLENGED CHOICE.
IT'S VITAL WE ATTRACT MORE
INVESTMENT AND VISITORS
DOWNTOWN, BUT WE ARE EITHER
UNWILLING OR UNABLE TO
MEANINGFULLY ADDRESS THE HUMAN
CRISIS ON OUR STREETS. NAME ONE
ENTRANCE TO DOWNTOWN WHERE
VISITORS DON'T EITHER
IMMEDIATELY OR WITHIN A SHORT
DISTANCE, CONFRONT A
HUMANITARIAN CRISIS. WE
DECLARED A STATE OF EMERGENCY
ON THE HOUSELESS 20 YEARS AGO.
CAN WE BLAME FOLKS FOR THINKING
WE HAVE NO IDEA HOW TO RUN A
CITY? WHY, IN 2026 ARE THE SAME
FIRST FOUR BLOCKS THAT FOLKS
ENCOUNTER FROM THE BURNSIDE
BRIDGE INTO DOWNTOWN? A
DYSTOPIAN NIGHTMARE. OVER
40,000 TRIPS GO ACROSS THAT
BRIDGE EVERY DAY. WHEN PEOPLE
SEE THIS CHAOS, THEY PERCEIVE
THE CITY AS IN CRISIS AND
UNABLE TO DEAL WITH ITS
CHALLENGES, LEADING MANY TO
AVOID DOWNTOWN AND FOR SOME,
PORTLAND ALTOGETHER. THAT'S NOT
KEEPING PORTLAND WEIRD. IT'S
KEEPING PORTLAND BROKE. THANK
YOU FOR YOUR TIME. GOOD DAY.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> NEXT UP WE HAVE ADDIE SMITH.
ADDIE YOU'RE MUTED. CAN YOU
HEAR US?
>> I'M SORRY. KEELAN CAN YOU GO
TO THE NEXT PERSON AND LET ME
GO LAST PLEASE?
>> SURE THING. WE'LL GO ON TO A
LOT OF VAGINA. ELANA. ALL RIGHT.
WE'LL GO ON TO ROGER WALL.
>> WE'RE JUST LAUGHING ABOUT
WHAT SHOWED UP UP THERE.
>> LITTLE LEBANESE, WELL
RECOMMENDED. SO THANK YOU.
PLEASE FEEL FREE TO INTRODUCE
YOURSELF FOR THE RECORD.
>> GOOD MORNING. MY NAME IS
ROGER WALL AND I AM HERE
REPRESENTING THE OREGON RAIL
HERITAGE FOUNDATION AND THE
OREGON RAIL HERITAGE CENTER.
WE'RE LOCATED AT TILIKUM
CROSSING BRIDGE AT SOUTHEAST
WATER AVENUE, AND WE'RE PART OF
DISTRICT THREE. WE'RE HERE
TODAY. WITH ME ARE RENEE
DEVEREAUX, OUR EXECUTIVE
DIRECTOR. RICK FRANKLIN, THE
BOARD CHAIR PRESIDENT, AND JIM
THOMAS, A BOARD MEMBER AND A
FORMER DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY.
DAVID DARLING, I WANT TO BEGIN
WITH SOMETHING THAT YOU ALL MAY
NOT KNOW. THE CITY OF PORTLAND
OWNS THREE HISTORIC STEAM
LOCOMOTIVES, D.O.J. STEAM
LOCOMOTIVES. THEY ARE HOUSED AT
THE OREGON RAIL HERITAGE CENTER
ON LAND ALSO OWNED BY THE CITY
OF PORTLAND. SO WE HAVE A VERY
CLOSE RELATIONSHIP. THOSE
LOCOMOTIVES ARE ENTRUSTED TO
OUR CARE THROUGH AGREEMENTS
WITH THE CITY FOR BOTH THE
PRESERVATION AND THEIR
OPERATION. THESE AREN'T JUST
SIMPLY MUSEUM ARTIFACTS. THEY
ARE PART OF PORTLAND'S LIVING
HISTORY. THEY INCLUDE THE
SOUTHERN PACIFIC 4449, ONE OF
THE WORLD'S BEST KNOWN STEAM
LOCOMOTIVES. IT WAS THE
AMERICAN FREEDOM TRAIN. IN 1976,
BICENTENNIAL, PULLING
HISTORICAL ARTIFACTS OVER
30,000 MILES OVER 27 MONTHS
AROUND THIS NATION. THESE
LOCOMOTIVES BRING VISITORS TO
PORTLAND FROM ACROSS THE
COUNTRY AND AROUND THE WORLD.
THEY PROVIDE SCHOOLCHILDREN,
FAMILIES, AND THE PUBLIC AN
OPPORTUNITY TO LEARN HOW
RAILROADS AND DIVERSE WORKERS
HELPED TO BUILD PORTLAND AND
OUR NATION, AND THE IMPORTANT
ROLE RAILROADS CONTINUE TO PLAY.
TODAY, MORE THAN 40,000 PEOPLE
VISIT THE RAIL HERITAGE CENTER
EACH YEAR, AND OUR EXCURSION
TRAINS CARRY APPROXIMATELY 3000
PASSENGERS. YOU MAY HAVE HEARD
THE HOLIDAY EXPRESS WHISTLE
DURING THE HOLIDAY SEASON.
TODAY, WE HAVE AN OPPORTUNITY
TO PROTECT THE RAILROAD THAT
MAKES MUCH OF THAT POSSIBLE, OR
HAS ENTERED INTO AN AGREEMENT
TO PURCHASE AND PERMANENTLY
PRESERVE THE OREGON PACIFIC
RAILROAD, WHICH RUNS ADJACENT
TO US. THIS IS NOT AN ABANDONED
RAILROAD. WE HOPE SOMEDAY TO
RESTORE. IT IS A WORKING
RAILROAD IN PORTLAND TODAY. IT
SERVES INDUSTRIAL BUSINESSES,
CONNECTS WITH BOTH THE UNION
PACIFIC AND BNSF, AND PRESERVES
A RARE AND
>> A UNIQUE URBAN FREIGHT
CORRIDOR. ONCE A RAILROAD
CORRIDOR LIKE THIS DISAPPEARS,
IT IS ALMOST IMPOSSIBLE TO
RECREATE. IT IS ALSO A RAILROAD
OF. OUR HISTORIC TRAINS OPERATE
ON. PURCHASES WILL BE
PERMANENTLY. PROTECT OUR
OPERATIONS, STRENGTHEN OUR
EDUCATIONAL AND TOURISM
PROGRAMS, AND PRESERVE AN
IMPORTANT INFRASTRUCTURE. ORF
HAS APPLIED FOR FUNDING THROUGH
THE OREGON STATE CONNECT OREGON
PROGRAM, AND WE'RE ASKING THAT
YOU SUPPORT US TODAY, NOT WITH
FUNDING, BUT WITH A LETTER TO
THE OREGON DEPARTMENT OF
TRANSPORTATION TO SUPPORT THIS
PURCHASE AND THE PRESERVATION
OF THIS CORRIDOR IN PORTLAND,
OREGON. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> ADI. CAN YOU HEAR US?
>> YES. I'M READY. GIVE ME ONE
SECOND.
I APOLOGIZE. I DROPPED
MY LAPTOP, SO IT'S GOING
HAYWIRE. HELLO. MY NAME IS ADI
SMITH. TODAY IS WEDNESDAY,
SEPTEMBER 9TH, 2026. I'M
SPEAKING BEFORE THE PORTLAND
CITY COUNCIL. I WANT TO ONCE
AGAIN CALL OUT SOPHIE PIEHL AT
THE WILLAMETTE WEEKLY FOR HER
RACIST AND BIASED REPORTING ON
IVORY MATTHEWS, THE FORMER CEO
AT HOME FORWARD HOME FORWARD
STILL EMPLOYS IAN DAVIES, THE
CHIEF OPERATING OFFICER WHO'S
LIKELY RESPONSIBLE FOR THE $30
MILLION SHORTFALL. AS CHIEF
OPERATING OFFICER, HE WAS
RESPONSIBLE FOR THE MID AND
LONG TERM OPERATIONS OF HOME
FORWARD'S REAL ESTATE PORTFOLIO,
MAKING STRATEGIC
RECOMMENDATIONS ON SALES,
CAPITAL ISSUES AND, MOST
IMPORTANTLY, CASH FLOW. THE CEO
SHOULD ANALYZE PROPERTY
PERFORMANCE TO BALANCE
FINANCIAL RETURNS WITH
IMPROVING HOUSING STABILITY AND
THE TENANT EXPERIENCE,
INTEGRATE SAFETY STANDARDS
ACROSS PROPERTIES, AND BUILD
FRAMEWORKS FOR LEADERSHIP
RESPONSES TO URGENT EMERGENCY
SITUATIONS, AND ENSURE
CONSISTENCY OF EMPLOYEES ACROSS
DEPARTMENTS. THE CHIEF
OPERATING OFFICER IS
RESPONSIBLE FOR OVERSEEING THE
DAILY EXECUTION OF STRATEGIC
AND OPERATIONAL OBJECTIVES.
THEY LEAD THE ORGANIZATION'S
HOUSING SERVICE AND ASSET
MANAGEMENT PROGRAMS, ENSURING
THAT OPERATIONS ARE ALIGNED
WITH THE ORGANIZATION'S MISSION
AND RACIAL EQUITY GOALS. IAN
DAVIE HAS NOT DONE THIS AND
SHOULD BE TERMINATED. SOPHIE
PEEL, A WHITE WOMAN, HASN'T
MENTIONED IAN DAVIES ONCE. SHE
ALSO HASN'T MENTIONED THE
FORMER CHIEF FINANCIAL OFFICER,
CANDY SAGE, ANOTHER WHITE WOMAN
IN ANY OF HER REPORTING. IT IS
RACIST AND IT IS BIASED. IAN
DAVIES HAS BEEN WITH HOME
FORWARD FOR SEVEN YEARS AND
CANDY SAGE WAS WITH HOME
FORWARD FOR OVER 20 YEARS, NOT
TO MENTION HER SILENCE ON
UNEDUCATED AND UNQUALIFIED.
MICHAEL BUONOCORE, WHO'S BEEN
WITH HOME FORWARD FOR OVER 20
YEARS BUT MENTIONS THE OVER $30
MILLION SHORTFALL WHEN TALKING
ABOUT TRAININGS A BLACK WOMAN
ATTENDED WHO WORKED FOR HOME
FORWARD FOR FOUR YEARS. NEXT, I
WANT TO CALL OUT THE DEMOCRATIC
PARTY OF OREGON OFFICERS NATHAN
SOLTES, KIM SCHMIDT, EILEEN
KEELEY, DIANE GROVER, KEN
TRUONG, STEPH NEWTON, AND
ESPECIALLY CANDY EVANS AND RON
MORGAN. THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY OF
OREGON OFFICERS ARE RACIST.
CANDY EVANS TOLD A BLACK WOMAN
THAT SHE WASN'T A FIT TO
VOLUNTEER AT THE STATE FAIR.
THIS AFTER THE BLACK WOMAN HAD
SIGNED UP, SCHEDULED A TIME
SLOT, GONE TO THE BOOTH
TRAINING AND SET ASIDE TIME TO
GO. THIS BLACK WOMAN IS AN
ELECTED PCP. MALES. DOZENS OF
POSTCARDS, VOLUNTEERS THEIR
TIME WITH MULTIPLE DEMOCRATIC
PARTY COMMITTEES AND MORE.
SHE'S ALSO BEEN ASKED TO
CANVASS FOR THE CURRENT
GOVERNOR. HOWEVER, CANDY EVANS
SAYS SHE'S NOT A FIT TO
VOLUNTEER AT A BOOTH. GET
PEOPLE REGISTERED TO VOTE AT
THE STATE FAIR. IT'S TIME TO
REMOVE NATHAN SOLTZ AND ALL OF
THE OFFICERS IN THE DEMOCRATIC
PARTY OF OREGON. THEY'VE
IGNORED NUMEROUS RACIST
EXPERIENCES. WHY ARE BLACK
PEOPLE CONSISTENTLY TOLD TO
FOCUS ON MAKING SURE A
REPUBLICAN DOESN'T TAKE OFFICE
OVER ANTI-BLACKNESS AND RACISM
WITHIN THE PARTY? THESE ARE
WHITE DEMOCRATS BEING RACIST TO
BLACK DEMOCRATS WITHIN THE
PARTY. IT IS TIME FOR NEW
LEADERSHIP. I ALSO WANT TO CALL
OUT THE CITY COUNCIL, GRESHAM
CITY COUNCIL, MULTNOMAH COUNTY
COMMISSIONERS AND MAYOR FOR
KEEPING THE SAME BOARD MEMBERS
IN PLACE AT HOME. FORWARD.
THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> OUR ALTERNATE TODAY IS SUSAN
MURNIGHAN. SUSAN. THAT
COMPLETES PUBLIC COMMUNICATIONS.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH,
COLLEAGUES. OUR NEXT ITEM IS
THE CONSENT AGENDA. APPROVAL
KEELAN. CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE
CAN YOU PLEASE READ THE CONSENT
AGENDA?
>> YEAH.
>> THE CONSENT AGENDA. I'LL
CALL THE ROLE FOR THE REMAINDER
OF THE ITEMS ON THE CONSENT
AGENDA THAT WEREN'T PULLED.
OKAY. KOYAMA LANE. I AYE,
MORILLO. I NOVICK. I CLARK. I
GREEN. I MISS ZIMMERMAN I
AVALOS. I SMITH. I KANAL I
PIRTLE-GUINEY. I RYAN. A DUNPHY.
I THE CONSENT AGENDA IS
APPROVED WITH 12 VOTES.
>> THANK YOU. KEELAN CAN WE
PLEASE CALL ITEMS SIX, SEVEN
AND EIGHT TOGETHER AS A PACKET?
>> OKAY, SORRY. JUST A SECOND.
LET ME MAKE SURE. OKAY. ITEM
OUR DOCUMENT 2026-252. INITIATE
FORECLOSURE ACTION ON 7250
NORTH EAST LOMBARD STREET FOR
THE COLLECTION OF DELINQUENT
CITY LIENS PLACED AGAINST THE
PROPERTY. DOCUMENT TWO OH,
SORRY. DOCUMENT 2026-257.
INITIATE FORECLOSURE ACTION ON
4324 SOUTHEAST 65TH AVENUE FOR
THE COLLECTION OF DELINQUENT
CITY LIENS PLACED AGAINST THE
PROPERTY AND DOCUMENT. 2026-258
INITIATE FORECLOSURE ACTION ON
6627 SOUTHEAST WOODSTOCK
BOULEVARD FOR THE COLLECTION OF
DELINQUENT CITY LIENS PLACED
AGAINST THE PROPERTY.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH, KEELAN
COLLEAGUES. REVENUE HAS ASKED
THAT THESE ITEMS BE REFERRED
BACK TO THE MAYOR'S OFFICE,
WHICH THEY HAVE THE RIGHT TO DO,
BUT I SEE COUNCILOR KANAL HAS.
>> YEAH, I WOULD OBJECT TO TO
REFERRING BACK ITEM SIX.
>> OKAY.
>> UNTIL WE HAVE. AND IF I CAN
TAKE 30S TO SPEAK TO IT, IT'S
SIMPLY THAT THIS ISN'T OUR
DISTRICT. I'VE BEEN GOTTEN
ABSOLUTELY NO INFORMATION ON
WHAT'S GONE ON, AND I DON'T
THINK IT'S APPROPRIATE FOR THE
ADMINISTRATION TO USE THE
COUNCIL AGENDA AS LEVERAGE
WITHOUT ACTUALLY TALKING TO US
ABOUT WHAT'S GOING ON HERE. SO
THE NUMBERS ARE CHANGING ON THE
AGENDA. JUST SO EVERYBODY KNOWS,
THIS IS THE LOMBARD ONE.
>> GOTCHA. THANK YOU.
>> I'M REFERRING TO 252026-252.
>> WELL THE ADMINISTRATION DOES
HAVE THE RIGHT TO PULL ITEMS
BACK. AND SO I WILL BE ASKING
FOR THE COUNCIL TO HAVE FURTHER
FOR FURTHER INFORMATION ON THIS
AS THE ADMINISTRATION PULLS IT
BACK. BUT AND THANK YOU FOR
COMING UP. BUT I DON'T ACTUALLY
NEED YOU. THE ADMINISTRATION
HAS THE RIGHT TO PULL THESE
BACK. AND SO THESE THREE ITEMS
WILL BE PLACED ON FILE. AND
KEELAN. CAN YOU PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER NINE?
>> OKAY.
>> DOCUMENT 2026-306. CREATE
NEW NON-REPRESENTED
CLASSIFICATION OF COUNCIL
PUBLIC INFORMATION OFFICER AND
ESTABLISH A COMPENSATION RANGE
FOR THIS CLASSIFICATION.
>> THANK YOU. SINCE THIS ITEM
WAS ON CONSENT, THERE IS NOT A
STAFF SUMMARY REPORT FOR IT.
COUNCILOR SMITH, YOU PULLED
THIS ITEM. WELL WELCOME TO.
>> CAN YOU READ THE READ THE
ITEM PLEASE. KEELAN.
>> YES, I CAN REPEAT THE TITLE.
CREATE A NEW NON-REPRESENTED
CLASSIFICATION OF COUNCIL
PUBLIC INFORMATION OFFICER AND
ESTABLISH A COMPENSATION RANGE
FOR THIS CLASSIFICATION
DOCUMENT NUMBER 2026-306.
>> YES. COUNCIL PRESIDENT, I
PULLED THIS ITEM BECAUSE I
WASN'T QUITE CLEAR WHAT IT WAS
AND WHAT THE OBJECTIVE WAS WAS
GOING TO BE FOR THIS. IT IS IN
COUNCIL OPERATIONS. I THOUGHT
THIS PARTICULAR POSITION WAS
UNDER THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR,
AND I HAD FURTHER CONVERSATION
WITH IS DANA HERE?
>> DANA IS IN THE BACK OF THE
ROOM. YES. COME ON UP, DANA.
>> AND I JUST WANTED TO MAKE
SURE THAT DANA, WE HAD A
CONVERSATION YESTERDAY, AND I
JUST WANTED TO MAKE SURE THAT
THIS WAS A POSITION THAT WAS TO
SERVE ALL OF COUNCIL, THAT THIS
WAS NOT A A C A POSITION. THIS
WAS NOT A MAYOR'S POSITION.
THIS IS A POSITION THAT WILL
SERVE ALL 12 OF US. AND THAT'S
WHAT I WANTED TO MAKE SURE. AND
WE HAD THAT CONVERSATION IN
PRIVATE. BUT I WANTED TO SAY IT
OUT HERE. THAT WAS THE REASON
WHY I PULLED IT.
>> SURE. COUNCILOR COUNCIL
PRESIDENT, COUNCILOR SMITH
THAT'S CORRECT. THIS POSITION
HAS.
>> BEEN INTRODUCED.
>> FOR THE RECORD. OH DARN IT.
THANKS. GOOD MORNING. DANA
RICHARDSON, COUNCIL OPERATIONS
MANAGER. THIS POSITION HAS
CURRENTLY BEEN SERVING THE
COUNCIL DOING A LOT OF THESE
DUTIES AS A SENIOR COUNCIL AIDE
THERE. THAT'S THE REASON FOR
THIS NEW CLASSIFICATION IS TO
BETTER REFLECT THE SCOPE OF THE
WORK OF THIS INDIVIDUAL. AND
YES, THEY WORK ON BEHALF OF THE
ENTIRE COUNCIL.
>> AND THE ONE POINT THAT YOU
MADE THAT WAS VERY. THAT WAS
THAT WAS CLEAR THAT THE REASON
WHY I PULLED IT, IN ADDITION TO
THAT OTHER ISSUE, WAS THAT IT
HAD SOMETHING TO DO WITH
PERSONNEL AND LABOR. AND I
THOUGHT, WOW, WHY IS THIS
PERSON DOING LABOR? SO CAN YOU
EXPLAIN THE OTHER REASON WHY
THIS JOB DESCRIPTION WAS WAS
DESCRIBED IN THIS WAY?
>> YES. COUNCILOR SMITH, AS THE
CLASSIFICATION IS PRESENTED,
THIS POSITION IS
NON-REPRESENTED, AND IT WILL
ALLOW THE PERSON IN THIS
POSITION TO SPEAK ON BEHALF OF
THE COUNCIL. WHEN THE COUNCIL
HAS A UNITED POSITION ON A
LABOR OR PERSONNEL ISSUE.
>> RELATING TO OUR EMPLOYEES.
>> IN LABOR. EXACTLY.
>> OKAY. THANK YOU, I
APPRECIATE IT, AND THANK YOU
FOR COMING UP.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH,
COUNCILOR. COLLEAGUES, IS THERE
ANY FURTHER DISCUSSION ON THIS
ITEM? SEEING NO ONE IN THE
QUEUE, THIS ITEM NOW MOVES TO
SECOND READING. THANK YOU. CAN
WE PLEASE CALL? SORRY, ITEM NEW
ITEM NUMBER TEN, THE NORTHEAST
ALBERTA STREET FORECLOSURE.
>> DOCUMENT 2026. DASH. I'M
SORRY. YOU KNOW WHAT? LET ME
MAKE SURE I'M CALLING THE RIGHT
ONE. THE DOCUMENT.
>> DOCUMENT 220 26256.
>> THERE WE GO.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH. INITIATE
DOCUMENT 2026-256. INITIATE
FORECLOSURE ACTION ON 2734
THROUGH 2738 NORTHEAST ALBERTA
STREET FOR THE COLLECTION OF
DELINQUENT CITY LIENS PLACED
AGAINST THE PROPERTY.
>> THANK YOU COLLEAGUES. AS
BEFORE, THIS WAS AN ITEM THAT
WAS PULLED FROM CONSENT.
THERE'S NOT A STAFF SUMMARY
REPORT AVAILABLE. I UNDERSTAND
THERE IS A PERSON AVAILABLE
HERE TO SPEAK TO THIS ITEM, BUT
I WILL TURN TO COUNCILOR AVALOS
AND SEE IF SHE HAS ANY OPENING
REMARKS ON IT. YOU ARE WELCOME
TO SAY NO.
>> WELL I DO, YEAH. OKAY. I'LL
SHARE MY CHAIR REMARKS. SO
THESE ORDINANCES COME TO THE
COUNCIL FROM HOUSING AND
PERMITTING. THEY AUTHORIZE THE
CITY TREASURER TO INITIATE
FORECLOSURE PROCEEDINGS ON
DELINQUENT CITY LIENS. AND
THESE WERE IDENTIFIED THROUGH
THE CITY'S VACANT AND
DISTRESSED PROPERTIES PROCESS
AND WERE DETERMINED TO MEET THE
CRITERIA FOR FORECLOSURE UNDER
CITY ADMINISTRATIVE RULE. THE
COMMITTEE FIRST HEARD THESE
ITEMS ON JULY 21ST, AND THEY'RE
DEFINITELY, AS YOU CAN SEE, WAS
A LOT OF MIXING AROUND OF
THINGS. BUT AT THAT MEETING, OH
BOY, WHATEVER I WAS READING
JUST DISAPPEARED IN FRONT OF MY
EYES. OKAY. HOLD ON. SHOOT. ONE
SECOND. OKAY, SO RATHER THAN
IMMEDIATELY ADVANCING THE FULL
PACKAGE, WE CONTINUED THE ITEMS
TO AUGUST 4TH TO GIVE THE
COMMITTEE MEMBERS ADDITIONAL
TIME TO UNDERSTAND. AND THEN
THAT ADDITIONAL TIME DID RESULT
IN SOME CHANGES. AND SO THAT'S
WHY WE'VE GOT SOME PROPERTIES
THAT WERE ULTIMATELY WITHDRAWN
AFTER SOME RESOLUTIONS WERE
REACHED, INCLUDING OWNERS
SATISFYING OUTSTANDING BALANCES
OR ENTERING INTO PAYMENT PLANS.
WE ALSO HELD THE HAROLD STREET
PROPERTY IN COMMITTEE TO GIVE
THE PROPERTY OWNER PROPERTY
OWNER'S FAMILY ADDITIONAL TIME
TO DETERMINE WHETHER THEY CAN
RESOLVE THE SITUATION. AND YEAH,
I THINK THAT'S ALL FOR NOW.
THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. KEELAN.
I UNDERSTAND THERE'S SOMEONE
SIGNED UP FOR PUBLIC TESTIMONY
ON THIS.
>> YEAH, WE HAVE ONE PERSON
SIGNED UP. ME SO, HONEY.
>> YES.
>> SORRY.
>> SOMEBODY IS.
>> CONTROLLING US. COUNCIL
PRESIDENT.
>> OH, IS THAT WHAT I DIDN'T
LISTEN, I DIDN'T HEAR IT.
>> OKAY.
>> FAIR ENOUGH. I DID NOT CATCH
THAT. THANK YOU. COUNSELOR.
OKAY. SEEING NO ONE ELSE TO
DISCUSS THIS, THIS ITEM.
COLLEAGUES, IS THERE ANY
FURTHER COUNCIL DISCUSSION ON
THIS? SEEING NONE. THIS ITEM
MOVES TO SECOND READING. THANK
YOU. CAN WE PLEASE CALL NEW
ITEM NUMBER 11, WHICH IS
DOCUMENT 2026 272.
>> OH, SORRY.
>> I DON'T. YEAH. DOCUMENT
2026-272. APPROPRIATE GRANT
AWARD OF $35 MILLION FOR
SECTION 108 LOAN GUARANTEE
PROGRAM.
>> COLLEAGUES, THIS IS THE
SECOND READING OF A NON
EMERGENCY ORDINANCE. WE'VE
ALREADY HAD TESTIMONY AND STAFF
SUMMARY REPORT. IS THERE ANY
FURTHER COUNCIL DISCUSSION ON
THIS ITEM? SEEING NONE. KEELAN
CAN WE PLEASE CALL THE ROLL?
>> KOYAMA LANE. I MORILLO. I
NOVICK.
>> I.
>> CLARK I.
>> GREEN I.
>> ZIMMERMAN AVALOS. I SMITH. I
KANAL. I PIRTLE-GUINEY.
>> I.
>> RYAN A.
>> DUNPHY I.
>> ORDINANCE PASSES WITH A VOTE
OF 12 AYES.
>> THANK YOU. KEELAN. PLEASE
CALL ITEM NUMBER ITEM NUMBER 12
2020. DOCUMENT 2026-243.
>> YEP. AUTHORIZE EXCEPTION TO
CODE. CHAPTER 17.93 RENAMING
CITY STREETS AND AUTHORIZE THE
RENAMING OF CESAR CHAVEZ
BOULEVARD TO CAMPESINOS
BOULEVARD. ALLOW EXCEPTIONS TO
CODE SECTIONS 17.9, 3.010, 17.9,
3.020, 17.9, 3.030, 17.9, 3.040
AND 17.93.050.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH,
COLLEAGUES. WE HEARD PUBLIC
TESTIMONY ON THIS, BUT THIS WAS
CONTINUED AS A FIRST. I BELIEVE
IT WAS CONTINUED AS A CONTINUED
FIRST READING. BUT I ALSO
UNDERSTAND THAT COUNCILOR
KOYAMA LANE HAS AN AMENDMENT.
SO. COUNCILOR. KOYAMA LANE. AM
I WRONG.
>> POINT OF ORDER?
>> YEAH, OKAY.
>> I'M WRONG.
>> SECOND READING. THIS IS THE
SECOND READING. OKAY, BUT I
STILL UNDERSTAND. COUNCILOR
KOYAMA LANE AMENDMENT.
>> YEAH. FIRST, I WOULD LIKE TO
WELCOME OUR MEXICAN CONSUL
GENERAL CARLOS QUESNEL, WHO'S
HERE WITH US TODAY. IT'S AN
HONOR TO HAVE HIM HERE. THE
CONVERSATION LAST WEEK WAS
REALLY MOVING AND MEANINGFUL. I
WANT TO THANK ALL MY COLLEAGUES
FOR ENGAGING IN VERY THOUGHTFUL
WAYS, HONORING THE CAMPESINOS
COMMUNITY AND MOVEMENT, WHILE
ALSO ACKNOWLEDGING AND
ADDRESSING THE CONCERNS OF THE
RESIDENTS WHO WANT TO REVERT IT
BACK TO 39TH. AND IT'S REALLY
IMPORTANT THAT WE RECOGNIZE THE
WORK OF ACTIVISTS AND COMMUNITY.
NAMING A STREET IS ONE OF THE
MOST VISIBLE, PERMANENT WAYS
THE CITY CAN HONOR HISTORICAL
LEGACIES COMMUNITIES.
ADDITIONALLY, IT'S IMPORTANT
THAT WE LISTEN TO SURVIVORS
LIKE DOLORES HUERTA AND HONOR
LATINO LABOR LEADERS AND FARM
WORKERS BY RENAMING THIS
BOULEVARD TO CAMPESINOS. THANK
YOU TO ALL OF THE COMMUNITY
MEMBERS WHO CAME TO TESTIFY AND
SUPPORT OUR CITY'S CONTINUED
COMMITMENT TO OUR VALUES. AND
AS COUNCILOR SMITH SAID AT OUR
LAST MEETING, WE ARE MAKING
HISTORY. IT'S TRUE. HISTORY IS
NOW, AND I HOPE THE HISTORY
BOOKS TELL A STORY OF A
COMMUNITY THAT TOOK A STAND TO
HONOR LABOR LEADERS, SURVIVORS
AND MARGINALIZED COMMUNITY
MEMBERS AND ULTIMATELY CHANGE
THE CODE TO MAKE A BETTER
PROCESS FOR EVERYONE. THAT'S
WHAT WE'RE GOING TO WORK ON
NEXT. ADDITIONALLY, I'D LIKE TO
INTRODUCE AN AMENDMENT. OUR
ORDINANCE, AS IT STANDS, HAS
NOT ACCOUNTED FOR THE DOUBLE
SIGNAGE REQUIREMENT THAT'S IN
THE CURRENT CODE, WHICH
REQUIRES FEATURING BOTH E
CHAVEZ BOULEVARD AND CAMPESINOS
FOR FIVE YEARS. THIS WOULD BE
UNACCEPTABLE BECAUSE OF THE
CIRCUMSTANCES AROUND CHAVEZ.
AND SO THIS AMENDMENT WAIVES
THE FIVE YEAR REQUIREMENT AND
SEEKS TO REMOVE CHAVEZ'S NAME
FROM OUR STREETS AS SOON AS
POSSIBLE. THIS AMENDMENT WAS
CRAFTED WITH THE SUPPORT OF
FOLKS IN PBOT WITH A, D, C, A,
AND ALSO A CITY ATTORNEY HELPED
WITH THIS. AND ALSO COUNCILOR
SMITH. AND AS COUNCILOR KANAL
SAID LAST WEEK, SUPPORTING
SURVIVORS IS PART OF OUR
COMMITMENT TO EQUITY. MOVING
QUICKLY ON THIS, RATHER THAN
DEBATING IT INDEFINITELY IS
ITSELF A FORM OF THAT SUPPORT.
THANK YOU FOR THOSE WORDS. SO I
WOULD LIKE TO FORMALLY MOVE.
KOYAMA LANE ONE.
>> COUNCILOR KOYAMA LANE MOVES.
KOYAMA LANE ONE. IS THERE A
SECOND.
>> SECOND, SECOND.
>> COUNSELOR CLARK BEACH JUST A
LITTLE BIT THERE. COUNCILOR
CLARK SECONDS. COLLEAGUES
DISCUSSION OF THE AMENDMENT.
>> COUNSELOR POINT OF
INFORMATION. WHERE IS THE
AMENDMENT?
>> IT SHOULD BE IN YOUR INBOX.
>> IN OUR INBOX.
>> OKAY.
>> THANK YOU TO DISCUSSION OF
THE AMENDMENT, COUNSELOR.
PIRTLE-GUINEY.
>> YEAH. COUNCIL PRESIDENT, I'M
SORRY TO HAVE TO ASK QUESTIONS
ABOUT THIS, BUT I WOULD LIKE TO
ASK A QUESTION OF THE PBOT
DIRECTOR. WHAT INTERIM DCA.
>> ALSO ALSO ACTING PBOT
DIRECTOR.
>> INTERIM DCA ENACTING PBOT
DIRECTOR WILLIAMS THANK YOU.
WHEN WE HAD A DISCUSSION ABOUT
THE UNDERLYING ITEM, I ASKED
YOU ABOUT HOW THE TRANSITION
WOULD WORK AND THE NOTIFICATION
OF THE VARIOUS ENTITIES THAT
MAKE CHANGES IN SYSTEMS SO
PEOPLE CAN STILL HAVE THEIR
DAILY LIVES CONTINUE. THAT WAS
A CONCERN THAT I HEARD RAISED
BY MULTIPLE PEOPLE WHO LIVE
ALONG THE STREET, IS THE
RETENTION OF TWO STREET SIGNS
FOR FIVE YEARS, SOMETHING THAT
WE DO TO HELP INDIVIDUALS GOING
DOWN THE STREET WITH WAYFINDING,
OR IS IT SOMETHING THAT WE DO?
BECAUSE THERE IS A TECHNICAL
IMPLICATION FOR ALL OF THOSE
VARIOUS MAPPING ENTITIES AND
APPS AND THINGS LIKE THAT,
WHICH WE WOULD BE CHANGING BY
LIMITING THIS TO A ONE YEAR
PERIOD OF TIME. ESSENTIALLY,
WHAT I'M TRYING TO UNDERSTAND
IS, IS THIS. IS THIS ABOUT
PEOPLE RECOGNIZING WHAT STREET
IT IS? AND IS THIS ABOUT THE
NAME AND, AND KEEPING THE NAME
UP THERE THAT FOLKS RIGHTFULLY
WANT REMOVED? OR IS THERE A
MORE TECHNICAL IMPLICATION THAT
WOULD HAVE AN IMPACT ON THE
PEOPLE WHO LIVE ON THE STREET
AND THEIR ABILITY TO DO TO LIVE
THEIR DAILY LIVES?
>> GOOD MORNING. COUNCILOR,
THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR THE
QUESTION. FOR THE RECORD,
MILLICENT WILLIAMS, DEPUTY CITY
ADMINISTRATOR, INTERIM DEPUTY
CITY ADMINISTRATOR FOR PUBLIC
WORKS AND ACTING PBOT DIRECTOR,
TO ADDRESS YOUR QUESTION. IT'S
A LITTLE BIT OF BOTH. THERE IS
THE TECHNICAL NEED FOR US TO
MAINTAIN THE SIGNS AND THE
NAMING CONVENTION AS IT
CURRENTLY EXISTS TODAY, AND
THAT'S FOR ANY STREET. BUT
THERE'S ALSO THE NEED TO
ACKNOWLEDGE THAT IT DOES TAKE
THE TIME TO TRANSITION THOSE
NAMES THROUGH ALL OF THE
ENTITIES THAT WE DISCUSSED LAST
WEEK TO INCLUDE THE US POSTAL
SERVICE, OF COURSE, THE STATE
DEPARTMENT OF TRANSPORTATION
AND OTHERS, THE MAPPING
SERVICES. ALL OF THOSE FOLKS
NEED TO BE MADE AWARE OF, OF
THOSE CHANGES, THE REDUCTION IN
THE AMOUNT OF TIME DOES NOT
CHANGE. THE URGENCY AND THE
NEED TO ADDRESS THAT NAME
CHANGING. AND FOR THE RECORD,
IT DOES NOT KEEP HISTORICAL
SYSTEMS FROM ACKNOWLEDGING EVEN
39TH STREET. SO THERE ARE
SYSTEMS TODAY THAT IF YOU
ACCESS THEM LOOKING FOR CESAR
CHAVEZ, IT'LL SAY 39TH. SO
THERE'S A LONG STANDING HISTORY
OF NAMES SHOWING UP ON THE
RECORD FOR A VERY LONG PERIOD
OF TIME, ALLOWING PEOPLE THE
OPPORTUNITY TO CHANGE THEIR
DEEDS, TO CHANGE THE STATIONERY,
TO CHANGE WHATEVER THEY NEED TO
CHANGE WITHOUT THERE BEING A
SIGNIFICANT IMPEDIMENT TO THEM
BEING ABLE TO RECEIVE WHATEVER
IT IS THAT THEY NEED TO RECEIVE
FOR BANKS TO BE ABLE TO MAKE
THE CHANGES THAT NEED TO BE
MADE, AND FOR THERE NOT TO BE
ANY PUNITIVE, PUNITIVE, OR
ACCIDENTAL SKIPPING OF PEOPLE
RECEIVING WHATEVER IT IS THAT
THEY NEED.
>> SO DOES.
>> I'M SORRY, DOES LIMITING
THIS FROM FIVE YEARS TO ONE
YEAR CREATE A TECHNICAL
DIFFERENCE IN IMPLEMENTATION
AND IN THE EXPERIENCE FOR
PEOPLE WHO LIVE ON THE STREET?
OR IS IT SIMPLY ABOUT WHAT SIGN
HAPPENS TO BE ON THE STREET
CORNER? AND THERE IS NO
TECHNICAL DIFFERENCE?
>> THERE'S NO TECHNICAL
DIFFERENCE.
>> OKAY. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR
PIRTLE-GUINEY COUNCILOR NOVICK.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. I
ALSO HAVE A QUESTION FOR THE
ACTING AND DEPUTY. SO I JUST
WANTED TO I THINK THIS RELATES
FOR HOW LONG WILL THE POST
OFFICE DELIVER MAIL TO CESAR
CHAVEZ? AND IN FACT, AS THE
POST OFFICE EVEN STILL DELIVER
MAIL TO 39TH.
>> YES, FOREVER, THEY WILL
CONTINUE TO DELIVER TO 39TH TO
CESAR CHAVEZ AND THEN TO THE
NEW NEWLY NAMED STREET.
>> AND AND THIS IS FOR THE
SPONSOR AS WELL. I MEAN, HAVE
WE DONE ANY OUTREACH TO
BUSINESSES OR RESIDENTS ALONG
CESAR CHAVEZ TO LIKE, ASK THEM
IF THEY'RE PARTICULAR VALUE TO
THEM TO HAVING MORE THAN MORE
THAN A YEAR TO, TO MAKE THIS
ADJUSTMENT? I ACTUALLY MET WITH
SOME FOLKS IN CRESTON,
KENILWORTH YESTERDAY, AND I
WERE UPSET ABOUT THE PROCESS.
AND I WAS SAYING, WELL, YOU
KNOW, THAT THIS SAME SIGNS ARE
UP FOR FIVE YEARS. AND SOME OF
THEM FOUND IT REASSURING. I WAS
JUST WONDERING IF WE'VE DONE
ANY OUTREACH TO FOLKS TO ASK
ABOUT WHETHER A YEAR IS, IS
LONG ENOUGH.
>> THANK YOU FOR THE QUESTION.
I'VE HAD CONVERSATIONS WITH
SOME BUSINESS OWNERS AND, AND
WHEN WE WERE ON THE DAIS LAST
WEEK, INVITED ANY FOLKS THAT
WOULD LIKE ASSISTANCE OR WOULD
LIKE SUPPORT WITH THE CHANGES
TO REACH OUT TO MY OFFICE AND
ALSO SUGGESTED THAT PROSPER
PORTLAND BE TAPPED FOR FIGURING
OUT HOW WE CAN USE SOME OF
THOSE SMALL BUSINESS GRANTS TO
SUPPORT. BUT THIS THIS
AMENDMENT IS MORE OF A.
SOMETHING THAT WE DID WITH PBOT
IN THE LAST FEW HOURS. THANK
YOU FOR YOUR SUPPORT ON THIS.
REALIZING THAT RATHER THAN
GIVING PBOT FIVE YEARS TO DO
THIS, IT ACTUALLY MANDATES IN
THE CODE THAT YOU HAVE TO HAVE
BOTH NAMES UP. SO WANTED TO
PROVIDE FLEXIBILITY. AND WHEN
TALKING WITH DIRECTOR INTERIM
DC A AND SHOSHANA COHEN, THEY.
I GOT A SUGGESTION FROM
SHOSHANA TO USE THE SAME
LANGUAGE THAT WAS USED WHEN WE
JUST CHANGED. JACKSON. SO THIS
IS WHAT THEY SUGGESTED THAT WE
DID.
>> THAT WAS A YEAR AS WELL.
>> I BELIEVE IT'S TWO YEARS FOR
FOR JACK. IS IT IS IT? I'M
SORRY I DON'T HAVE THE DETAILS
ON JACKSON, EVEN THOUGH WE JUST
FINISHED DOING THAT WORK THE
OTHER DAY.
>> I CAN GET I CAN DOUBLE CHECK
WITH SHOSHANA.
>> I CAN I CAN CERTAINLY FIND
THAT OUT FOR YOU.
>> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. COUNCILOR. NOVICK.
COUNCILOR SMITH.
>> THANK YOU, THANK YOU.
INTERIM DC A WILLIAMS. I JUST
FOUND OUT ABOUT THIS THREE
HOURS AGO, AND I WAS NOT AWARE
THAT THERE WAS ALREADY AN
AMENDMENT IN THE WORKS THAT WAS
BEING WORKED ON. I WAS TOLD
ABOUT THIS. LIKE IT, WE CAN
BRING THIS UP BECAUSE IT MIGHT
BE AN ISSUE, AND WE MAY BE ABLE
TO DO THIS AS AN AMENDMENT, BUT
THIS IS CLEARLY SOMETHING THAT
HAD BEEN THOUGHT ABOUT. I WAS
NOT SURE ABOUT THE ONE YEAR. I
JUST IT JUST STUCK IN MY HEAD
ABOUT THE ONE YEAR AND GIVING
PEOPLE TIME TO. THERE'S A LOT
GOING ON. GIVING PEOPLE TIME TO
CHANGE THEIR LETTERHEAD AND ALL
THOSE THINGS. I DON'T THINK
THAT ONE YEAR IS ENOUGH. THAT'S
WHAT I'M SAYING. I DON'T THINK
IT'S ENOUGH. I DON'T KNOW THAT
WE CAN GET IT OUT IN A YEAR. DO
YOU THINK WE CAN GET THIS OUT
IN A YEAR?
>> WE WOULD NOT BE ABLE. IT'S
LIKELY THAT WE WOULD NOT BE
ABLE TO DO ALL THE NAME CHANGES
AND POST ALL OF THE SIGNS
WITHIN A YEAR, GIVEN THE
OVERALL PROCESS.
>> SO THAT'S WHAT I'M CONCERNED
ABOUT.
>> DO WE NEED FIVE? PROBABLY
NOT. BUT ONE IS IS SO NOT
IMPOSSIBLE, BUT IT WOULD BE NOT
WITHOUT ITS CHALLENGES.
>> SO I WOULD LIKE TO ADD
ANOTHER YEAR ONTO THIS. AT
ANOTHER AT ANOTHER AMENDMENT TO
THIS TO GIVE MORE TIME BECAUSE
I'M JUST I'M JUST NOT CLEAR. SO
I'D LIKE TO MAKE A MOTION AND
ADD AN AMENDMENT TO THE
AMENDMENT TO GIVE ANOTHER YEAR.
>> DO YOU HAVE THE FLOOR? SORRY.
>> WE'RE IN THE MIDDLE OF THE
ONE AMENDMENT MOTION RIGHT NOW.
SO WE'LL. RIGHT.
>> SO WE'RE UNABLE TO. YEAH. WE
ARE DEBATING A MOTION. WE
CANNOT MAKE AN ADDITIONAL
MOTION DURING THAT. OKAY. BUT
IF THE.
>> YEAH.
>> WE CAN WE CAN.
>> THANK YOU. COUNCIL PRESIDENT
THANK YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT I
DID HAVE THE FLOOR. I HAD MY
HAND UP.
>> YEP.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
COUNCILOR PIRTLE-GUINEY. YOU
ALREADY SPOKE. SO I'LL COME
BACK.
>> COUNCIL PRESIDENT IS IT CAN
I BE.
>> RECOGNIZED TO PULL MY
AMENDMENT AND THEN RESTATE IT
WITH TWO YEARS?
>> LET ME GET THROUGH THE QUEUE
HERE REAL QUICK. YOU ARE
QUICKLY COMING UP HERE IN A
SECOND. COUNCILOR KANAL.
>> ALL RIGHT. SO JUST IN TERMS
OF THE THE THE RENAMING OF
JACKSON STREET TO ROSE HILL
STREET, THAT'S WE'RE TALKING
ABOUT ORDINANCE 192142 THAT WAS
ADOPTED IN FEBRUARY OF THIS
YEAR. THAT DOES SIX MONTHS. SO
I'M GOING TO READ FROM THAT.
THE REQUIREMENTS IN THE CODE
SUBSECTION 1793060 A ARE HEREBY
WAIVED FOR THE PROPOSED
RENAMING OF A PORTION OF
SOUTHWEST JACKSON STREET TO
SOUTHWEST ROSE HILL STREET.
INSTEAD, THE EXISTING STREET
NAME SIGN AND PROPOSED NEW
STREET NAME SIGN SHALL BOTH BE
POSTED AND MAINTAINED FOR SIX
MONTHS, FOLLOWING APPROVAL FOR
THE PROPOSED RENAMING OF A
PORTION OF SOUTHWEST JACKSON
STREET TO SOUTHWEST ROSE HILL
STREET. WHY WOULD IT BE
DIFFERENT IN THIS PARTICULAR.
IS IT. IS IT SIMPLY THE LENGTH
OF THE STREET, OR IS THERE
ANOTHER REASON WHY A YEAR WOULD
BE INSUFFICIENT?
>> THANK YOU FOR THAT,
COUNCILOR. AFTER I SAID TWO
YEARS, I REMEMBERED THAT IT WAS
A SIX MONTH PERIOD. PART OF
THAT IS DRIVEN BY THE LENGTH OF
THE STREET. THERE ARE LIMITED
NUMBER OF BLOCKS. IT'S THREE
BLOCKS THAT WE WOULD NEED TO
CHANGE THE SIGNAGE ON FOR US TO
REMOVE JACKSON AND CHANGE IT TO
ROSE HILL. SO THAT IS SOMETHING
THAT WE COULD DO QUITE QUICKLY
WITH LIMITED AMOUNT OF LABOR
AND PLANNING. AND THERE ARE A
SIGNIFICANTLY SMALLER NUMBER OF
ADDRESSES THAT WE WOULD NEED TO
ENGAGE WITH IN ORDER TO DO THAT.
TO MAKE THAT CHANGE, THE CESAR
CHAVEZ STREET NAMING RENAMING
REQUIRES, IT'S A FIVE AND A
HALF MILE STRETCH, SO WE WOULD
NEED TO ADDRESS THAT, GET THE
SIGNING, THE SIGNAGE PRODUCED.
THERE WOULD BE SOME OUTREACH ON
THE STAFF'S BEHALF. AND WE
WOULD ALSO NEED TO WORK WITH
THE OREGON DEPARTMENT OF
TRANSPORTATION. THERE ARE
STREET SIGNS, OR THERE ARE
WAYFINDING SIGNS THAT CROSS THE
INTERSTATE. AND SO THERE WOULD
BE THE NEED TO DO THAT
COORDINATION, BECAUSE IT WOULD
REQUIRE A CLOSURE IN EITHER
DIRECTION, WHERE THOSE SIGNS
ARE FOR US TO REPLACE THE SIGN.
SO IT WOULD TAKE A LITTLE BIT
MORE EFFORT OR SIGNIFICANTLY
MORE EFFORT IN ORDER TO DO THAT.
AGAIN, SOMETHING THAT COULD BE
DONE WITHIN A YEAR BECAUSE OF
THE LENGTH OF THE STREET AND
THE DETAILS ASSOCIATED. IT
WOULD BE A HARD, HARD PUSH. AND
I'D ALSO LIKE TO ACKNOWLEDGE
THAT WHILE WE DO HAVE STAFF
THAT DEDICATE A PORTION OF
THEIR TIME TO THIS WORK, THIS
WOULD REQUIRE THE BUREAU TO
IDENTIFY ADDITIONAL FOLKS TO
HELP TO ENSURE THAT WE GOT THIS
OVER THE FINISH LINE, OR CREATE
THE OPPORTUNITY FOR THE PERSON
WHO SPENDS MOST OF THEIR TIME
WORKING ON, FOR EXAMPLE, THE
ROSE HILL STREET RENAMING
DEDICATE ALMOST ALL OF THEIR
TIME TO THAT EFFORT.
>> THANKS. SO I WAS THAT MAKES
SENSE. I WAS CURIOUS IF THERE
WERE ANY OTHER REASONS, I THINK,
AND MAYBE THIS DIDN'T HAPPEN
BETWEEN THE TWO, BUT MY
RECOLLECTION IS THAT BETWEEN
APRIL WHEN THIS CAME UP AND NOW
THE ONE PERSON WHO MAKES THE
SIGNS LEFT PBOT.
>> THAT'S LESS OF A CONCERN.
NOW, THE SIGN MAKER DID RETIRE
IN APRIL, SO WE NO LONGER HAVE
A SIGN SHOP WITHIN THE BUREAU.
WE DO HAVE ON TAP CONTRACTORS
WHO ARE ABLE TO CREATE THE
SIGNS THAT WE NEED. THAT'S NOT
A BARRIER TO US BEING ABLE TO
MOVE FORWARD.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU,
COUNCILOR.
>> COUNCILOR KOYAMA LANE.
>> 17.93.06 IMPLEMENTATION A
SAYS BOTH NAMES WILL BE IN
PLACE FOR A PERIOD OF FIVE
YEARS, UNLESS A PETITION IS
SUBMITTED TO THE CITY
ADMINISTRATOR FROM A MAJORITY
OF ABUTTING PROPERTY OCCUPANTS
REQUESTING THAT THE DUAL
SIGNAGE PERIOD BE SHORTENED.
BOTH STREET NAMES WILL BE
MAINTAINED FOR THE FIVE YEAR
PERIOD AT THE SAME LEVEL OF
MAINTENANCE APPROVED FOR STREET
NAME SIGN MAINTENANCE
MAINTENANCE CITYWIDE, AT WHICH
TIME THE OLD NAME WILL BE
REMOVED. THE WAY THIS CODE IS
WRITTEN SAYS THERE IS NO WAY IN
FIVE YEARS THAT CHAVEZ'S NAME
WILL COME DOWN. I WOULD LIKE
FOR THERE TO BE SOME
FLEXIBILITY. I ASKED FOR PBOT
FOR HELP ON WHAT TO PICK. I WAS
TOLD ONE YEAR. NOW I'M HEARING
SOMETHING DIFFERENT. I WAS
ACTUALLY OKAY WITH JUST
CHANGING THE WORDING TO UP TO
FIVE YEARS SO PBOT CAN HAVE
SOME FLEXIBILITY. SO I'M SEEING
SOME NODDING, SO MAYBE THAT'S
WHAT I NEED TO DRAFT RATHER
THAN ASKING OTHERS FOR SUPPORT.
SO I WILL BE BRINGING THAT.
WHAT I WOULD LIKE IS IF THINGS
ARE GOING WELL FOR PBOT TO HAVE
THE CHOICE TO TAKE THAT NAME
DOWN, NOT BE FORCED TO KEEP
BOTH UP. BECAUSE ONE OF MY
CONSTITUENTS SENT ME A NOTE
THAT SAYS EVERY TIME THEY SEE
CESAR CHAVEZ STREET, WHEN THEY
GO TO SAFEWAY OR TRADER JOE'S,
THEY'RE REMINDED ABOUT MEN
ABUSING WOMEN AND GETTING AWAY
WITH IT. SO I WILL BE BRINGING
A NEW AMENDMENT. I'LL WITHDRAW
MY CURRENT ONE.
>> OKAY. COUNCILOR CLARK, DO
YOU AGREE WITH WITHDRAWING THAT
SINCE YOU. SECONDED?
>> YES.
>> OKAY. COUNCILOR KOYAMA LANE
AMENDMENT HAS BEEN WITHDRAWN.
COLLEAGUES. NOW TO THE
UNDERLYING WHICH CHANGES MY
ORDER OF PEOPLE TALKING.
COUNCILOR. NOVICK.
>> YES, THANK YOU, MR.
PRESIDENT. THERE'S AN AMENDMENT
THAT I THOUGHT OF BRINGING LAST
WEEK AND DECIDED IT WASN'T
WORTH IT BECAUSE IT'S JUST A
WHEREAS CLAUSE, AND SINCE THEN
I'VE CONCLUDED THAT IT IS WORTH
DOING. AND I STILL WASN'T GOING
TO DO IT IF THERE WEREN'T ANY
OTHER AMENDMENTS, BECAUSE I
DON'T WANT TO MESS WITH THE
SECOND READING. BUT THERE'S
LANGUAGE IN PARAGRAPH TWO OF
THE RESOLUTION THAT SAYS
THERE'S WIDESPREAD CONSENSUS IN
THE COMMUNITY TO MAKE THIS NAME
CHANGE, AND I DON'T THINK
THAT'S ACTUALLY TRUE. THE
MAJORITY OF PEOPLE, INDIVIDUAL
PEOPLE WHO HAVE COMMENTED ON
THIS PROPOSAL, ARE OPPOSED TO
IT. THERE'S A LOT OF PEOPLE WHO
WOULD LIKE IT TO BE 39TH. SO BY
SAYING THERE'S WIDESPREAD
CONSENSUS IN THE COMMUNITY, I
THINK IT KIND OF TELLS A LOT OF
PEOPLE THAT THEY DON'T EXIST.
AND ALTHOUGH I AGREE WITH THIS
NAME CHANGE, I'M CONCERNED,
PARTICULARLY WHEN THERE REALLY
WAS VERY LITTLE OUTREACH TO THE
BROADER COMMUNITY ABOUT THIS
ISSUE, I'M CONCERNED ABOUT
HAVING THAT LANGUAGE. SO AGAIN,
BECAUSE THERE'S ANOTHER
AMENDMENT ON THE FLOOR, WE'VE
SENT OUT A PROPOSED AMENDMENT
WHICH WOULD SIMPLY SAY UNDER
ITEM TWO, INSTEAD OF WIDESPREAD
CONSENSUS ACROSS THE COMMUNITY,
HAS COALESCED AROUND A SHARED
DESIRE TO SAY COUNCIL DESIRES
TO SWIFTLY RENAME PORTLAND
CESAR CHAVEZ BOULEVARD IN A
MANNER THAT BENEFITS AND HONORS
LA CASA LATINO, LATINX, LABOR
LEADERS AND FARMWORKER
ORGANIZATIONS. SO I OFFER THAT
AMENDMENT.
>> COUNCILOR NOVICK MOVES
NOVICK ONE. IS THERE A SECOND.
SECOND COUNCILOR KANAL SECONDS
COLLEAGUES TO THE AMENDMENT.
COUNCILOR SMITH TO THE
AMENDMENT.
>> THANK YOU. I DON'T SUPPORT
THIS AMENDMENT. I THINK IT IS
GENERAL ENOUGH AND THAT THERE
IS WIDESPREAD SUPPORT FOR THIS.
I DID NOT SAY THAT THERE WAS
OVERWHELMING SUPPORT. WORDS
MATTER AND THERE IS WIDE
SUPPORT. ALL YOU HAVE TO DO IS
GO TO MY FACEBOOK AND INSTAGRAM
PAGES AND YOU WILL SEE THE WIDE
SUPPORT. NOW, IF YOU'RE SAYING
THE PEOPLE WHO LIVE IN DISTRICT
THREE, I MEAN, THAT'S THAT'S A
LITTLE BIT. THAT'S DIFFERENT.
BUT I THINK CHANGING THE, THE
SPIRIT OF WHAT THIS IS BECAUSE
THERE IS WIDESPREAD SUPPORT FOR
THIS NAME CHANGE AND TRYING TO
WORDSMITH THIS AT THIS POINT, I
THINK IS, IS NOT CRITICAL FOR
US TO PASS THIS ORDINANCE TODAY.
I THINK IT'S NITPICKING.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR SMITH.
IS THERE SOMEONE ELSE IN THE
QUEUE WHO WANTS TO SPEAK TO
THIS AMENDMENT?
>> YES.
>> COUNCILOR GREEN.
>> THANK YOU. COUNCILOR NOVICK
IS A PERSON WHO CARES A LOT
ABOUT PRECISION IN OUR FINDINGS
AND ALSO OUR IMPACT STATEMENTS.
I THINK IT'S MORE I THINK. IT'S
TRUER TO SAY THAT COUNCIL JUST
IT'S A DECLARATIVE STATEMENT OF
COUNCIL'S WILL. COUNCIL DESIRES
TO DO THIS THING, AND WE'RE NOT
WE'RE NOT ADDING EXTRA
ASSERTIONS ABOUT THE CONSENSUS
POSITION. SO FOR THAT REASON,
I'M GOING TO SUPPORT YOUR
AMENDMENT. THANK YOU.
>> ANYBODY ELSE IN THE QUEUE
THAT WANTS TO SPEAK TO THIS
AMENDMENT? IT HAS BEEN I'M
SORRY, COULD COUNCILOR.
>> MY HAND IS UP.
>> I'M SORRY, I CAN'T. OKAY. GO
AHEAD.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU, MADAM
VICE PRESIDENT. THE IS MARTA
HERE, MARTA AND SOME OF THE.
ADVOCATES. COULD YOU PLEASE
COME UP TO THE TO THE DESK. AND
SO I HATE TO GO OVER THIS AGAIN.
THERE WERE OVER 350
ORGANIZATIONS AND INDIVIDUALS
WHO SIGNED A LETTER TO SHOW
THAT THERE WAS WIDESPREAD
SUPPORT. AND IF YOU WANT TO
ALSO SAY, IN ADDITION TO
WIDESPREAD SUPPORT, THAT THERE
IS COUNCIL SUPPORT AS WELL,
OKAY. BUT LEAVING IT WHERE IT
IS. SO CAN YOU TELL ME, MARTA,
COULD YOU INTRODUCE YOURSELF?
>> SORRY, COUNCILOR, WE DO NOT
HAVE PUBLIC TESTIMONY OR
INVITED TESTIMONY ON SECOND
READINGS, SO I APPRECIATE THESE
FOLKS ARE DEFINITELY OUT.
>> OF ORDER.
>> ABSOLUTELY.
>> ASK YOU A QUESTION.
>> YEAH.
>> CAN YOU GIVE ME A POINT OF
PERSONAL PRIVILEGE? BECAUSE
WE'RE DEBATING WHETHER OR NOT
WE CHANGE A WORD AND WE'RE
WORDSMITHING ON THE SECOND
READING. IF THAT WAS A PROBLEM,
I FEEL LIKE IT SHOULD HAVE BEEN
BROUGHT UP BEFORE.
>> HEARD, BUT I AM NOT GOING TO
BE ENTERTAINING ADDITIONAL
PUBLIC TESTIMONY THIS TIME.
SORRY. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU.
>> OKAY.
>> IT'S NOT ALLOWED TO TALK.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
COUNCILOR NOVICK.
>> I JUST WANTED TO SAY THANK
YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. COUNCILOR
SMITH I AGREE THAT WORDS MATTER
AND THE WORD THAT WAS MOST
CONCERNED TO ME HERE IS
WIDESPREAD CONSENSUS, WHICH
IMPLIES THAT EVERYBODY AGREES.
YOU'VE SAID WIDESPREAD SUPPORT.
I WOULD ACTUALLY BE OKAY IF WE
CHANGED IT TO. THERE IS
WIDESPREAD SUPPORT IN THE
COMMUNITY FOR SWIFTLY RENAMING
ET-CETERA.
>> OKAY.
>> THANK YOU.
>> MAY I ANSWER.
>> COUNCILOR SMITH?
>> SURE. COUNCILOR NOVICK. THAT
SOUNDS A LOT BETTER.
>> IN THAT CASE, HANG ON, LET
ME SEE WHAT THAT WOULD MEAN.
JUST DOING ON THIS FLY. THERE
IS WIDESPREAD SUPPORT. I WOULD
CHANGE IT TO. THERE'S
WIDESPREAD SUPPORT IN THE
COMMUNITY TO SWIFTLY RENAME.
>> AND AGAIN, AMENDMENTS. EVEN
THOUGH I APPRECIATE THE
CONVERSATION, WE DO NEED TO
REDUCE THIS TO WRITING.
>> I'LL DO THAT.
>> OKAY. THANK YOU, COUNCILOR
COUNCILOR MORILLO.
>> I JUST WANT TO GET SOME
CLARIFICATION FROM COUNCILOR
NOVICK. SO WHEN YOU SAY IN THE
COMMUNITY, ARE YOU TALKING
ABOUT WITHIN THE LATINO
COMMUNITY, SINCE YOU'RE SAYING
THAT FOLKS IN DISTRICT THREE IN
THE LAURELHURST NEIGHBORHOOD
ARE NOT FOR IT? WHAT IS THE
INTENTION OF THE CHANGE NOW.
>> MAY I RESPOND?
>> YES, SIR.
>> I THINK THAT SINCE WE'RE THE
PORTLAND CITY COUNCIL, WE SAY
IN THE COMMUNITY, WE MEAN THE
ENTIRE COMMUNITY OF THE CITY OF
PORTLAND. AND I WOULD ALSO NOTE,
IF IT MATTERS, THAT WE HAD A
LETTER THIS WEEK OBJECTING TO
THE PROCESS FOR THIS, ALTHOUGH
NOT THE NAME CHANGE FROM THE
CRESTON KENILWORTH NEIGHBORHOOD,
NOT FROM THE LAURELHURST
NEIGHBORHOOD. I THINK THAT I
THINK THAT THE COMMUNITY IS THE
ENTIRE COMMUNITY OF PORTLAND,
NOT JUST PEOPLE THAT SOME
COUNCILORS HAPPEN TO HAVE
TALKED TO.
>> YEAH, THAT'S FAIR. I, I
UNDERSTAND THAT, I THINK. YEAH,
THIS IS A TOUGH ONE. I
UNDERSTAND WHY THERE ARE TIMES
WHERE THIS COUNCIL HAS
CIRCUMVENTED PROCESS, BECAUSE I
DO THINK WE HAVE A TENDENCY TO
DUE PROCESS FOR THIS PROCESS AT
TIMES. AND THIS IS VERY PAINFUL
SPECIFICALLY FOR THE LATINO
COMMUNITY. SO WE'RE HAVING A
BIT OF A DIFFERENT REACTION TO
IT RIGHT NOW. AND. HONESTLY, I
THINK SOME OF THE COMMENTS
ABOUT CHANGING IT BACK TO 39TH
ARE ALSO AN ERASURE OF WHAT WAS
DONE WITH THE ORIGINAL NAME
CHANGE. AND SO I JUST WANT TO
NAME THAT HERE. AS A SOUTH
AMERICAN IMMIGRANT ON THIS
COUNCIL, AS OUR COMMUNITIES ARE
BEING TARGETED AND WE ARE BEING
FORCED TO HIDE AND NOT BE SEEN,
NOT GO TO WORK FOR POTENTIALLY
BEING TARGETED BY IMMIGRATION
ENFORCEMENT, THAT I THINK WE
ARE BEING TOLD TO HIDE, NOT BE
A PART OF THE PUBLIC, NOT BE
SEEN IN MANY WAYS. AND SO WE
ARE NOT A HUGE MAJORITY IN
DISTRICT THREE. DISTRICT THREE,
LIKE THE REST OF THE CITY, IS
VAST MAJORITY WHITE
NONIMMIGRANT. BUT THERE ARE
LATINOS IN DISTRICT THREE TWO,
AND THIS IS UNIQUELY PAINFUL
FOR US. SO I GUESS I JUST WANT
TO NAME THAT AS WE'RE
PROCEEDING WITH THIS DISCUSSION
ABOUT WHEN WE SAY WHO THE
MAJORITY IS, THIS CITY IS ALSO
MAJORITY WHITE, AND THEY DON'T
HAVE THE TIES TO THAT COMMUNITY
THAT'S ACTIVELY BEING HARMED.
AND, AND YEAH, SORRY, I'M A
LITTLE SICK TODAY, SO I'M NOT
BEING AS ELOQUENT AS I WANT TO
BE, BUT I HOPE THAT I'M JUST
LIKE NAMING THE THE TENSION AS
WE'RE HAVING THAT DISCUSSION
MOVING FORWARD.
>> THANK YOU. COUNCILOR MORILLO
COLLEAGUES, I WOULD LIKE TO
MOVE THIS TOWARDS A VOTE,
PLEASE. COLLEAGUES WHO ARE IN
THE QUEUE HAVE EACH SPOKEN A
NUMBER OF TIMES. COUNCILOR
NOVICK WE STILL HAVE YOUR OPEN
AMENDMENT OR ARE WE WITHDRAWING
THAT?
>> I'M I'M WITHDRAWING THAT AND
ASK MY CHIEF OF STAFF TO
QUICKLY WRITE UP THE REVISED
AMENDMENT THAT TALKS ABOUT
SUPPORT RATHER THAN CONSENSUS.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH,
COUNCILOR SMITH.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT.
I WAS JUST GOING TO CALL THE
QUESTION.
>> GOTCHA. THANK YOU.
>> POINT OF INFORMATION. POINT
OF INFORMATION.
>> COUNCILOR AVALOS.
>> IT SOUNDS LIKE WE HAVE TWO
AMENDMENTS THAT ARE BEING
CRAFTED. CAN I JUST CONFIRM OUR
COUNCILOR NOVICK AND COUNCILOR?
KOYAMA LANE. ARE YOU WORKING ON
GETTING US SOMETHING? YES. OKAY.
SO IS IT THAT WE JUST NEED TO
PAUSE UNTIL THOSE ARE READY?
LIKE FIVE MINUTES.
>> COUNCIL PRESIDENT.
>> COUNCILOR PIRTLE-GUINEY.
>> IN THE QUEUE TO PROPOSE THAT
WE MOVE THIS UNTIL AFTER THE
NEXT ITEM ON THE AGENDA, AND
HOPE THAT THE TIME OF THE NEXT
ITEM GIVES US TIME TO GET THOSE
TWO AMENDMENTS. NOT BECAUSE I
WANT TO DELAY THIS
UNNECESSARILY, BUT BECAUSE I
THINK WE HAVE SOME FOLKS WHO
ARE HOPING TO HAVE AN
OPPORTUNITY, AND I DON'T WANT
TO DELAY OUR MEETING STALLING.
>> SECOND.
>> I AGREE. OKAY. THEN I AM
GOING TO ASK THAT WE MOVE. I
DON'T PROCEDURALLY KNOW HOW TO
DO THIS. WE JUST MOVED TO THE
NEXT ITEM AND COME BACK TO THIS.
HOW DO I DO THIS?
>> I THINK YOU HAVE THE OPTION,
WITHOUT OBJECTION FROM THE REST
OF COUNCIL TO JUST PAUSE OR
PAUSE THIS ITEM AND THEN COME
BACK.
>> TO IT.
>> WE'RE GOING TO PAUSE THIS
ITEM SO COUNCILORS CAN GET
ADDITIONAL WORK DONE. AND WE'RE
GOING TO MOVE TO ITEM. 13,
WHICH IS DOCUMENT 2026-270. AND
WE'LL COME BACK TO THIS ONE.
>> EXCEPT THE FUTURE OF LARGE,
LARGE SCALE PERFORMING ARTS
RECOMMENDATIONS TO ADVANCE A
NEW BROADWAY CAPABLE VENUE AS
PART OF THE PROPOSED PERFORMING
ARTS AND CULTURE CENTER AT
PORTLAND STATE UNIVERSITY, AND
INITIATE PLANNING FOR THE
FUTURE OF THE KELLER AUDITORIUM.
>> THANK YOU COLLEAGUES, THIS
IS A CONTINUED FIRST, THIS IS A
RESOLUTION WE ARE CONTINUING
FROM LAST WEEK WHERE WE HEARD
53 PIECES OF TESTIMONY. WE ARE
NOW INTO A POSITION WHERE WE
HAVE TECHNICAL AND CLARIFYING
QUESTIONS OR COUNCIL DISCUSSION.
IS THERE ANY FOLKS FEEL FREE TO
JUMP INTO THE QUEUE. ACTUALLY,
I HAVE A COUPLE OF TECHNICAL OR
CLARIFYING QUESTIONS AND I'M
HOPING THAT. DONNIE OR SUE POCK
ARE AVAILABLE TO COME ON UP.
THERE. SUE. HI, SUE.
>> DONNIE.
>> THANK YOU. AND SUE, MAYBE
YOU ARE ABLE TO ANSWER THIS
FIRST ONE. AND ALSO IN THE
PROCESS OF ME TALKING, WE'LL
GIVE DONNIE A FEW MINUTES TO
WALK IN. BUT IN RESPONSE TO
SOME OF THE TESTIMONY THAT I
HEARD LAST WEEK, THERE WAS A.
THERE WAS A LITTLE. THERE WAS
SOME. THERE WAS A LACK OF
CLARITY ON WHETHER OR NOT THE
NEW PERFORMING ARTS AND CULTURE
CENTER WILL BE A CITY OWNED
ASSET. CAN YOU CONFIRM THAT
WHATEVER GETS BUILT, WHERE IT
GETS BUILT, THIS WILL CONTINUE
TO BE A CITY OWNED ASSET AND
WILL HAVE THE SAME SHARE OF,
YOU KNOW, REVENUE AS IT DOES
CURRENTLY WITH THE OTHER FIVE
BUILDINGS.
>> FOR THE RECORD, I'M SUE PARK.
MY UNDERSTANDING IS THAT IT
WOULD BE A CITY OWNED ASSET AS
TO WHO OPERATES IT AND WHAT
WOULD BE KIND OF THE BUSINESS
PLAN OR REVENUE SHARE. NONE OF
THAT HAS BEEN DETERMINED AT
THIS POINT. WE NEED A DECISION
FIRST, AND THEN WE CAN MOVE ON
TO THINK THROUGH THOSE VERY
IMPORTANT DETAILS.
>> AND TO THAT EXACT SPECIFIC
END, THE RFP FOR MANAGEMENT OF
THE OF THE P5 GOES OUT TODAY. I
UNDERSTAND, OR AT LEAST THIS
WEEK AND HOPEFULLY AT SOME
POINT DOES THE STRUCTURE
IMAGINED IN THE RFP GIVE US
SPACE TO FOLD IN A PROPOSED NEW
THEATER INTO THE P5 UMBRELLA?
>> THE CURRENT THE RFP, THE WAY
IT'S WRITTEN NOW IS JUST FOR
THE CURRENT FIVE VENUES AS A
PART OF PORTLAND FIVE, IT WILL
MAKE IT CLEAR THAT PSU IS NOT
INCLUDED, AND THAT WOULD HAVE
TO BE A SEPARATE PROCESS. AND
WE WOULD NEED TO CONSIDER,
AGAIN WHO'S OPERATING AND WHAT
IS THE OPERATING MODEL TO. AND
A FUTURE RFP POTENTIALLY.
>> OKAY.
>> AND THEN ONE OTHER QUESTION
I HAD IN RESPONSE TO PUBLIC
TESTIMONY THAT WE HEARD LAST
WEEK WAS WHAT. AND YOU MAY NOT
BE ABLE TO ANSWER THIS DIRECTLY,
BUT WHAT WAS THE CITY'S
ASSESSMENT OF THE SEISMIC RISK
OF THE KELLER. WE HEARD
CONFLICTING THINGS LAST WEEK.
>> YEAH.
>> SO THE CITY COMMISSIONED A
STUDY IN 2020, MILLER
CONSULTING ENGINEERS, AND THEIR
CONCLUSION WAS THAT KELLER
AUDITORIUM WOULD NOT WITHSTAND
A MAJOR EARTHQUAKE. IN
TESTIMONY, WE DID HEAR FROM
OTHERS WHO WERE A PART OF THE
HALPRIN PROPOSAL AND CONCEPTING.
OTHERWISE, TO OUR KNOWLEDGE.
THAT WAS NOT A FULL STRUCTURAL
ANALYSIS OF THE KELLER BY A
LICENSED STRUCTURAL ENGINEER.
AND THE ONLY ONE OF THAT KIND
WAS WHAT WAS CONDUCTED AND
RECOGNIZED BY THE CITY IN 2020.
>> THANK YOU COLLEAGUES. GO
AHEAD AND JUMP IN THE QUEUE FOR
ANY TECHNICAL OR CLARIFYING
QUESTIONS OR DISCUSSION BROADLY.
COUNCILOR RYAN, KICK US OFF.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT.
QUESTIONS ABOUT THE CITY'S
FINANCIAL RESPONSIBILITY. IT
HASN'T BEEN VERY CLEAR. IS IT
44 MILLION?
>> THE CITY HAS NOT MADE A
COMMITMENT AT THIS TIME TO THE
44 MILLION THAT WAS POSED.
>> OKAY. SO WE'RE WE'RE
DISCUSSING A RESOLUTION THAT
DOESN'T HAVE A FINANCIAL
COMMITMENT.
>> THERE ARE NO FINANCIAL
COMMITMENTS. THE RESOLUTION
GREENLIGHTS FINANCIAL PLANNING
AND GETTING CLARITY ON THE
ROLES AND RESPONSIBILITIES OF
PSU IN THE CITY.
>> OKAY, IT'S BEEN MURKY AT
BEST. SO SOMETIMES I HEAR THAT
WE ARE, SOMETIMES I DON'T. IF
IN FACT WE DID, WE ARE GOING TO
COMMIT. I HEARD THAT FROM PSU
ITSELF. WHEN DOES PSU EXPECT
THAT PAYMENT? MAYBE SOMEONE
FROM PSU WHO HAS THAT
EXPECTATION? HI SARAH COULD
COME UP AND SAY WHAT THAT
ANSWER IS.
>> RIGHT?
>> SO SHE WAS WALKING.
>> YEAH.
>> WE JUST NEED THIS TO BE
TRANSPARENT.
>> HI, SIR. HI, COUNCILOR RYAN,
THIS IS SARAH SCHWARTZ, PSU
PRESIDENT, PSU FOUNDATION
PRESIDENT AND LEAD FOR THE
PROJECT. FOR THE RECORD. SO
THIS THIS RESOLUTION SIMPLY
ALLOWS US TO GET IN THE ROOM
AND START TO FIGURE OUT HOW THE
FINANCIAL STACK WILL COME
TOGETHER BETWEEN PSU AND THE
CITY. AT THIS STAGE, WE HAVE
FROM THE LAST TWO AND A HALF
YEARS, SEVERAL PARTNERS WHO
HAVE PUT RESOURCES FORWARD AND
MADE COMMITMENTS. SO WE DO NEED,
AT SOME POINT VERY SOON, SOME
LEVEL OF COMMITMENT FROM THE
CITY THAT THEY ARE FULLY IN ON
THE PROJECT, WHICH INCLUDES
SOME IDENTIFICATION OF RESOURCE
TOWARDS THE PROJECT,
SPECIFICALLY TOWARDS THE
PROJECT THAT WILL BE OWNED BY
THE CITY OF PORTLAND, WHICH IS
THE 3000 SEAT VENUE.
>> I APPRECIATE BEING CLEAR
ABOUT THAT. SO THERE IS GOING
TO BE A FINANCIAL COMMITMENT.
DO YOU SEE A AYE, MORILLO
YOU'RE HERE, MAYBE YOU HAVE
SOME SENSE OF WHERE THE SOURCE
IS FOR THAT. AYE, MORILLO CFO
BIERY.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR. FOR
THE RECORD, I'M NOT CITY
ADMINISTRATOR RAYMOND LEACH
CHIEF FINANCIAL OFFICER JONAS
BIERY SITTING IN FOR THE CA. I
WOULD JUST ACKNOWLEDGE AS AS
WAS MENTIONED, IT'S A DYNAMIC
SITUATION WITH LOTS OF POSSIBLE
PATHWAYS. AND SO IT JUST
REMAINS, I THINK, AN ACTIVE
CONVERSATION TO IDENTIFY HOW
THAT BOTH THE BROADER COST
SHARE AND THE CITY OBLIGATION
WILL ULTIMATELY PLAY OUT.
>> OKAY. SO IN SUMMARY, WE KNOW
THERE'S GOING TO BE A FINANCIAL
COMMITMENT. WE KNOW THAT IT'S
GOING TO BE DUE SOONER THAN
LATER AND WE DON'T HAVE A
SOURCE IDENTIFIED. OKAY, THANKS.
ANOTHER TECHNICAL QUESTION IS
ABOUT THE TRAFFIC STUDIES. DID
WE DO A TRAFFIC STUDY ON
SOUTHWEST THIRD IN FRONT OF THE
KELLER BETWEEN THE FOUNTAIN AND
THE. YEAH. DID WE DO A STUDY ON
WHAT I THINK A LOT OF PEOPLE
ENVISIONED IS FOR THAT TO NOT
BE A STREET, BUT THAT TO BE AN
OPEN PLAZA THAT WOULD ALLOW
MORE FLEXIBILITY AS WE ENVISION
A REMODELED AND RESTORED,
HISTORICALLY RESTORED KELLER.
>> THE THE STUDY THAT WE DID
ASKED FOR THREE SCENARIOS SINCE
WE WERE AT THAT POINT
CONSIDERING A. TWO VENUE
STRATEGY. SO IT WAS RENOVATED.
KELLER. NEW SITE AT PSU OR BOTH
OPERATING SIMULTANEOUSLY. AND
SO THAT WAS WHAT WAS REQUESTED.
AND THERE WERE NO FATAL FLAWS
FOR ANY OF THOSE SCENARIOS AS
TO. KIND OF A DEEPER, DETAILED
STUDY ON THE CLOSURE OF THIRD
AVENUE. I WOULD HAVE TO GET
BACK TO YOU ON THAT. I KNOW
THAT WAS SOMETHING THAT WAS IN
CONVERSATION. I DON'T HAVE THE
DETAILS OR THE SPECIFICS ON
WHAT WAS CONCLUDED REGARDING
THAT SCENARIO.
>> THANK YOU. SO THERE WASN'T A
TRAFFIC STUDY WITH THAT
SPECIFIC VISION IN MIND. WHAT
ABOUT ON SOUTHWEST LINCOLN,
WHERE IT'S ONE LANE AND THEN
YOU HAVE THE LIGHT RAIL IN THE
MIDDLE? WAS THERE A TRAFFIC
STUDY THAT LOOKED AT THE IMPACT
OF THE TRAFFIC GOING TO THE
PERFORMANCES, GOING TO THE
HOTEL, UP TO MAYBE 4000 PEOPLE
ON THAT ONE LANE ROAD? WHAT WAS
THAT? WHAT WAS THE CONCLUSION
OF THAT TRAFFIC STUDY?
>> I'D HAVE TO LOOK AT THE THE
TECHNICAL REPORT. I'M SORRY. I
I'M NOT SO FAMILIAR WITH THE
THE DETAILS AND THE TECHNICAL.
THIS IS NOT MY AREA OF
EXPERTISE.
>> THESE ARE QUESTIONS I'VE
BEEN ASKING FOR LIKE 3 OR 4
YEARS. SO I JUST WANT SOME
ANSWERS SOMEDAY. THANK YOU.
>> BE HAPPY TO SHARE WITH YOU
THE FULL TRAFFIC STUDY.
>> THANK YOU COUNCILMEMBER.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR RYAN.
COUNCILOR GREEN.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT.
SO WE HEARD SOME TESTIMONY LAST
WEEK ON THE NEED TO UPGRADE THE
PERFORMING SORT OF ARTS
CURRICULUM, YOU KNOW, CAPACITY
AT PORTLAND STATE. I'VE DONE
THE TOUR. IT'S WOEFULLY
INADEQUATE FOR THOSE STUDENTS.
SO I GUESS MY QUESTION IS THE
RESOLUTION THAT WE'RE
CONTEMPLATING IS ABOUT THE CITY
OF PORTLAND DOING A PERFORMING
ARTS VENUE. IF IF THE CITY DID
NOT DO THAT, WOULD THOSE
STUDENTS STILL GET AN UPGRADED
SET OF FACILITIES TO DO THEIR
THEIR WORK IN?
>> I WOULD ANSWER THAT QUESTION
TO SAY THAT RIGHT NOW WE ARE
FULLY FOCUSED ON THE VISION
THAT WE'VE PRESENTED TO YOU.
AND OF COURSE, THERE CAN BE
SCENARIO PLANNING THAT CAN
HAPPEN IF IN FACT THERE'S A
CHANGE IN THE DIRECTION. BUT WE
ARE FULLY FORWARD WITH THE
KELLER, EXCUSE ME, WITH THE
3000 SEAT VENUE BEING A PART OF
THE PROJECT AT THIS TIME.
>> OKAY. SO. IT'S NOT SUPER
CLEAR, BUT.
>> WELL, IF I CAN RESTATE THAT,
I APOLOGIZE. THE HIGHEST AND
BEST USE OF THE 4.25 ACRES IS
HAVING THE 3000 SEAT VENUE AT
THE HEART OF A LARGER CULTURAL
AND ACADEMIC SETTING. SO WE
WOULD, IN FACT, LOVE OVER TIME
TO HAVE ALL THE APPROPRIATE
SPACES FOR OUR STUDENTS. BUT AT
THIS MOMENT IN TIME, THIS
PARTICULAR VISION MAKES SENSE
AS HIGHEST AND BEST USE FOR
THAT SET OF ACREAGE THAT WE
HAVE ON CAMPUS.
>> OKAY, THANKS FOR CLARIFYING
ON THAT. SO I JUST WANT TO MAKE
SURE THAT WE KNOW WHAT WE'RE
TALKING ABOUT. THE PUBLIC KNOWS
WHAT WE'RE TALKING ABOUT. SO
WE'RE CONTEMPLATING A
RESOLUTION TO MOVE US DOWN A
PATH THAT WILL GO TOWARDS A
FINANCIAL COMMITMENT. AND
THAT'S ABOUT A PERFORMING ARTS
VENUE. AND SO ALL THE TESTIMONY
WE HEARD ABOUT THE STUDENTS IS
ANCILLARY TO THAT.
>> CORRECT. OKAY. REALLY,
WHAT'S BEFORE THE COUNCIL IS
THE DETERMINATION AROUND
BUILDING THE 3000 SEAT VENUE ON
THE PSU LAND.
>> BUT IF BUT IF THE CITY
COUNCIL CHOSE NOT TO GO DOWN
THIS ROAD, IT WOULDN'T IT
WOULDN'T BE BECAUSE THE CITY
COUNCIL MADE A DECISION WHY
THOSE STUDENTS WOULDN'T GET
THOSE UPGRADES. IT'D BE
PORTLAND STATE UNIVERSITY,
RIGHT?
>> CORRECT. THEN IT WOULD BE
BACK TO US TO MAKE
DETERMINATIONS FROM THERE.
>> THANK YOU. AND I MEANT TO
START MY TIMER. COUNCIL
PRESIDENT, I APOLOGIZE.
>> I STARTED BEFORE YOU.
>> YEAH, I KNOW YOU DID. CFO
BIERY. I DON'T KNOW IF YOU KNOW
THIS ANSWER OFF THE TOP OF YOUR
HEAD. AND IF YOU DON'T, THAT'S
OKAY. WE CAN TRY TO GET IT INTO
THE CONVERSATION, BUT I RECALL
WHEN WE WERE THINKING THROUGH
THE FINANCIAL STABILITY WORK
AND WE WERE TRYING TO
UNDERSTAND OUR COST CENTERS,
THE INTERNAL SERVICE FUND. AND
THE RATE STRUCTURE THAT SORT OF
RECOVER THOSE COSTS. SOME OF
THAT'S DRIVEN BY THE VANPORT
BUILDING AND THE DEBT SERVICE
ON THAT. DO YOU HAVE A SENSE OF
SCALE ON THAT?
>> YEAH. COUNCILOR, I DON'T
KNOW, OFF THE TOP OF MY HEAD
WHAT THAT SENSE OF SCALE IS,
THAT WE CAN WORK WITH THE TEAM
TO GET YOU SPECIFICALLY THOSE
AMOUNTS AND HOW THEY FACTOR
THROUGH THOSE FACILITIES
RELATED INTERAGENCY RATES.
>> THANK YOU. AND I APOLOGIZE
FOR PUTTING YOU ON THE SPOT
LIKE THAT. IT'S A YOU DON'T
WANT TO GIVE AN IMPRECISE
ANSWER, BUT THE REASON I BRING
IT UP IS BECAUSE TO COUNCILOR
RYAN'S QUESTIONS, IF WE GO DOWN
THIS ROAD AND THEN WE ENDED UP
GETTING INTO THE SAME FINANCIAL
ARRANGEMENT THAT WE CURRENTLY
HAVE WITH THE VANPORT BUILDING,
THAT'S GOING TO DRIVE AN
INCREASE IN OUR INTERNAL
SERVICE COSTS. AND SO UNLESS WE
ARE ABLE TO IDENTIFY A SPECIFIC
SOURCE OF FUNDS THAT DOESN'T DO
THAT, WE JUST HAVE TO RECOGNIZE
THAT THIS WOULD BE A DECISION
THAT RAISES THE OVERALL COST
ACROSS ALL OF OUR BUREAUS. AND
I KNOW I'M RUNNING OUT OF TIME.
SO I THINK THE LAST QUESTION I
HAVE ACTUALLY FOR THE CITY
ATTORNEY IS THAT ONE OF THE
THINGS I'VE BEEN THINKING A LOT
ABOUT IS THE DIVISION OF POWER
BETWEEN THE EXECUTIVE AND THE
THE COUNCIL. AND WHEN WE ADOPT
A RESOLUTION LIKE THIS IN THE
CITY ATTORNEY'S VIEW, WOULD IT
THEN EMPOWER THE EXECUTIVE TO
START SIGNING CONTRACTS AND
NEGOTIATING ON BEHALF OF THE
CITY THAT WOULD THEN BIND THE
CITY IN SOME KIND OF SENSE?
THAT'S THE QUESTION I HAVE.
>> I THINK.
>> GENERALLY THE CITY
ADMINISTRATOR IS EMPOWERED TO
SIGN CONTRACTS. AS LONG AS
THERE'S A BUDGET ALLOCATION FOR
IT. THAT'S WHAT'S SPECIFIED IN
THE CHARTER. SO IF IF THERE'S
NOT A IF IT'S NOT BUDGETED FOR,
THEN THEY'RE NOT GOING TO BE
ABLE TO SIGN A CONTRACT. IS
THAT IS THAT ANSWER YOUR
QUESTION OR. I MEAN.
>> IT DOES, BECAUSE I THINK THE
THING I'M CONCERNED ABOUT, LIKE
WE RECENTLY SIGNED A CONTRACT
FOR THE US TENNIS ASSOCIATION,
WHICH I KNOW THAT THERE'S A
DIFFERENCE OF OPINION ON THAT
AT THIS DAIS, BUT THAT THAT'S A
25 YEAR CONTRACT AND WE
APPROVED A ONE YEAR BUDGET. AND
SO I'M STARTING TO GET NERVOUS
ABOUT WHAT IS THE LENGTH OF
TIME HAVE WE FAILED TO SORT OF
CLARIFY WHAT THAT SCOPE AND
BOUNDARY IS? WHAT I DON'T WANT
TO HAPPEN HERE IS, IS ALL OF
THE BACKGROUND INFORMATION HAS
BEEN SAID IS SORT OF COUCHED IN
TERMS OF, DON'T WORRY, THIS
DOES NOT COMMIT THE CITY TO
ANYTHING FINANCIALLY. YOU'LL
ALWAYS HAVE A CHOICE. BUT IF WE
TAKE THIS STEP, ARE WE THEN
GOING TO BE PRESENTED WITH A NO
CHOICE SCENARIO WHERE IT'S LIKE,
WELL, YOU GUYS ALREADY SAID YES
BY A RESOLUTION, SO NOW PAY FOR
IT. LIKE THAT'S WHAT I'M
WORRIED ABOUT. AND I WANT TO
MAKE SURE THAT THAT'S.
>> ON THE.
>> RECORD NOW, BECAUSE IT'S NOT
$44 MILLION, IT'S $440 MILLION
BECAUSE THE 44 IS 10%. THAT'S
THE 10% KITTY UP FRONT. AND
THAT'S WHAT I'VE GOTTEN FROM MY
CONVERSATIONS AS WELL. AND SO
IF WE'RE GOING TO GO DOWN THIS
ROAD OF COMMITTING OURSELVES TO
$440 MILLION WITH NO FUNDING
SOURCE, WE JUST NEED TO BE
CRYSTAL CLEAR ABOUT WHAT THAT
MEANS AND WHAT OUR TRADE OFFS
ARE. SO I'LL LEAVE IT THERE FOR
NOW.
>> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH,
COUNCILOR GREEN. COUNCILOR
PIRTLE-GUINEY.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT
SUE, I WANT TO ASK A QUICK
QUESTION BECAUSE YOU SAID
SOMETHING IN YOUR CONVERSATION
WITH COUNCILOR DUNPHY THAT WAS
CURIOUS TO ME. SO I UNDERSTAND
FROM THE PREVIOUS CONVERSATIONS
WE HAD IN COMMITTEE AND FROM
THE DIALOG THAT YOU HAD WITH
THE COUNCIL COUNCIL PRESIDENT,
THAT THE MOVING FORWARD WITH
CONVERSATIONS AROUND A CITY
OWNED VENUE ON THE PSU CAMPUS
WOULD BE SEPARATE FROM OUR FIVE
VENUES. BUT IS THERE ANYTHING
IN THE RFP THAT'S ON THE TABLE
RIGHT NOW FOR THE OPERATION OF
THOSE VENUES OR IN THE
RESOLUTION THAT WE'RE MOVING
FORWARD TODAY THAT WOULD
PREVENT US FROM OPERATING A
FUTURE VENUE OWNED BY THE CITY
AND LOCATED ON THE PSU CAMPUS,
ALONGSIDE OUR FIVE VENUES. IF A
FUTURE CITY COUNCIL OR
ADMINISTRATION DECIDED THAT
THAT WAS THE BEST CHOICE FOR
THE CITY.
>> THE RFP DOES NOT LIMIT THAT
POSSIBILITY.
>> OKAY? NOR DOES WHAT WE'RE
CONSIDERING TODAY. SO WE'RE
ESSENTIALLY LEAVING THAT OPEN.
WE'RE NOT BINDING OURSELVES TO
THAT. WE'RE ALSO NOT BINDING
OURSELVES AWAY FROM THAT. OKAY.
I THINK THAT'S IMPORTANT. I
THINK THESE CONVERSATIONS ABOUT
COST ARE IMPORTANT. COLLEAGUES,
WE ARE BEING ASKED HOW WE WANT
TO MOVE FORWARD FOR THE ARTS IN
OUR COMMUNITY. AND I JUST WOULD
ASK THAT WE FIGURE OUT A WAY
THAT WE CAN TAKE THIS STEP IN A
WAY THAT IS COMFORTABLE FOR
FOLKS. IF WE NEED TO GET SOME
THINGS ON THE RECORD, LET'S
MAKE SURE WE DO THAT. BUT LET'S
MOVE FORWARD. WE NEED TO HAVE A
VENUE THAT CAN OPERATE THESE
LARGE SCALE PRODUCTIONS. WE
NEED TO DO SO IN A WAY THAT
DOESN'T CREATE A BREAK IN
OPERATIONS, WHICH WOULD BE
NEGATIVE FOR OUR COMMUNITY FOR
A LOT OF DIFFERENT REASONS.
FIRST AND FOREMOST, THE JOBS,
BUT ALSO THE ACCESS TO CULTURE
AND THE ARTS. AND I
>> I THINK THIS GIVES US THE
STEP TO START TO DO THAT. SO I
HOPE WE TAKE THAT SERIOUSLY. IT
GIVES US THE STEP TO START TO
DO THAT WHILE ALSO CONTINUING
TO INVEST IN THE KELLER. AND I
HOPE WE CAN FIND A WAY TO MOVE
FORWARD TODAY WITHOUT TOO MUCH
DELAY. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. COUNCILOR.
PIRTLE-GUINEY. COUNCILOR.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT.
I WANT TO GO BACK TO THE COST
OF THIS AND SOMETHING THAT
COUNCILOR GREEN SAID IN TERMS
OF THE ENTIRE COST OF THIS
PARTICULAR THAT THE BUY IN
WOULD BE 440 MILLION FROM THE
CITY OF PORTLAND. IS THIS WHAT
IT IS? IT IS BINDING US TO.
>> THE ESTIMATED COST FOR THE
3000 SEATER AT PSU IS 447
MILLION. THAT IS NOT TO SAY
THAT THE CITY WOULD BE ON THE
HOOK FOR THE ENTIRE AMOUNT. THE
HOPE IS WITH THIS RESOLUTION
THAT THERE CAN BE FURTHER WORK
DONE IN TERMS OF FINANCIAL
PLANNING AND DEVELOPING A
CAPITAL STACK TO UNDERSTAND
WHAT THE FUNDING SOURCES ARE.
THE CITY CERTAINLY WILL NEED TO
COMMIT, BUT THE THINKING IS
THERE WOULD BE DIVERSIFIED
SOURCES.
>> SO LET ME TELL YOU WHAT MY
CONCERN IS. I WAS ON THE ARTS
COMMITTEE WHEN THIS CAME UP,
AND I WANTED TO FIGURE OUT A
PATHWAY SO THAT THE KELLER
COULD GET DONE, BECAUSE WE
ACTUALLY OWN THAT RIGHT NOW,
WE'RE NOT BUILDING A STAGE. WE
ALREADY HAVE A STAGE THAT WE
CAN GO FORWARD WITH. THE OTHER
PIECE THAT I THAT I'M HAVING A
DUAL CONVERSATION WITH MYSELF
ABOUT IS THAT WE HAVE A
CONTRACT THAT WE HAVE TO GET
DONE WITH, WITH THE BLAZERS.
AND THAT IS ANOTHER MULTI
HUNDRED MILLION DOLLAR DEAL.
AND I'M TRYING TO FIGURE OUT
WHERE WE GET ALL THIS MONEY
FROM. UNLESS THERE'S SOME MONEY
UNDER THE THE PARK BENCHES THAT
I DON'T KNOW ABOUT, IT'S NOT
CLEAR TO ME. IN TERMS OF
GETTING A CAPITAL. I WOULD
THINK THAT YOU WOULD HAVE THE
CAPITAL STACK FIGURED OUT
BEFORE YOU GOT A RESOLUTION
FROM US. WHY NOT GO GET A
CAPITAL THAT CAN TELL ME WHERE
YOU'RE GETTING THE MONEY FROM
BEFORE YOU'RE ASKING ME TO TO
VOTE BLINDLY ON SOMETHING THAT
I DON'T SEE A PATHWAY. I DON'T
SEE A PATHWAY. HOW WE DO THIS.
AND I NEEDED TO EXPLAIN FROM
OUR CFO TO THE TO THE FOLKS WHO
BROUGHT IT HERE, HOW WE'RE
GOING TO PAY FOR THIS IF WE
WANT TO JUST DO A RESOLUTION TO
SAY, OH, YEAH, WE'RE THINKING
ABOUT IT, AND THAT'S WHAT WE'RE
GOING TO DO. BUT THIS
RESOLUTION BINDS US TO PAY FOR
THIS. RIGHT NOW.
>> IT DOES NOT.
>> BUT BUT IN ESSENCE, IT DOES.
IT'S SAYING THAT WE'RE WE'RE
GOING TO GO FORWARD. AND THEN
ONCE WE FIND OUT WHAT THE STACK
LOOKS LIKE, THEN WE WE'RE DOING
THINGS BACKWARDS TO ME.
>> IF I MAY, COUNCILOR SMITH,
IF I COULD JUST JUMP IN FOR A
QUICK MOMENT. SO THREE YEARS
AGO, WHEN THE CITY ASKED FOR A
PROPOSAL FOR A NEW VENUE AS A
CONTEMPLATION POINT, WE DID DO
SIGNIFICANT WORK ON THE PSU
SIDE TO START TO DEVELOP WHAT A
CAPITAL STACK COULD LOOK LIKE,
RIGHT OVER THE LAST TWO AND A
HALF YEARS, WITH CHANGES IN
COUNCIL AND A WHOLE VARIETY OF
THINGS, ANY CONVERSATIONS THAT
WE MIGHT HAVE BEEN ABLE TO HAVE
WITH ANY OF THE FINANCIAL FOLKS
ACROSS THE CITY, THOSE HAVE
BEEN PUT ON HOLD. WE HAVE NOT
HAD ANY ACCESS TO SPEAK WITH
PEOPLE TO ACTUALLY SAY, HERE
ARE THE 27 THINGS THAT WE HAVE
ON OUR LIST THAT WE THINK COULD
BE POSSIBILITIES. NOT ALL OF
THEM ARE GOING TO BE FROM THE
CITY. THEY COME FROM A VARIETY
OF SOURCES. WHAT THIS
RESOLUTION DOES, FROM OUR
PERSPECTIVE IS FINALLY ALLOWS
THAT CONVERSATION TO HAPPEN. WE
ARE NOT HERE TRYING TO HOODWINK
YOU INTO ANY SORT OF LONG TERM
COMMITMENT. THIS IS TO TAKE
THAT NEXT STEP THAT WE'VE
REALLY BEEN WAITING FOR, FOR
QUITE A LONG TIME, TO SIT IN A
ROOM AND SAY OF THIS LIST OF
ITEMS AND OF THE THINGS THAT,
YOU KNOW, WHAT'S OUR PATH
FORWARD. AND AGAIN, IT WILL NOT
RELY SOLELY ON CITY ASSETS AND
CITY DOLLARS. MANY
MUNICIPALITIES ARE ABLE TO PUT
TOGETHER CREATIVE PATHS FORWARD.
WE THINK PORTLAND HAS A REAL
SHOT AT BEING ABLE TO DO THAT,
TOO, BUT WE NEED TO BE ABLE TO
DO THAT WITH THE PARTNERS AT
THE CITY TO FIGURE IT OUT.
>> RIGHT. AND I DON'T THINK
YOU'RE TRYING TO HOODWINK US AT
ALL. I THINK YOU'RE TRYING TO
TO GET US THROUGH THIS
RESOLUTION, MAKE PSU THE
PRIORITY. THAT'S WHAT I THINK
YOU'RE TRYING TO DO WITHOUT
HAVING THE OTHER CAPITAL STACK
TO GO ALONG WITH IT.
>> IF I CAN. ALSO, I'M SORRY
JUST TO ADD IN ON THIS TOO. SO
ALSO OVER THIS COURSE OF TIME,
WE HAVE SECURED THE STATE BONDS
AGAIN PRIMARILY FOR THE PSU
COMPONENT, BUT IT WILL SERVE
ALL OF THE UNDERGIRDING FOR THE
ENTIRE PROJECT. AND EVEN MORE
IMPORTANTLY, WE HAVE $12.5
MILLION IN PHILANTHROPY DONORS
WHO STEPPED FORWARD ALMOST
WITHIN THE FIRST SIX MONTHS OF
THE FIRST ROUND OF CITY COUNCIL
ACTION, WHO WERE VERY
ENTREPRENEURIAL AND SAID THEY
WANTED TO STEP FORWARD, TO SHOW
CONFIDENCE THAT THERE ARE FOLKS
WHO ARE WILLING TO SUPPORT A
PROJECT OF THIS SCALE AND OF
THIS VISION. I AM THE PRIMARY
FUNDRAISER FOR IT. I AM
CONCERNED THAT WE WILL START TO
LOSE DONOR INTEREST IN THIS
PROJECT, AND PERHAPS EVEN DONOR
PHILANTHROPY THAT'S BEEN STATED
TO DATE BECAUSE OF THE
PROTRACTED NATURE OF THE
PROJECT. WHICH IS NOT TO SAY
THAT THIS ISN'T HUGE, AND WE
NEED TO BE VERY DILIGENT IN
STEPPING THROUGH EACH POINT. I
GUESS MY WHAT I WOULD HOPE THAT
WE COULD WALK AWAY FROM TODAY
IS A SENSE OF URGENCY TO MOVE
FORWARD AND ASSESS THIS OUT.
BECAUSE TO COUNCILOR RYAN'S
QUESTION AND OTHERS AND
COUNCILOR GREEN'S. IT MAY BE
THAT AFTER A COUPLE OF MONTHS
OF WORKING TOGETHER, WE MAY
DETERMINE, IN FACT, THAT WE
COME BACK TO YOU AND SAY THE
PATH LOOKS PRETTY DIFFERENT
THAN WHAT WE THOUGHT IT MIGHT
BE. NOW WE'RE GOING A DIFFERENT
DIRECTION. SO PSU AND OUR
DONORS ALSO HAVE A COMPONENT IN
THIS AS WELL TOO. BUT AGAIN,
WE'RE MISSING THE CITY'S VOICE
AT THE TABLE TO ACTUALLY DO THE
FINANCIAL STACK WORK, RIGHT?
>> BECAUSE THEY WANT TO KNOW
THAT THE CITY IS GOING TO COME
IN. AND SO WHILE WE ARE SAYING
IT DOESN'T, IT DOESN'T BIND US
TO THIS, BUT IT REALLY DOES
BIND US TO IT. AND UNTIL WE
FIGURE OUT HOW WE'RE GOING TO
PAY FOR ALL THESE OTHER THINGS
THAT WE HAVE IN THE QUEUE RIGHT
NOW, I'M NOT COMFORTABLE RIGHT
NOW WITH THIS RESOLUTION. I'M
NOT COMFORTABLE WITH THIS AT
ALL. AND I UNDERSTAND YOU'RE
TRYING TO KEEP YOUR YOUR DONORS
TOGETHER, BUT I ALSO KNOW THAT
THERE ARE A LOT OF STUDENTS WHO
ARE NOT GOING TO BE ABLE TO GO
TO SCHOOL AT PSU, BECAUSE THERE
ARE A LOT OF FUNDING THAT
YOU'RE MISSING ON THE OTHER
PUBLIC SIDE. AND SO WHILE KIDS
ARE NOT ALLOWED ARE NOT GOING
TO BE ALLOWED TO GO TO SCHOOL
BECAUSE OF THE FUNDING ISSUES
THAT YOU HAVE ON THE, ON THE ON
THE PUBLIC SIDE, NOT THE
PRIVATE FUNDRAISING SIDE FOR
THIS. IT JUST DOES NOT LOOK
GOOD THAT YOU'RE RAISING ALL
THESE MILLIONS AND GAZILLIONS
OF DOLLARS. AND THEN WE HAVE
STUDENTS WHO ARE NOT GOING TO
BE ABLE TO GO TO SCHOOL. SO
THAT'S A PROBLEM. THAT'S THAT'S
A PUBLIC RELATIONS PROBLEM.
>> LAST YEAR, WE RAISED $45.6
MILLION ALMOST SPECIFICALLY FOR
STUDENT SUCCESS AND STUDENT
SUPPORT AT THE PSU FOUNDATION.
I UNDERSTAND THE OPTICS. I
THINK VERY SIMILAR TO WHAT CITY
COUNCIL IS FACING. WE HAVE TO
BOTH MANAGE VERY CHALLENGING
FINANCIAL SITUATIONS AT THE
SAME TIME OF LOOKING FORWARD
TOWARD BIG VISION AND
INVESTMENT. FORWARD IS ONE WAY
TO ENSURE THAT OUR STUDENTS
WILL HAVE STATE OF THE ART
FACILITIES, THAT WE WILL GROW
ENROLLMENT IN AREAS WHERE WE
ARE ALREADY HAVING LOTS OF
ENROLLMENT GROWTH ACROSS THE
CAMPUS. THE COLLEGE OF THE ARTS
IS A GEM FOR US. WE SEE THIS AS
A TRANSFORMATIONAL OPPORTUNITY
AND A WAY TO DO TWO THINGS AT
ONCE WORK ON OUR FINANCIAL
SUSTAINABILITY AND OUR STUDENT
SUPPORT FOR THE IMMEDIATE
FUTURE OR FOR THE IMMEDIATE.
NOW, I SHOULD SAY, WHILE BEING
VISIONARY AND FORWARD THINKING
FOR OUR STUDENTS OF THE FUTURE,
NOT TO MENTION OUR CITY OF
PORTLAND.
>> AND COUNCILOR.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. WE'RE
PAST FIVE MINUTES. THANK YOU,
COUNCILOR SMITH.
>> COUNCILOR KANAL THANK YOU.
I'LL SAVE MY COMMENT. THINGS
FOR FOR LATER. I THINK THE
QUESTIONS I HAVE ARE REALLY
DERIVED FROM A CONTEXT THAT
THAT COUNCILOR GREENE
REFERENCED, WHICH IS THE TENNIS
CENTER. THAT DOESN'T SOUND LIKE
IT'S RELEVANT TO EVERYBODY, BUT
I WANT TO JUST BE CLEAR THAT ON
MAY 18TH, IN THIS CHAMBER, WE
TOOK A DID A TECHNICAL
AMENDMENT TO EXTEND FUNDING FOR
THE TENNIS CENTER, WHICH WAS
GOING TO EXPIRE JUNE 30TH OF
THIS YEAR TO DECEMBER 31ST OF
THIS YEAR. AND IN THAT, I ASKED
WHETHER OR NOT THAT WOULD
COMMIT US TO A PATH OF
PRIVATIZATION, AND I WAS TOLD,
NO, WE'LL BE. IT'LL COME BACK.
I'LL READ THE TRANSCRIPT IN A
MOMENT. AND THEN I FOUND OUT
YESTERDAY IN THE CHAMBER THAT A
CONTRACT HAS ALREADY BEEN
SIGNED TO TRANSFER CONTROL TO
THE PORTLAND TENNIS CENTER. SO
I AGREE WITH COUNCILOR SMITH'S
ANALYSIS THAT THIS WOULD COMMIT
US. AND SO I THINK THAT WE HAVE
TO HAVE THAT CONVERSATION. BUT
I DON'T THINK IT'S IT'S AND
THAT'S NOT BECAUSE OF ANYTHING
PSU HAS DONE THAT HAS TO DO
WITH THE INTERNAL SIDE WITHIN
THIS CHAMBER AND BETWEEN THE
TWO FLOORS OF THIS BUILDING.
THAT IS MY CONCERN. I JUST WANT
TO BE CLEAR ABOUT THAT. I JUST.
TRANSCRIPT HERE IS AMENDMENT
THREE, TECHNICAL AMENDMENT
THREE. IT TALKS ABOUT MAKING
ABOUT THOUGHTFUL DECISION
MAKING AND IMPLEMENTATION OF
THE POTENTIAL TRANSITION. I'M A
LITTLE CURIOUS AS TO WHY THERE
HASN'T YET BEEN A COUNCIL VOTE
ON TRANSFERRING ANYTHING WITH
US TO. AND THERE ARE SEVERAL
COUNCILORS WHO HAVE EXPRESSED
CONCERN, TREPIDATION, WHATEVER
WORD, HESITATION, LET'S SAY
ABOUT IT. SO I'M CURIOUS HOW
MUCH THIS COMMITS US TO THAT
COURSE OF ACTION WITHOUT A
DEBATE. THAT'S ME ASKING KA LEE
HIS RESPONSE IT DOESN'T COMMIT
YOU TO IT. COUNCIL OFFICIALLY
HAS TO ADOPT THE BUDGET, WHICH
THIS WOULD BE A PART OF IT.
THIS IS JUST AMENDING THE
PORTIONS OF THE MAYOR'S
PROPOSED BUDGET AS IT RELATES
TO THIS WORK. COUNCIL OFFICIAL
WILL MAKE THE DECISION AS IT
RELATES TO THE OVERALL ADOPTED
BUDGET, WHICH THIS MAY BE
INCLUDED AS PART OF YOUR
DELIBERATION WITH THIS
AMENDMENT. AND I ASKED, SO THE
ADOPTED BUDGET IS WHERE THE
DECISION ON TRANSFERRING ON
PRIVATIZING THIS THE PORTLAND
TENNIS CENTER IS MADE, OR IS
THAT A SEPARATE STANDALONE
ORDINANCE? C A LEE IT'S THE
APPROPRIATION OF THE MONEY IS
DONE THROUGH THIS BUDGETING
PROCESS. IF THERE'S
DOCUMENTATION AS IT RELATES TO
THE PRIVATIZATION OF THAT, THAT
WOULD BE DONE SEPARATELY. SO WE
WERE TOLD THAT WE WERE GOING TO
GET A SEPARATE CONVERSATION ON
IT. AND THEN BEHIND OUR BACK,
AND I USE THOSE THOSE WORDS
VERY SPECIFICALLY. IT WAS DONE
AROUND US. I BELIEVE THAT IF WE
WERE TO SUPPORT THIS, THIS
RESOLUTION, WE'RE COMMITTING TO
THE WHOLE PACKAGE. NOW, THAT
MIGHT ONLY BE $44 MILLION, $42
MILLION, NOT THE WHOLE, BECAUSE
I RECOGNIZE THAT THERE'S OTHER
FINANCIAL COMPONENTS THAT ARE
PART OF THIS. BUT I DID WANT TO
ASK THE COUNCIL PRESIDENT IF
YOU COULD REMIND US, HOW MUCH
DID IT COST? WHAT WERE YOU
QUOTED ABOUT MOVING YOUR DESK
ACROSS THE HALL IN YOUR
DISTRICT, IN YOUR CITY HALL
OFFICE?
>> IT WAS ABOUT $24,000.
>> OKAY, SO $24,000 TO MOVE A
DESK THAT A DISTANCE THAT'S
ABOUT FROM HERE TO THE BACK OF
THIS, THIS CHAMBER, THAT'S THE
INTERNAL RATES THAT WE'RE
PAYING, AND THAT'S WHAT'S GOING
TO GO UP IF WE DON'T HAVE
ANOTHER FUNDING SOURCE. SO
THAT'S ALREADY, I WOULD ARGUE,
TOO HIGH. I THINK THAT'S
PROBABLY A CONSENSUS POSITION
HERE. THAT $24,000 TO MOVE A
DESK IS TOO HIGH, BUT IT'S ONE
OF SEVERAL THINGS THAT WE'VE
BEEN QUOTED, THESE EXTREMELY
HIGH AMOUNTS ON HERE. AND, AND
WE AS COUNCILORS HAVE, YOU KNOW,
THE CHARGES ARE LEVIED ON US
JUST THE SAME AS BETWEEN THE
BUREAUS. SO THAT'S A CONCERN
THAT I HAVE. AND I, I DID WANT
TO ASK I REALLY APPRECIATE
COUNCILOR RYAN OUTLINING HIS
THOUGHTS, WHICH HE'S BEEN
BRINGING UP FOR A FEW YEARS. I
ALSO NOTED IN THE THE EX
OFFICIO REPORT THAT COUNCILOR
CLARK SERVED ON THAT, BUT DID
NOT SUPPORT THIS RECOMMENDATION
AS PER THE REPORT. AND I WOULD
BE REALLY CURIOUS AS WE GO
THROUGH THE QUEUE, I'M NOT
GOING TO PUT YOU ON THE SPOT IF
YOU CAN SPEAK TO THAT, BECAUSE
I THINK THESE ARE THESE ARE
QUESTIONS THAT I IMAGINE YOU
WERE MORE IN THE WEEDS AS AS
WAS COUNCILOR RYAN ON THIS. I
DID WANT TO SAY THANK YOU TO TO
SUE BECAUSE I KNOW YOU WERE THE
CONTACT PERSON. YESTERDAY. WE
TALKED ABOUT THE INTERSTATE
FIREHOUSE CULTURAL CENTER, AND
I KNOW THAT I DON'T KNOW IF YOU
STILL WORK ON THAT OR AND WHEN
WE TALK ABOUT THE ARTS, THEY'RE
NOT JUST LARGE SCALE VENUES
DOWNTOWN. THEY'RE ALSO 99 SEAT
THEATERS ON INTERSTATE IN
DISTRICT TWO, WHERE PEOPLE HAVE
OFTEN SEEN THEIR FIRST PLAYS.
AND SO THEY'RE ALSO THE KELLER
THAT ALREADY EXISTS. THEY'RE
ALSO POTENTIALLY WHATEVER
HAPPENS AT PSU. AND SO I WOULD
LOVE TO HAVE THAT BROADER
CONVERSATION HERE. AND I
UNDERSTAND THAT THAT THERE'S
BEEN A LONG PROCESS GOING ON.
AND I THINK ONE OF THE
CHALLENGES IS THAT WHEN YOU RUN
FOR OFFICE, YOU KIND OF INHERIT
ALL OF THE MUCK THAT CAME
BEFORE. AND THERE WAS A LOT OF
THAT PRIOR TO JANUARY 1ST, 2025
THAT WE'RE DIGGING OUT OF HERE.
AND THAT MEANS OWNING SOME OF
THE DECISIONS IN THE PAST, BUT
IT ALSO MEANS OWNING THE FACT
THAT THE BUDGET IS NOT GREAT.
AND SO I DON'T KNOW THAT THERE
IS A THE FINANCIAL RESOURCES
AVAILABLE TO DO ALL THE THINGS
WE WOULD WANT TO DO. AND I'M
INTERESTED AS THIS PROCESS
CONTINUES IN EXPLORING, IF I IF
IF THERE'S A PATH I HADN'T
THOUGHT OF. THANKS.
>> THANK YOU. COUNCILOR KANAL
COLLEAGUES. I WILL JUST NOTE I
DO SEE DC A DONNIE OLIVEIRA
HANGING OUT IN THE BACK. IF
THERE ARE ANY TECHNICAL
QUESTIONS THAT SUE IS UNABLE TO
ANSWER. COUNCILOR AVALOS.
>> THANK YOU. LET ME START BY
SAYING I'M FEELING CONFLICTED
AND A LITTLE BIT CONFUSED. I'M
LISTENING TO THE ANSWERS TO THE
QUESTIONS THAT MY COLLEAGUES
ARE ASKING, AND I'M STARTING TO
GROW CONCERNED. AND SO BUT I
WANTED TO START BY ALSO
FLAGGING SOME AMENDMENTS THAT I
BROUGHT FORWARD IN CITY LIFE
AND TALKED ABOUT WHY I DID THAT.
AND, YOU KNOW, I CAME INTO THIS
HAVING THOSE AMENDMENTS FEELING
OKAY. BUT NOW I'M I DON'T KNOW
HOW I'M FEELING. SO I JUST WANT
TO BE HONEST THAT I AM
GRAPPLING WITH THIS. BUT WHAT
THE AMENDMENTS WERE DOING, THE
PRINCIPLE BEHIND THEM WAS
ESSENTIALLY WHAT I'M HEARING,
THESE FEARS, RIGHT, THAT WE'RE
ADVANCING A PROJECT BUT NOT
FINANCIALLY COMMITTING TO IT.
AND SO I AMENDED IT IN A WAY
THAT SUPPORTS THAT MAKES THE
RESOLUTION, SUPPORT, PLANNING
AND PRE-DEVELOPMENT FOR THE
POTENTIAL NEW VENUE, BUT ALSO
PRESERVES COUNCIL'S APPROVAL OF
THE FINANCIAL PLAN, THE CAPITAL
FUNDING STRATEGY, THE CITY'S
FINANCIAL OBLIGATIONS. BEFORE
WE MAKE A FINAL COMMITMENT, IT
ALSO MAKES IT EXPLICIT THAT
THIS RESOLUTION DOES NOT
AUTHORIZE OR COMMIT ADDITIONAL
CITY FUNDING FOR DEVELOPMENT OR
CONSTRUCTION BEFORE THE CITY
TAKES ON THOSE OBLIGATIONS,
STAFF NEED TO RETURN TO COUNCIL
WITH THE TOTAL PROJECT COST AND
THE CITY PROPOSED CITY
CONTRIBUTION. THE FULL CAPITAL
STACK. ET CETERA. ET CETERA. SO
I GUESS WHAT I'M WANTING TO
UNDERSTAND, AND I ALSO WANT TO
SAY THIS FOR EVERYONE THAT'S
LEFT IN THE QUEUE, BECAUSE ONE,
I'D LOVE TO HEAR REACTION ON
LIKE, IF YOU HAD THOSE FEARS,
DID MY AMENDMENTS HELP THOSE
FEARS AT ALL? AND IF NOT, TELL
ME MORE. I'D LOVE TO KNOW. AND
THEN I ALSO WOULD LOVE TO HEAR
FROM YOU. I SEE YOUR NEXT IN
THE QUEUE, COUNCILOR CLARK OR
VICE PRESIDENT CLARK ABOUT WHAT
WAS GOING ON. AND THEN I THINK,
I GUESS, WHAT IS THE. THIS
SENTIMENT THAT PEOPLE ARE
FEELING THAT IF WE PUT THIS
FORWARD, THAT EVEN THOUGH IT
TECHNICALLY DOESN'T COMMIT,
PEOPLE FEEL COMMITTED. I THINK
THAT I WANT TO UNDERSTAND WHAT
YOUR EXPECTATION IS OF US BY
APPROVING THIS LIKE DOES. WHY
DOES IT HAVE TO COME TO US? I
GUESS I KNOW THAT THERE WAS A
COMMISSION AND WE HAVE TO
APPROVE FINDINGS. AND SO I
GUESS I'M JUST FEELING I'M
TRYING TO UNDERSTAND THE
PROCESS OF WHY THIS HAS TO COME
IN THIS WAY TO US. AND THEN
ALSO, I IMAGINE IT IS THE
EXPECTATION THAT BY US
APPROVING THIS PLANNING, THAT
PSU EXPECTS US TO BE PART OF
THAT CAPITAL STACK. SO I THINK
I'M ALSO WANTING TO GET WHAT
HAPPENS IF WE APPROVE THIS. WE
MOVE FORWARD AND WE AS THE CITY,
YOU KNOW, PER MY AMENDMENTS,
I'M HOPING THAT ANY DECISION ON
ACTUAL FUNDING IS STILL GOING
TO COME BACK TO US. SO I AM NOT
COMMITTING ANY MONEY TO YOU
RIGHT NOW. I ABSOLUTELY AGREE
WITH MY COLLEAGUES THAT I DON'T
EVEN KNOW WHERE THAT'S COMING
FROM. BUT ARE YOU GOING TO BE
EXPECTING US TO BE PART OF THE
CAPITAL STACK? AND IF WE'RE NOT,
THEN WHAT? AND THEN I GUESS
ANOTHER QUESTION OF WHAT
HAPPENS IF THIS RESOLUTION DOES
NOT PASS, BECAUSE I'M JUST KIND
OF GLANCING AROUND THE DAIS AND
I DON'T KNOW IF PEOPLE ARE
HAVING APPETITE FOR THIS. AND
SO I THINK I'M ALSO WEIGHING
LIKE, WHAT, WHAT DOES THAT MEAN
IF IT DOESN'T PASS? SO I DON'T
KNOW WHO THOSE QUESTIONS ARE
FOR. THEY'RE KIND OF BROAD.
MAYBE MY MAYBE LET ME DIRECT
THE QUESTION AROUND WHAT IS THE
EXPECTATION OF US BEING PART OF
THE CAPITAL STACK IF WE'RE PART
OF THIS PLANNING? ARE YOU
EXPECTING US TO BE PART OF THAT?
HOW ARE YOU SEEING THE CITY'S
ROLE MOVING FORWARD?
>> YES. I JUST WANT TO RESTATE
AGAIN THAT THIS WOULD BE THE
CITY'S VENUE. PSU WAS INVITED
BY THE CITY, THE THEN COUNCIL,
TO COME FORWARD WITH A PROPOSAL,
AS THEY DID FOR A VARIETY OF
GROUPS. AND WE WENT THROUGH A
WHOLE PROCESS TO WINNOW DOWN TO
THE DECISION THAT HAPPENED IN
OCTOBER OF 2024, WHICH WAS A
TWO VENUE STRATEGY TO CONTINUE
LOOKING AT THE KELLER AND TO
ALSO START MOVING FORWARD. ON
THE PSU SITE. THERE WAS AN LOI
THAT WAS SIGNED IN NOVEMBER OF
2024 BETWEEN PSU AND THE CITY
ADMINISTRATOR THAT CLEARLY
OUTLINED THE NEXT STEPS, WHICH
INCLUDED THINGS LIKE DEVELOPING
A CAPITAL STACK, SECURING STATE
FUNDING, TAKING THE LEAD ON
PHILANTHROPIC WORK. WE'VE
ACCOMPLISHED ALL OF THOSE
THINGS. THAT LOI ALSO CONTAINED
A MARKET FEASIBILITY STUDY
REQUEST, AN ECONOMIC
FEASIBILITY STUDY, REQUEST, A
TRAFFIC STUDY, ALL OF WHICH
HAVE BEEN COMPLETED. AND IN
ADDITION TO THAT, OF COURSE,
THE MAYOR'S EX OFFICIO AND THE
STEERING COMMITTEE, WHICH WERE
CONVENED THIS SPRING TO AGAIN
REVIEW THE MATERIALS TO REALLY
LOOK AT THE ISSUE. I STATE ALL
OF THAT, TO SAY THAT IT'S BEEN
A VERY THOROUGH PROCESS, AND IT
STARTED WITH THE CITY. SO, YES,
THIS IS THE CITY'S VENUE. PSU
IS HERE. AS YOUR PARTNER, WE
BELIEVE THAT WE CAN HELP UNLOCK
RESOURCES TO PAY FOR PORTIONS
OF THE CITY COMPONENT. BUT AT
THE END OF THE DAY, THIS CAME
FROM A CITY REQUEST. IT WOULD
BE A CITY VENUE AND THE CITY
WOULD ABSOLUTELY BE PART OF THE
PARTNERSHIP AND FINANCING THE
PROJECT. AND BY THE PROJECT, I
MEAN ONLY THE 3000 SEAT VENUE.
WE HAVE ALL THE COSTS COVERED
FOR THE PSU, ACADEMIC AND
COMMUNITY SPACES, AND WE HAVE A
PARTNER NEGOTIATION FOR THE
HOTEL AND WE HAVE THE PARKING
PAID FOR. OKAY. SO THAT'S THE
ONLY PART THAT'S IN FRONT OF
CITY COUNCIL.
>> THANK YOU. AND I THINK ALSO
VICE PRESIDENT CLARK, WHEN YOU
GO UP, I'D LOVE TO IF YOU COULD
SHARE ABOUT YOUR AMENDMENT WITH
THE KELLER AND MAYBE EXPLAIN A
LITTLE BIT OF THAT. BUT I THINK
WHAT YOU'RE HEARING FROM THIS
COUNCIL IS THAT AS WHAT I'M
REALIZING AS A COUNCILOR IS
THAT DECISIONS GET MADE BEFORE
WE'RE HERE, RIGHT. AND WE'RE
PICKING THINGS UP. WE'RE ALSO
FACING UNEXPECTED BUDGET
SHORTFALLS. I MEAN, WE'VE HAD
ONLY BUDGET DEFICITS SINCE
WE'VE BEEN COUNCILORS. SO WE
ARE VERY WARY OF WHERE OUR
DOLLARS GO. AND SO I THINK JUST
SO THAT YOU I SAY THAT BECAUSE
I DON'T WANT YOU TO FEEL LIKE
WE DON'T THINK THAT YOU DID
YOUR DUE DILIGENCE OR THAT YOU
DID THE PROCESS OR THAT THE
CITY STARTED THIS. ABSOLUTELY.
THAT WASN'T ME. BUT I AM STILL
RESPONSIBLE FOR THOSE THINGS.
BUT, YOU KNOW, I HAVE TO WEIGH
WHAT IS CURRENT, RIGHT? AND
WHAT IS OUR CURRENT BUDGET
CAPACITY. AND SO I THINK THAT'S
WHERE I'M GRAPPLING BECAUSE I'M
LIKE, WHAT, BY US EVEN TELLING
YOU TO DO THIS AND GO THROUGH
THIS WHOLE PROCESS, WHAT HAVE
WE UNINTENTIONALLY COMMITTED
THROUGH THERE? AND SO I'M NOT
TRYING TO GO BACK NECESSARILY
IN OUR COMMITMENTS, BUT I AM
FACED WITH A LITERAL BUDGET
REALITY THAT LIKE, DOESN'T
MATTER WHAT I COMMIT IF I DON'T
HAVE MONEY FOR IT. RIGHT. SO I
THINK THAT'S WHAT WE'RE
GRAPPLING WITH. JUST SO YOU
KNOW, THAT IT'S NOT ABOUT
FEELING LIKE THAT PROCESS
WASN'T THOROUGH. I THINK IT WAS.
I THINK WE'RE JUST HITTING A
WALL WITH OUR BUDGET AND THAT'S
WHAT WE'RE WEIGHING.
>> COMPLETELY APPRECIATE THAT
AND JUST VERY MUCH RESPECT YOUR
POSITION. AND I'LL SAY AGAIN,
SIMILAR TO PSU, RIGHT, THERE'S
THE IMMEDIATE CRUNCH AS WELL AS
TRYING TO BE VISIONARY FOR THE
FUTURE. I ALSO JUST WANTED TO
NOTE FOR THE CAPITAL STACK,
WHILE THE CITY WOULD BE A
COMPONENT OF IT, THERE ARE
OTHER DOLLARS, INCLUDING
FEDERAL DOLLARS THAT WE SEE AS
POSSIBLE FOR THIS PROJECT. WE
ALSO SEE PRIVATE FUNDERS AND WE
ALSO SEE PHILANTHROPY, BOTH
LOCAL AS WELL AS NATIONALLY. SO
I DON'T WANT TO, AGAIN, SOFT
SELL THIS. THERE'S DEFINITELY
CITY DOLLARS THAT WOULD BE PUT
INTO THIS AS IT BEING A CITY
VENUE, AND WE'RE JUST REALLY
EXCITED TO START DOING SOME OF
THE HOMEWORK WITH YOU ALL
BECAUSE WE THINK THERE COULD BE
A PATH. LAST THING I'LL SAY,
WE'VE DONE MULTIPLE CASE
STUDIES WITH A WHOLE VARIETY OF
VENUES. THESE ONLY COME ALONG
MAYBE ONCE EVERY 20 YEARS
NATIONALLY. THEY'RE A REALLY
BIG DEAL. YOU DO NEED TO TAKE
THE TIME TO FEEL LIKE YOU ARE
VERY MUCH IN SUPPORT OF THIS
VISION, AND THAT YOU SEE THE
CITY WANTING TO PUT THIS
FORWARD. SO WE WANT YOU TO BE
DOING THAT TOO. I WILL TELL YOU,
IN NONE OF THOSE CASES, DID ANY
MUNICIPALITY START DOWN THE
TRACK KNOWING EXACTLY WHERE ALL
THE DOLLARS ARE GOING TO COME
FROM? IF YOU LOOK AT THE DOCTOR
PHILLIPS CENTER, WHICH IS
REALLY A STATE OF THE ART TEN
ACRE PROJECT THAT IS STILL
CONTINUING TO DEVELOP TODAY,
THEY WENT THROUGH ABOUT FOUR
MAYORS, AND I DON'T KNOW HOW
MANY CITY COUNCILS IN ORDER TO
ACCOMPLISH THE PROJECT, BUT
THEY DID GET THERE. AND IT IS
NOW A GOLD STANDARD. NATIONALLY,
WE SEE AN OPPORTUNITY FOR
PORTLAND TO BECOME A CENTER OF
GRAVITY LIKE THAT. I ALSO
RESPECTFULLY UNDERSTAND WHAT
YOU'RE WEIGHING AND THE
SNAPSHOT IN TIME, WHICH IS
DIFFERENT FROM WHERE WE STARTED
A COUPLE OF YEARS AGO. SO THANK
YOU.
>> COUNCILOR AVALOS, MAY I
RESPOND TO YOUR QUESTION ABOUT
WHY ARE WE BRINGING THIS BEFORE
YOU?
>> THAT'D BE HELPFUL.
>> THANK YOU. JUST TO BACK UP A
LITTLE BIT IN THE PREVIOUS FORM
OF GOVERNMENT, OCTOBER 2024,
THERE WAS A COUNCIL RESOLUTION
THAT BASICALLY THERE WERE TWO
OPTIONS KELLER OR PSU. THE
DIRECTION WAS, LET'S TRY TO DO
BOTH. SO THAT'S THE TWO VENUE
STRATEGY. CAN PORTLAND SUPPORT
TWO LARGE SCALE, 3000 SEAT,
BROADWAY CAPABLE THEATERS? AND
THEN WE DID ECONOMIC AND
ECONOMIC IMPACT STUDY, MARKET
FEASIBILITY STUDY,
TRANSPORTATION STUDY. THE
CONCLUSION WAS PORTLAND ONLY
HAS DEMAND, PROGRAM SUPPLY AND
MARKET DEMAND FOR ONE VENUE,
ONE LARGE SCALE VENUE. SO THEN
THE QUESTION BECOMES WHICH ONE?
AND THAT'S WHERE OUR
CONSULTANTS WHO HUNT IN
PARTNERS, WHO DID THE MARKET
FEASIBILITY AND ECONOMIC IMPACT
STUDY, RECOMMENDED BUILDING NEW
AT PSU AND THE STEERING
COMMITTEE, AND THE UNANIMOUSLY
SUPPORTED BUILDING NEW AT PSU.
AND THE EX OFFICIO SUPPORTED IT
WITH THE MAJORITY, NOT NOT ALL
MEMBERS. AND SO WHERE BASED ON
ALL THOSE RECOMMENDATIONS, THE
MAYOR'S RESOLUTION IS COMING
FORWARD AND SAYING, LET'S MOVE
FORWARD IN PLANNING, NOT
COMMITTING TO BUILDING A NEW
VENUE AT PSU AND REIMAGINING
THE KELLER AS A SMALLER VENUE.
AND WE NEED YOUR SUPPORT ON
THAT APPROACH, BECAUSE THE TWO
VENUE STRATEGY IS NOT AN OPTION.
>> THANK YOU. THAT'S ALL FOR
NOW.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR.
COLLEAGUES, JUST A HEADS UP,
THERE ARE EIGHT MORE COUNCILORS
IN THE QUEUE. I AM GOING TO
LIMIT DEBATE AFTER COUNCILOR
CLARK CONCLUDES. SO IF ANYBODY
ELSE WANTS TO GET IN THE QUEUE,
PLEASE DO NOW, VICE PRESIDENT
CLARK, TAKE IT AWAY.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT.
I WASN'T PREPARED TO ACTUALLY
MAKE A HUGE STATEMENT. I WAS
GOING TO SAVE THAT, BUT I'LL
TRY TO WEAVE IT ALL TOGETHER.
WE CAN DO THAT AFTER. I REALLY
APPRECIATE COUNCILOR AVALOS
AMENDMENTS AND MY OWN. I THINK
WE WERE BOTH TRYING TO THREAD
THE NEEDLE. WE'RE BOTH TRYING
TO MAKE THIS PALATABLE AND
PROTECT OURSELVES AND. AND FROM
MY PERSPECTIVE, IT'S TO KEEP
WORKING ON THE. KELLER. CLEARLY,
I'VE BEEN AN ADVOCATE FOR THE
KELLER ALL THE WAY THROUGH THIS
PROCESS. ON THE EX OFFICIO
COMMITTEE, I WAS PRO KELLER. I
THINK THAT THE TRANSPORTATION
STUDY WAS SUBSTANDARD, I REALLY
DO. I DON'T THINK IT WAS AS
COMPLETE AS IT SHOULD BE, GIVEN
THE IMPACT OF 405 AND THE LIGHT
RAIL RIGHT IN FRONT OF THE
FACILITY, I WASN'T HAPPY WITH
THE REPORT. I THOUGHT THEY WENT
BEYOND WHAT THEY WERE ASKED TO
DO BY MAKING A RECOMMENDATION
TO SUPPORT PSU. SO I WAS ON THE
SHORT END OF THE STICK AND THE
EX OFFICIO GROUP, BUT I
REALIZED I WAS ON THE LOSING
END AND I SAID, WELL, WHAT WE
NEED TO DO IS TO HAVE ADDENDA,
WHICH YOU AND I HAVE ADDRESSED
IN OUR AMENDMENTS. I DID WANT
TO GO BACK TO WHAT SOME OF THE
OTHER MY OTHER COLLEAGUES
MENTIONED EARLIER, AND JUST
PURSUE THIS. I I'M NOT I DON'T
UNDERSTAND WHY WE NEED A
RESOLUTION NECESSARILY. I MEAN,
THIS IS WORK THAT COULD BE DONE
BY THE ADMINISTRATION. YOU
WOULD THINK, YOU KNOW, A LOT OF
THIS WORK, HOWEVER, I'M VERY
SENSITIVE TO THE FACT THAT PSU
NEEDS TO HAVE A NEW ACADEMIC
FACILITY. MY CHOIR PRACTICES AT
PSU, IT'S AS BAD AS MY HIGH
SCHOOL. YOU KNOW, THEY DO NEED
ANOTHER FACILITY, SO I RESPECT
THAT. AND THEY WENT TO THE
LEGISLATURE, THEY GOT THE FUNDS,
AND I DON'T WANT TO GET IN THE
WAY OF THAT. I WANT THEM TO
HAVE THAT FACILITY. BUT I HAVE
LOTS OF CONCERNS. OBVIOUSLY,
I'VE EXPRESSED ALL THE WAY
THROUGH THIS PROCESS. I WANT TO
GO BACK TO WHAT COUNCILOR GREEN
BROUGHT UP ABOUT THE COMMITMENT.
AND IN THE IN THE RESOLUTION,
IT TALKS ABOUT DECEMBER 1ST.
DOES THAT MEAN THAT ON DECEMBER
1ST, THIS THE REPORT ANSWERING
ALL THESE QUESTIONS THAT ARE IN
THE RESOLUTION IS COMING BACK
TO US. MAYBE. I DON'T KNOW IF
DONNIE OLIVEIRA CAN ANSWER THAT.
IS THAT GOING TO BE A DECISION
POINT FOR US DECEMBER 1ST? WHAT
DOES THAT MEAN EXACTLY? AND TO
THE POINT ABOUT DECISIONS GET
MADE WITHOUT US HAVING A VOTE,
I WANT TO BE VERY CLEAR THAT
AND AS YOU HAVE AMENDED THIS
RESOLUTION TO SAY, WE ARE NOT
MAKING A FINANCIAL COMMITMENT,
END OF STATEMENT. WE ARE NOT.
BUT WHAT HAPPENS IN DECEMBER
1ST? DOES IT COME BACK TO US AT
THAT POINT? ARE YOU COMING TO
COUNCIL FOR ANOTHER DECISION?
>> YEAH. THANK YOU FOR THE
QUESTION. VICE PRESIDENT CLARK
DONNIE OLIVEIRA. FOR THE RECORD,
I APOLOGIZE. I COULDN'T BE HERE
ANY SOONER. COUNCILOR, I THINK
THE PLACE TO START IS PICKING
UP SOMETHING THAT BOTH SARAH
AND SUE HAVE EXPRESSED ALREADY.
PART OF THE RESOLUTION. PART OF
THE INTENT WAS HERE WAS TO STOP
THE SWIRL THAT WAS GOING ON.
FOR THE LAST SEVERAL YEARS.
I'VE BEEN A PART OF THIS
CONVERSATION FOR FOR MANY YEARS
AS WELL, ABOUT WHAT TO DO WITH
THE VENUES. AND THE REALITY IS,
IS ALL WE'RE ASKING FOR IS A
GREEN LIGHT TO FORMALLY SIT
DOWN WITH PSU, TO CONTEMPLATE
WHAT IT MIGHT LOOK LIKE FOR THE
CITY TO PARTICIPATE IN THE RFP
PROCESS THAT WE STARTED TO
SARAH'S POINT ABOUT INVESTING
IN A PERFORMING ARTS VENUE ON A
PSU PARCEL. AS A REMINDER, THE
REASON WHY WE'RE EVEN HERE IS
BECAUSE WHEN WE STARTED
CONTEMPLATING A RENOVATION OF
KELLER VERY QUICKLY, WE
UNDERSTOOD THAT THE IMPACT OF
DOING THAT, OF PAUSING BROADWAY
OPERATIONS PROGRAMING, WOULD BE
DETRIMENTAL NOT JUST TO
BROADWAY, BUT TO OUR OVERALL P5
VENUES. SO THAT'S WHY THAT
SECONDARY VENUE EVEN BECAME A
SCENARIO TO CONTEMPLATE. SO
IT'S NOT JUST A PICK ONE OR THE
OTHER, IT IS. WHAT IS THE
OPPORTUNITY, COST OR IMPACT TO
ONLY DO? KELLER. SO THAT'S
WHERE THE SECONDARY VENUE
OPTION EVEN BEGAN TO BECOME A
POSSIBILITY, WAS WE STARTED TO
REALIZE THAT YOU CAN'T JUST
DISPLACE BROADWAY FOR SIX
MONTHS. THAT'S NOT VIABLE. YOU
CAN'T JUST PAY OFF THE LABOR.
THAT'S NOT REAL. WHAT IS REAL
IS WE WANT TO SUSTAIN BROADWAY
OPERATIONS. SO BACK TO YOUR
QUESTION. SO WE HAVE THIS
RESOLUTION BEFORE YOU. AND
THANK YOU, COUNCILOR AVALOS,
FOR YOUR AMENDMENTS THAT
CRYSTALLIZE THAT. WE NEED SOME
TO DO SOME HOMEWORK THAT WE
HAVEN'T DONE, BY THE WAY. AND I
ALSO WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THIS
RIGHT NOW, CANDIDLY WITH YOU
ALL. IF WE HAD DONE ALL THE
WORK AND COME TO YOU ALL WITH A
REALLY BAKED CAPITAL STACK, I'M
GUESSING THERE WOULD HAVE BEEN
SOME FRUSTRATIONS THAT WE DID
THAT WORK WITHOUT GETTING A
GREEN LIGHT FROM YOU FIRST.
RIGHT. SO THERE'S A LITTLE BIT
OF A TENSION HERE. WHAT DO YOU
WANT US TO DO? BRING YOU THE
NUMBERS OR GET YOUR PERMISSION
TO DO ADVANCE THAT WORK IN
TRANSPARENCY? SO HERE WE ARE
ASKING, HEY, ADMINISTRATION, GO
FORTH, FIGURE IT OUT, WORK WITH
PSU AND COME BACK TO US ON
DECEMBER 1ST WITH A CONCEPT
THAT WE CAN GET BEHIND. OR
MAYBE NOT. MAYBE IT DOESN'T
WORK OUT. WE HAVEN'T DONE THE
WORK YET. WE REALLY HAVEN'T.
OUR CFO HASN'T BEEN INVOLVED
BECAUSE WE HAVEN'T STARTED THAT
CONVERSATION. SO I COMPLETELY
HEAR THE CONCERN THAT MANY OF
YOU HAVE ABOUT COMMITTING
DOLLARS. COMPLETELY FAIR. WE'RE
CONCERNED, TOO, BECAUSE WE
HAVEN'T STARTED THE WORK. SO
COUNCILOR DECEMBER 1ST. BEST
CASE SCENARIO, WE WORK OUT WITH
OUR PARTNERS AT PSU WITH A
VIABLE OPTION FOR THIS COUNCIL
TO CONTEMPLATE. MAYBE IT'S FOR
44, MAYBE IT'S FOR 100, MAYBE
IT'S FOR THE FULL CAPITAL STACK
BECAUSE WE WE HIT THE LOTTERY.
BUT I DON'T HAVE THAT
INFORMATION FOR YOU BECAUSE WE
HAVEN'T STARTED THE WORK. IS
THAT IS THAT HELPFUL?
>> YEAH, I APPRECIATE THAT. AND
I WON'T TAKE UP ANY MORE TIME.
I'D LIKE TO COME BACK LATER AND
TALK ABOUT THIS A LITTLE BIT
MORE. BUT I AM, BOTTOM LINE,
VERY CONCERNED ABOUT THE MONEY
AND THAT WE AND I WOULD JUST
REITERATE WHAT I'VE HEARD FROM
MY COLLEAGUES IS THERE IS NO
MONEY. WE'RE FOCUSED RIGHT NOW
ON MODA. HOW DO WE GET THE
MONEY FOR MODA? I JUST DON'T I
DON'T FORESEE US COMING BACK IN
DECEMBER AND SAYING, OKAY,
CAPITAL STACK, YEAH, WE'RE
GOING TO GO FOR THIS MONEY. I
THINK WE'RE GOING TO BE IN THE
SAME PLACE IN DECEMBER THAT WE
ARE TODAY. UNFORTUNATELY. BUT I
AM TRYING TO THREAD THE NEEDLE.
AND I KNOW, DONNIE, WITH ALL
DUE RESPECT, THAT YOU DIDN'T
LIKE MY AMENDMENTS ABOUT
KEEPING KELLER ALIVE, BUT I DO
THINK THAT WE CAN MAKE SMALL
INVESTMENTS IN KELLER. WE'RE
GOING TO KEEP KELLER OPEN WHILE
WE GO THROUGH THIS PROCESS.
KELLER HAS TO STAY OPEN FOR THE
BROADWAY AND AMERICA SHOWS, AND
KELLER HAS TO STAY OPEN TO BE
ABLE TO SUPPORT FIVE. IT'S THE
ONLY PROFITABLE THING WE HAVE
IN. FIVE SO I'M JUST WORRIED
THAT WE'RE WE'RE NOT KICKING
THE CAN. WE'RE GETTING MORE
INFORMATION, BUT WE ARE GOING
TO KEEP KELLER ALIVE. AND.
KELLER. IN THIS RESOLUTION. WE
AMENDED IT TO DO THIS IN TANDEM
WITH THE. KELLER. I'LL JUST
LEAVE IT AT THAT. THANK YOU,
MR. CHAIR.
>> THANK YOU. COLLEAGUES, THERE
ARE TEN COUNCILORS IN QUEUE. IT
IS 1115. OUR STAFF NEED A BREAK.
I AM GOING TO GIVE US A 15
MINUTE BREAK AND COME BACK HERE
AT. OKAY. I'M GOING TO GIVE US
A 12 MINUTE BREAK. I'M GOING TO
HAVE US BACK HERE AT 1130.
>> THANK YOU.
>> WELCOME BACK FOLKS. THANK
YOU ALL SO MUCH FOR YOUR
PATIENCE. I UNDERSTAND WE ARE
GOING TO BE LOSING A COUPLE
FOLKS HERE IN A FEW MINUTES.
AND SO COLLEAGUES, WITH YOUR
PERMISSION, I AM GOING TO. I
HAVE NOTED THE QUEUE IN THE THE
LINEUP FOR THE CONVERSATION
WITH REGARD TO THE LARGE SCALE
PERFORMING ARTS VENUE. WE ARE
GOING TO GO BACK TO THE
CAMPESINOS ITEM. I UNDERSTAND
THERE ARE STILL TWO AMENDMENTS
AND THEN AN UNDERLYING. THEN WE
WILL MOVE TO. TO PASS IT. SO
WITH YOUR. PERMISSION,
COLLEAGUES, I WOULD LIKE TO
AGAIN PAUSE ITEM 13 AND REOPEN
ITEM 12 AND KEELAN. DO YOU NEED
TO READ IT, REREAD IT, OR ARE
WE JUST ON IT NOW?
>> YEAH, I THINK WE CAN JUST
MOVE BACK TO IT SINCE I'VE
ALREADY READ IT.
>> OKAY, COLLEAGUES, GO AHEAD
AND PULL YOURSELVES OUT OF THE
QUEUE FOR THE KELLER ITEM AND
FEEL FREE TO JUMP INTO THE
QUEUE FOR THE NOW REOPENED ITEM
12 DOCUMENT 2026-2, FOUR THREE.
AND I BELIEVE WE HAVE
AMENDMENTS TO START WITH. IS
THIS CORRECT? COUNCILOR KOYAMA
LANE, WOULD YOU LIKE TO START
WITH YOURS?
>> YES, I WOULD LIKE TO MOVE.
>> KOYAMA LANE AMENDMENT TWO.
YOU SHOULD HAVE A COPY OF THAT
IN YOUR INBOX. IT CONNECTS TO
WHAT WE WERE TALKING ABOUT
EARLIER. IT NOW STATES THAT THE
REQUIREMENT REQUIREMENTS IN
CODE SUBSECTION 17.9, 3.06,
ZERO POINT A ARE HEREBY WAIVED
FOR THE PROPOSED RENAMING OF
NORTHEAST AND SOUTHEAST CESAR
CHAVEZ BOULEVARD TO NORTHEAST
AND SOUTHEAST CAMPESINOS
BOULEVARD. INSTEAD, THE
EXISTING STREET NAME SIGN AND
PROPOSED NEW NAME SIGN SHALL
BOTH BE POSTED AND MAINTAINED
UP TO FIVE YEARS FOLLOWING
APPROVAL FOR THE PROPOSED
RENAMING OF THE NAMES. THANK
YOU FOR YOUR FEEDBACK, AND I'D
LIKE TO FORMALLY MOVE THIS
AMENDMENT AND WOULD APPRECIATE
A SECOND.
>> SECOND COUNCILOR KOYAMA LANE
MOVES KOYAMA LANE TO COUNCILOR
CLERK. VICE PRESIDENT, CLERK
SECONDS. COLLEAGUES, IS THERE A
DISCUSSION OF THIS AMENDMENT?
COUNCILOR. MORILLO. NO.
COUNCILOR. NOVICK. NO.
COUNCILOR. PIRTLE-GUINEY.
>> THANK YOU. I APPRECIATE THE
CHANGES, AND I JUST WANT TO SAY
ON THE RECORD THAT I HOPE THAT
PBOT, BECAUSE THIS IS A
FLEXIBLE TIMELINE, GIVES
NOTIFICATION ON THE SPECIFIC
TIMELINE THAT RESIDENTS ALONG
THE STREET SHOULD EXPECT TO
THOSE RESIDENTS WITH SOME SOME
ADVANCE WARNING. FOR EXAMPLE,
IF TEN MONTHS IN, YOU THINK YOU
CAN DO THIS IN 18 MONTHS, SHOOT
FOLKS WHO LIVE ON THE STREET
AND HAVE BUSINESSES ON THE
STREET. A LETTER LETTING THEM
KNOW THAT. I HOPE THAT PBOT IS
LISTENING. I DON'T SEE FOLKS IN
THE ROOM, BUT I WILL FOLLOW UP
TO MAKE SURE THEY KNOW THAT
THAT IS A REQUEST. THANK YOU,
COUNCILOR, FOR AMENDING YOUR
LANGUAGE.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR
PIRTLE-GUINEY COLLEAGUES,
SEEING NO ONE ELSE IN THE QUEUE
FOR DISCUSSION OF KOYAMA LANE
TWO KEELAN, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL
THE ROLL?
>> MOVED BY KOYAMA LANE.
SECONDED BY CLERK KOYAMA LANE I
AYE, MORILLO. I NOVICK. I CLERK.
I GREEN. HI ZIMMERMAN. I AVALOS.
>> I.
>> SMITH I.
>> KANAL I. PIRTLE-GUINEY I I I.
>> THE AMENDMENT IS APPROVED
WITH A VOTE OF 12 AYES.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH,
COUNCILOR NOVICK.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
I'D LIKE TO MOVE MY REWRITTEN
AMENDMENT, WHICH IS NOVICK TWO,
BECAUSE WE SENT OUT A ERRONEOUS
VERSION FIRST, THAT THE
AMENDMENT WOULD AMEND PARAGRAPH
TWO TO SAY THERE IS WIDESPREAD
SUPPORT IN THE COMMUNITY TO
SWIFTLY RENAME PORTLAND CESAR
CHAVEZ BOULEVARD IN A MANNER
THAT BEFITS AND HONORS. ET
CETERA. ET CETERA. SECOND.
>> COUNCILOR NOVICK MOVES
NOVICK TWO COUNCILOR KANAL
SECONDS. COLLEAGUES, IS THERE
FURTHER DISCUSSION OF THE
AMENDMENT?
>> TWO THREE?
>> SEEING NO ONE ELSE IN THE
QUEUE, KEELAN CAN WE PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON NOVICK TWO.
>> MOVED BY NOVICK. SECONDED BY
KANAL. KOYAMA LANE. AYE,
MORILLO. MORILLO. I NOVICK. I
CLARK GREEN. I ZIMMERMAN. I
AVALOS. I SMITH.
>> I I.
>> PIRTLE-GUINEY I RYAN. A
DUNPHY. I AMENDMENT IS APPROVED
WITH 12 VOTES.
>> THANK YOU. COUNCIL VICE
PRESIDENT.
>> CLERK THANK YOU, COUNCIL
PRESIDENT. I WOULD LIKE TO
OFFER AN AMENDMENT TO THE
ORDINANCE TO ADD AN EMERGENCY
CLAUSE. I BELIEVE IT'S
IMPORTANT THAT WE MOVE THIS
ITEM FORWARD AND NOT DELAY
ANOTHER WEEK. WE WOULD LIKE TO
ENSURE THAT WE ARE RESPONSIVE
TO COMMUNITY CONCERNS ABOUT THE
NEGATIVE IMPACT OF SURVIVORS OF
ABUSE AND OTHERS, AND TO ENSURE
THAT WE FACILITATE THE TIMELY
OPERATIONS OF CITY STAFF IN
CHANGING THE STREET NAME.
>> THANK YOU. VICE PRESIDENT.
CLERK. MOVES. CLERK ONE
COUNCILOR RYAN SECONDS. THE
AMENDMENT HAS BEEN REDUCED. I
SEE IT IN WRITING, SO I SEE A
COPY. DO WE HAVE A COPY OF IT?
>> OKAY.
>> OF THE EMERGENCY CLAUSE.
>> YEAH. OF THE EMERGENCY
CLAUSE. OKAY. I'M GOING TO GET
THAT INTO YOUR INBOXES.
COLLEAGUES. ANY DISCUSSION OF
THE CLERK? ONE AMENDMENT.
KEELAN HAVE YOU GOTTEN A COPY
OF THIS YET?
>> LET ME CHECK. CHECK. I THINK
MY TEAM IS CLEAR ON THE REASON
FOR THE EMERGENCY. SO I THINK
WE CAN PROCEED WITH THE VOTE IF
YOU'RE READY.
>> SOUNDS GOOD. LET'S PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON CLERK ONE.
>> MOVE BY CLERK. SECONDED BY
RYAN. THIS IS TO ADD THE
EMERGENCY CLAUSE. KOYAMA LANE.
I MORILLO. I NOVICK. I CLERK. I
GREEN. I ZIMMERMAN I AVALOS. I
SMITH. I NO. I PIRTLE-GUINEY. I
RYAN I DUNPHY. I AMENDMENT IS
APPROVED WITH 12 VOTES.
>> COLLEAGUES, IS THERE ANY
FURTHER DISCUSSION OF THE NOW
THRICE AMENDED UNDERLYING
ORDINANCE? COUNCILOR ZIMMERMAN.
>> NEVER LOSE THE MOMENT. SO
LET'S PASS THIS SUCKER.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR
COUNCILOR SMITH.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT,
AND THANK YOU, COUNCIL VICE
PRESIDENT, FOR ADDING THIS
EMERGENCY CLAUSE BECAUSE IT IS
SO IMPORTANT. IN 2009, WE WE
FIRST NAMED 39TH BOULEVARD,
CESAR CHAVEZ BOULEVARD. WE
UNKNOWINGLY HONORED A VERY
FLAWED MAN WHO GAVE VOICE TO
MILLIONS AND TAUGHT A NATION
THAT JUSTICE IS CULTIVATED
THROUGH ORGANIZING AND PEACEFUL
RESOLVE. WE ARE REMINDED THAT A
MOVEMENT IS NEVER BUILT BY ONE
INDIVIDUAL. IT IS BUILT BY THE
WORKERS IN THE ROLES BENT OVER
UNDER THE HEAT OF THE SUN,
ENDURING BACKBREAKING LABOR
FROM DAWN UNTIL DUSK, SO THAT
FAMILIES ACROSS OUR CITY AND
OUR STATE HAVE FOOD ON THEIR
TABLES. BY DEDICATING THIS
CORRIDOR TO OUR CAMPESINOS, WE
HONOR THE HANDS THAT FEED US.
THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR SMITH.
>> COUNCILOR NOVICK.
>> I THINK THAT THIS PROPOSAL
IS A VERY ELEGANT SOLUTION TO
THE PROBLEM THAT WE WERE FACED
WITH. I THINK THAT THE IDEA OF
HONORING CESAR CHAVEZ TO BEGIN
WITH WAS TO HONOR THE
FARMWORKERS MOVEMENT. AND I'M
SOMEBODY WHO DIDN'T EAT GRAPES
UNTIL I WAS LIKE SEVEN YEARS
OLD, BECAUSE YOU'RE SUPPOSED TO
BOYCOTT THEM. I AM SENSITIVE TO
THE CONCERNS OF FOLKS WHO FEEL
LIKE THIS WAS A RUSHED PROCESS,
BECAUSE IT WAS. AND THE COUNCIL
PRESIDENT HAS INDICATED A
DESIRE TO BRING FORWARD
SOMETHING THAT WOULD ESTABLISH
A PROCESS THAT'S NOT AS
ELABORATE AS THE STREET
RENAMING PROCESS THAT WE
CURRENTLY HAVE, BUT IS STILL
SOMETHING. AND HERE WE
BASICALLY HAD NOTHING. AND I
DON'T KNOW THAT ANY PROCESS
WOULD HAVE CHANGED ANYBODY'S
MIND. BUT PART OF THE POINT OF
PROCESS IS JUST TO ALLOW PEOPLE
A CHANCE TO YELL AT US. AND I
WISH WE'D FIGURED OUT A WAY TO
GIVE PEOPLE MORE OF A CHANCE TO
YELL AT US. AND I'M NOT GOING
TO CAST A PROTEST VOTE TODAY IN
SUPPORT OF GIVING PEOPLE MORE
TIME TO YELL AT US. BUT I'M
GOING TO VOTE YES. BUT I THINK
THAT WE NEED TO MAKE SURE THAT
BEFORE WE DO ANY MORE STREET
RENAMINGS, WE HAVE A PROCESS
THAT WE'RE ACTUALLY WILLING TO
STICK TO.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH,
COUNCILOR NOVICK COUNCILOR
KANAL.
>> JUST FLAGGING. THANKS FOR
THAT, AND I AM COMMITTED TO
GETTING THAT ON THE COMMITTEE,
THE WHOLE AGENDA. AND IT'S
YOU'LL SEE IT PENCILED IN FOR
THE FUTURE FOR THE NEXT COUPLE
OF MONTHS. THANKS.
>> THANK YOU. COUNCILOR KANAL
COLLEAGUES. SEEING NO ONE ELSE
IN THE QUEUE FOR DISCUSSION,
KEELAN, CAN WE PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON THE UNDERLYING NOW
AMENDED ORDINANCE?
>> THIS IS NOW AN EMERGENCY AND
IT REQUIRES NINE VOTES TO PASS.
KOYAMA LANE. THANK YOU SO MUCH,
>> ADVOCATES, I VOTE I.
>> AYE, MORILLO I.
>> NOVICK I.
>> CLARK I GREEN.
>> I ZIMMERMAN I AVALOS I SMITH.
>> I JUST LIKE TO SAY I AM
DEEPLY PROUD TO SPONSOR THIS
ORDINANCE, ALONG WITH MY
COLLEAGUE, COUNCILOR TIFFANY
KOYAMA LANE. THANK YOU FOR YOUR
HELP AND YOUR SUPPORT. I'M
EXCITED TO CAST MY VOTE IN
FAVOR OF THIS ORDINANCE ON ITS
SECOND READING, AND I URGE ALL
MY COLLEAGUES TO JOIN ME IN
SUBMITTING THIS TRIBUTE INTO
THE BEDROCK OF OUR CITY SPACES
AND STREETS. THANK YOU.
>> I KANAL. I PIRTLE-GUINEY. I
RYAN. A DUNPHY. I ORDINANCE
PASSES WITH 12 VOTES.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH,
COLLEAGUES. MOVING BACK TO ITEM
NUMBER 13, I WILL I HAVE FOLKS
IN THE QUEUE. I HAVE ALL TEN
COLLEAGUES, AND I WILL CALL
FOLKS OUT. IT WILL WE'RE GOING
TO START WITH IT'S GOING TO GO.
NOVICK. DUNPHY. ZIMMERMAN.
COUNCILOR. NOVICK.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
LET'S SEE, IS THE CITY ATTORNEY
HERE?
>> ONE OF THEM?
>> DO WE.
>> MAYBE I HAVE NOT ADVISED ON
THIS.
>> OKAY. WELL, THAT MIGHT BE SO
MY QUESTION I JUST WANT TO
CLEAR UP THIS IDEA OF WHETHER
THIS RESOLUTION COMMITS US TO
SPENDING ANY MONEY. SO IF
YOU'RE COMFORTABLE ANSWERING
THE QUESTION, I WILL POSE IT
THIS WAY. IF WE VOTE FOR THIS
RESOLUTION AND THEN WE DECIDE
THAT WE'RE NOT GOING TO COMMIT
$44 MILLION TO ANYTHING, AND
PSU THEN SUED US FOR $44
MILLION, WOULD YOU BE WORRIED
THAT THEY WOULD WIN?
>> I WOULD NO, I WOULD NOT. I
IT DOES NOT COME AT US TO
SPENDING THE MONEY. I WOULD NOT
BE WORRIED ABOUT DEFENDING OUR
POSITION IN COURT, THAT WE ARE
NOT OBLIGATED TO SPEND THE 44
MILLION.
>> OKAY. THANK YOU. AND AS TO
THE SUBSTANCE, THIS IS
DIFFICULT FOR ME. MOST OF MY
FRIENDS WHO CARE ABOUT THIS
ISSUE ARE COMMITTED TO THE
KELLER. IF I COULD WAVE A MAGIC
WAND, I WOULD MAKE THE KELLER,
YOU KNOW, SEISMICALLY RESILIENT
AND UP TO DATE OVERNIGHT. I SEE,
AND I ALSO SHARE MY COLLEAGUES
CONCERNS THAT I DON'T KNOW
WHERE THE HECK WE'RE GONNA GET
THE MONEY TO DO ANYTHING. I SEE
THIS VOTE AS A VOTE TO AT LEAST
EXPLORE THE POSSIBILITY THAT WE
WILL BE ABLE, OVER THE NEXT 20
YEARS, TO HAVE CONTINUOUS
BROADWAY LEVEL PRODUCTIONS, AND
THAT WE WON'T HAVE AN
INTERRUPTION FOR A SIGNIFICANT
PERIOD OF TIME, WHICH WOULD
COST PEOPLE'S JOBS AND HURT OUR
ECONOMY. I KNOW THAT SOME OF
THE KELLER ADVOCATES HAVE SAID
THAT MAYBE WE SHOULD HAVE A
TEMPORARY VENUE. I KNOW ALSO
THE BROADWAY ACROSS AMERICA
FOLKS HAVE SAID THAT THEY DON'T
SEE ANY WAY THAT THAT WOULD
WORK. SO I REGRET HAVING TO
WIND UP LIKE VOTING AGAINST MY
FRIENDS. BUT I JUST REALLY
THINK THAT I DON'T WANT TO
ANNOUNCE TODAY THAT WE'RE GOING
TO GIVE UP ON THE IDEA OF
CONTINUOUS PRODUCTIONS. AND
FINALLY, THIS WAS NOT DECISIVE
FOR ME, BUT I REALLY
APPRECIATED THE FACT THAT
ROSETTA TUCCI QUOTED HAIRSPRAY
LAST WEEK. I REALLY THINK THAT
ANYBODY TESTIFYING ON AN ISSUE
LIKE THIS SHOULD WORK IN A
BROADWAY MUSICAL REFERENCE.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR NOVICK
COLLEAGUES. I PUT MYSELF NEXT
IN THE QUEUE. I THINK I'VE BEEN
EXTREMELY CLEAR ABOUT WHERE I
STAND ON THIS PROPOSAL. I THINK
THAT A BUILDING, A NEW VENUE AT
PORTLAND STATE UNIVERSITY IS A
REALLY GOOD IDEA. BUT I WANT TO
TALK ABOUT WHAT THIS IS ALL
ABOUT IN THE BIG PICTURE, THE
KELLER IS ONE OF THE P5
THEATERS. THE CITY OWNS THE
BUILDING, WHICH WAS FIRST BUILT
IN 1917 AND REMODELED IN 1965
INTO WHAT WE KNOW TODAY. IT WAS
NAMED AFTER IRA KELLER, FIRST
CHAIR OF THE PORTLAND
DEVELOPMENT COMMISSION AND THE
ARCHITECT OF THE DEMOLITION OF
LOWER ALBINA. THE KELLER STILL
HAS TWO FULL WALLS THAT WERE
BUILT OUT OF THE 1917 BRICK
MASONRY. THEY DIDN'T FIX THAT
IN THE 1965 RENOVATION. SO IT'S
A SEISMIC DEATHTRAP, A 4000
SEAT ASSEMBLY SPACE, A GIANT
ROOM FULL OF KIDS SEEING THE
NUTCRACKER THAT WILL COLLAPSE
IN A SERIOUS EARTHQUAKE. THIS
IS ANOTHER ONE OF THE
SITUATIONS WHERE THE CITY OWNS
A BUILDING, THE ONLY BUILDING
IN PORTLAND THAT CAN HOST
BROADWAY CAPABLE SHOWS. AND IT
IS QUESTION OF WHETHER, OF HOW
AND WHEN WE PAY TO FIX IT, NOT
WHETHER WE WILL. AND I AM
CONVINCED THAT THE PSU PROPOSAL
IS THE RIGHT PROPOSAL TO MOVE
THE CITY FORWARD. THE PROPOSAL
TO CLOSE THE KELLER FOR MAJOR
RENOVATIONS, AS I'VE SAID MANY
TIMES, WOULD SUSPEND TOURING
BROADWAY PRODUCTIONS IN
PORTLAND FOR UP TO FIVE YEARS.
THAT WOULD PUT SCORES OF UNION
STAGEHANDS AND TICKET TAKERS
OUT OF WORK, SPECIFICALLY WITH
SKILLED TECHNICAL LABOR. THE
CITY WOULD VERY LIKELY LOSE A
MAJOR SECTION OF THIS WORKFORCE
TO SEATTLE, TO BOISE, OR TO
COMPETITOR CITIES IN THE
SUNBELT. AND WE WOULD LOSE THE
ECONOMIC ENGINE THAT PAYS FOR
ALL OTHER ACTIVITIES IN THE
CITY OWNED THEATERS DOWNTOWN.
THE EXTENDED LOSS OF BROADWAY
REVENUE WOULD BREAK P5'S
FINANCIAL BACK AT A TIME WHEN
IT'S ALREADY IN FINANCIAL
DISTRESS AND TRANSITION, AND
WOULD PLACE THE CITY ON A PATH
TOWARDS FULL, PRIVATE, FOR
PROFIT PRIVATIZATION OF THOSE
THEATERS. IT HAS HAPPENED IN
OTHER CITIES. IN CONTRAST, BY
MOVING FORWARD IN PARTNERSHIP
WITH PORTLAND STATE UNIVERSITY,
THE CITY WILL BE TAPPING INTO
ONE OF THE MOST EFFECTIVE AND
PROVEN CAPITAL PROJECT
DEVELOPMENT TEAMS IN OUR REGION
WHO HAVE CLEARLY AND REPEATEDLY
COMMITTED TO SPENDING THEIR
STAFF TIME, ENERGY AND
REPUTATION ON RAISING PRIVATE
DOLLARS FOR WHAT WILL BE A CITY
OWNED ASSET AND WHO ARE
PROPOSING A JOINT APPROACH ON
FUNDING ONGOING REGULAR
MAINTENANCE THROUGHOUT THE
MULTI-BUILDING COMPLEX. AFTER
30 YEARS LIMPING ALONG WITH OUR
BROKEN CITY METRO MODEL, THE
OPERATING MODEL HAS FINALLY
CRACKED AND OUR BUILDINGS ARE
TOO EMPTY, TOO EXPENSIVE FOR
COMMUNITY AND ARTS GROUPS ALIKE.
AND THEY ARE RUNNING OUT OF
MONEY. BUT IMAGINE, IN 5 OR 10
YEARS WE'VE BUILT THIS NEW
PERFORMING ARTS CENTER AT PSU.
NOT ONLY IS IT A NEW, COOL,
SHINY OBJECT, NOT ONLY DOES IT
GET CRANES IN THE SKY, BUT WE
WILL HAVE A STATE OF THE ART
ACADEMIC THEATER AND THE
REGION'S LARGEST PROFESSIONALLY
TOURING HOUSE, SHARING THE SAME
COMPLEX. PSU AND THE UNIONS ARE
ALREADY DISCUSSING A WORKFORCE
DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM. KIDS
GROWING UP IN MY DISTRICT WILL
BE ABLE TO GO FROM PARKROSE
HIGH SCHOOL AND THEIR THEATER
PROGRAM TO AN EDUCATION AT PSU
THAT THEY CAN AFFORD, WHERE
THERE WILL BE OPPORTUNITIES TO
WORK WITH PROFESSIONAL GRADE
EQUIPMENT AND HAVE DIRECT HANDS
ON EXPERIENCE WITH NATIONAL
LEVEL LABOR AND PRACTITIONERS.
RIGHT NOW, YOU HAVE TO LEAVE
OREGON TO GET THAT EDUCATION.
THAT IS NOT SOMETHING THAT KIDS
IN MY NEIGHBORHOOD CAN AFFORD
TO DO. THE NEW PERFORMING ARTS
CENTER WILL ALSO BE ACCESSIBLE
TO LOCAL ARTS COMMUNITY, WHICH
IS STARTING TO SCRAPE THE
BOTTOM OF THE BARREL OF A TWO
DECADE LONG CRISIS IN
AFFORDABLE ART SPACES. PSU
CONSULTED WITH LOCAL ARTS
GROUPS TO SET THE SIZE OF THEIR
PROPOSED ACADEMIC THEATER AT A
SIZE THAT LOCAL NONPROFITS CAN
ALSO FILL AND WILL BE ABLE TO
UTILIZE. AND FROM THE BEGINNING,
THEY PROPOSED TO MAKE STUDIO
AND OFFICE SPACE AVAILABLE TO
LOCAL GROUPS AS WELL. THIS
VENUE CAN CATALYZE THE WHOLE
TRANSITION OF THE SOUTH END OF
DOWNTOWN INTO A TRUE CULTURAL
DISTRICT. YES, OUR DOWNTOWN
THEATERS ARE CHANGING AFTER 30
YEARS OF THE UNIQUE CITY METRO
MANAGEMENT. METRO STEPS AWAY ON
JULY 1ST, 2027. SO LET'S
IMAGINE ONCE THE PERFORMING
ARTS CENTER IS SCOPED, FUNDED,
AND BUILT, IT'LL BECOME PART OF
THE P SIX MANAGED WITH A
COMMUNITY BENEFIT MISSION TO
PROVIDE GREAT ART AND
ENTERTAINMENT FOR THE COMMUNITY
AND GREAT PLACES FOR LOCAL
PROFESSIONALS TO GROW AND
PRESENT THEIR WORK. BROADWAY
MOVES TO JOIN A VIBRANT ART
CAMPUS AT THE PERFORMING ARTS
AND CULTURAL CENTER. COMMERCIAL
SHOWS BLOOM AT THE KELLER AND
THE SCHNITZ AND SOMEWHAT.
SOMEDAY, ONE OF THOSE SPACES
WILL BE REDEVELOPED INTO A TRUE
CONCERT HALL, THOUGH IT WILL
TAKE HARD WORK, VISION, AND OF
COURSE, MONEY. ALL OF THE
BENEFIT IS TO IS TO SO MANY
CROSS SECTIONS OF PORTLAND THAT
IT COULD BRING. THIS IS ALL
ABSOLUTELY POSSIBLE, BUT THE
FIRST STEP IS THINKING FORWARDS,
NOT BACKWARDS, WITH GOOD
PARTNERS AT THE TABLE AND A
PLAN THAT WILL SET UP SO MUCH
POTENTIAL FOR GROWTH. WE MUST
MOVE FORWARD TODAY. WE MUST
BELIEVE IN WHAT IS POSSIBLE,
AND WE MUST BELIEVE THAT WHAT
SHOULD BE AND COULD BE AND NOT
FALL BACK ON THOSE THINGS THAT
THAT THOSE WHO WOULD SAY THAT
THE CITY CAN'T DO BIG THINGS,
IT'S THE ONLY WAY FOR US TO
GROW IS TO PRIVATIZE. AND THAT
HALF MEASURES ARE THE BEST WE
CAN HOPE FOR IN THE ABSENCE OF
AN ACTUAL VISION. SO,
COLLEAGUES, LET'S MOVE FORWARD.
WE'VE BEEN IN THE TRENCHES OF
INDECISION FOR A DECADE, AND
PLEASE VOTE YES. COUNCILOR
THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME,
COUNCIL COLLEAGUES. COUNCILOR
ZIMMERMAN.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SO
I JUST WANT TO LAY OUT A FEW
QUESTIONS. AS YOU KNOW, IF THIS
WERE TO GO FORWARD, A
RESOLUTION TO ENGAGE IN A STUDY,
THE QUESTIONS THAT ARE REALLY
ON MY MIND IS, WHY DOES THE
CITY HAVE TO HAVE AN OWNERSHIP
STAKE MOVING FORWARD? I
ACTUALLY DON'T UNDERSTAND THAT.
SO I WOULD NEED THAT DEFINED
AND UNDERSTOOD AS WE GO FORWARD.
THE THE CAPITAL STACK IS
SOMETHING THAT I'M VERY
INTERESTED IN. I KNOW THAT THE
NOTE OF 12.5 WAS MENTIONED
EARLIER, BUT 12.5 OUT OF 450 IS
NOT A NUMBER I THINK IS
SIGNIFICANT IN TERMS OF GETTING
SOMETHING OVER. SO WHAT THAT
REALLY LOOKS LIKE ON TOP OF THE
STATE BONDS IS SOMETHING THAT
I'M I'M CURIOUS ABOUT. YOU KNOW,
I HAVE READ THIS NOW TIMES TO
THE POINT WHERE MY EYES ARE
BLURRING A LITTLE BIT TO ENSURE
THAT THERE IS NO COMMITMENT,
FULLY COMMITMENT OF MONEY IN
THIS. AND THAT'S WHAT I'M
SEEING. SO I'M LEANING TOWARDS
>> SUPPORTED THIS, MOSTLY
BECAUSE I AM A BELIEVER IN
GETTING IN THE ROOM TO FIGURE
OUT IF THIS CAN BE A THING OR
IF IT CAN'T. AND RIGHT NOW, ONE
OF THE DISAPPOINTING THINGS
ABOUT THIS ENTIRE EXPERIENCE
HAS BEEN THE THE LACK OF, OF
COHERENT ALIGNED MESSAGE OR
STORY OR WHAT COULD BE. AND I
THINK THERE'S A LOT OF WORK TO
BE DONE THERE ON THE PSU SIDE,
ON THE CITY SIDE. AND I HOPE ON
THE COMMUNITY SIDE. ONE OF MY
COLLEAGUES SAID TO ME, GOD, I
WISH YOU WERE ONE OF THOSE
THEATER GAYS. AND I THINK THAT
WAS PROBABLY BECAUSE THEY HOPED
I WAS MORE FIRED UP ON THIS
TOPIC. AND, AND I TAKE THAT IN
STRIDE BECAUSE I RECOGNIZE I
DON'T KNOW A LOT ABOUT. IS
PORTLAND RIGHT? FOR AN 18 OR
3900 PERSON THEATER? I DON'T
ACTUALLY WANT TO KNOW, LIKE,
THAT'S NOT MY WHEELHOUSE. WHAT
I'M LOOKING FOR. PEOPLE WHO DO
KNOW THAT INDUSTRY DO KNOW HOW
WE DO THE THING THAT COUNCIL
PRESIDENT JUST MENTIONED, WHICH
IS NOT GO DARK FOR FIVE YEARS.
THAT'S WHAT I'M INTERESTED IN.
SO I SAID IN COMMITTEE THAT
DESPITE NOT FULLY UNDERSTANDING
THE MARKET OF DIFFERENT THEATER,
THAT I LOOKED AT THE ROLE OF
BUILDING SOMETHING IS, IS, IS
GOOD IN TERMS OF I'M A I'M IN
FAVOR OF CRANES IN THE AIR
RIGHT NOW. I AM SO CONCERNED
ABOUT OUR ECONOMIC POSITION,
OUR WORKFORCE, THAT IF OUR
ENGAGING IN A NEGOTIATION GETS
PSU OR. I GUESS THE WORD I WANT
TO THINK OF IS ENABLES PSU,
THEN I'M OPEN TO THAT AT THIS.
AT THIS POINT, I WILL BE FULLY
INVESTED IN UNDERSTANDING WHAT
THE COMMITMENT WILL BE IF IT
COMES BACK LATER IN THE YEAR,
LIKE COUNCIL VICE PRESIDENT
MENTIONED, BUT I. I WANT TO
JUST KEEP IN MIND, LIKE I'M NOT
TAKING VOTES TO BUILD MATH
CENTERS, ENGINEERING LABS,
HISTORY, BUILDINGS. SO THE
QUESTION ABOUT WHY IS PORTLAND
INVOLVED IN PORTLAND STATE'S
PERFORMING ARTS CENTER REMAINS
A BIG QUESTION THAT SHOULD BE
ANSWERED IN THIS. AND I HOPE
THAT IT WILL BE. AND I AND I
HAVE FAITH IN TALKING WITH SOME
CITY FOLKS THAT THAT WE CAN GET
TO THAT POINT. BUT I DO THINK
THAT IF WE ARE ABLE TO ENABLE
ANOTHER MAJOR ORGANIZATION TO
DO A BIG THING, THEN WE SHOULD
BE OPEN TO THAT. AND SO WHILE
THIS HAS BEEN A FRUSTRATING
EXPERIENCE, I AM STILL LEANING
TOWARD A YES VOTE AT THIS POINT,
AND LARGELY BECAUSE I
APPRECIATE COUNCIL VICE
PRESIDENT WHO BROUGHT FORWARD
AN AMENDMENT IN COMMITTEE TO
CONCURRENT THIS WITH A KELLER
FUTURE, BECAUSE A KELLER FUTURE
WAS PARAMOUNTLY IMPORTANT TO ME,
AND I SAW HER PUT THAT IN AND I.
AND I THINK THIS RESOLUTION NOW
DOES THAT. AND SO THIS HAS BEEN
COMPLICATED. I WANTED TO SHARE
SOME THOUGHTS, BUT THAT'S WHERE
I'M AT. AND I'M STILL LEANING
TOWARD A YES ON THAT. AND I
APPRECIATE IT. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH,
COUNCILOR ZIMMERMAN. WE HAVE.
KANAL. PIRTLE-GUINEY. AND THEN
SMITH. SO. COUNCILOR KANAL.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT.
I THINK, YOU KNOW, THE THING
THAT EACH DECISION WE MAKE IS
GOING TO HAVE SOME PROBLEM. AND
THE PROBLEM I HAVEN'T YET BEEN
ABLE TO SOLVE IS GOING TO
CHANGE DEPENDING ON AS AS THIS
CONVERSATION EVOLVES, RIGHT. SO.
I REALLY I WANTED TO ANSWER
COUNCILOR AVALOS QUESTION. YOU
KNOW, WHEN WE STARTED ENGAGING
WITH THIS, IT WAS ALREADY POST
AMENDMENT, BUT THE AMENDMENTS
ARE, ARE GOOD. AND I NOTICED IN
THE DOCUMENT, IT DOES SAY
MULTIPLE TIMES THAT THIS
DOESN'T COMMIT AND THERE'LL BE
A PROCESS FOR MONEY. I DO WANT
TO ACKNOWLEDGE THAT. AND SOME
OF THAT IS IS A RELATION TO THE
AMENDMENTS. AND I THINK WHAT
WHAT EVERYONE'S SEEING HERE IS
JUST A TRUST GAP BETWEEN THE
ADMINISTRATION AND THE COUNCIL
ON WHETHER OR NOT WE ACTUALLY
ARE ANYTHING MORE THAN AN
ADVISORY COMMITTEE TO THE MAYOR.
AND THAT'S BEEN THE SAME
CONVERSATION WE'VE HAD FOR A
WHILE. AND I WOULD HOPE THAT
THE MEDIA IN THIS ROOM ACTUALLY
TALK ABOUT THAT, BECAUSE IT HAS
NOT BEEN DISCUSSED ENOUGH. I
ALSO WANT TO SAY THAT THAT
COUNCILOR CLARK'S AMENDMENT HAS
BEEN A GOOD KIND OF
COMPLICATION TO THIS FOR ME,
BECAUSE I DO APPRECIATE THAT IT
DIDN'T COMMIT US FULLY TO ONLY
GOING DOWN THE PSU PATH, BUT
ALSO LOOKING AT WHAT WE HAVE TO
DO TO RETAIN THE KELLER, AT
LEAST FOR THE FIVE YEARS, BUT
ALSO IN A SMALLER STATE GOING
FORWARD. AND I'M PERSONALLY
VERY INTERESTED IN THIS. I HAD
THE PRIVILEGE. I LIVED IN NEW
YORK FOR A LITTLE BIT, GOT A
CHANCE TO SEE, LIKE THE PLAY
CALLED GRACE ON BROADWAY.
OBVIOUSLY A BIG SUPPORTER OF
PSU. I'M A PORTLANDER BECAUSE
MY DAD GOT INTO PSU AND WENT TO
GRAD SCHOOL HERE. THAT'S WHY MY
FAMILY LIVES HERE. I THINK THAT
THE CHALLENGE I'M DEALING WITH
RIGHT NOW IS PSU IS A STATE
UNIVERSITY, AND THE STATE IS
RESTRICTING OUR ABILITY TO DO
TAXATION AT THE LEVEL THAT WE
MIGHT WANT TO. IF WE. THE IF
YOU LOOK AT THE FORECLOSURE
PLACES WHERE WE HAVE. ON
TODAY'S AGENDA ON PORTLAND MAPS,
YOU'RE GOING TO SEE A LOT OF
PROPERTY TAX ASSESSMENT LEVELS
THAT ARE MUCH LOWER THAN THE
MARKET VALUE. AND IF WE WERE
ABLE TO GET OUT FROM MEASURE
FIVE AND 50, WE WOULD BE ABLE
TO PAY FOR THINGS LIKE THIS
EASILY. THE REASON THAT
PORTLAND IS, HAS HAS HAD
DIFFICULTY TAKING BIG SWINGS IS
LARGELY BECAUSE OF STATE
RESTRICTION. AND IT'S HARD FOR
ME TO TRY AND MOVE. TAXATION
AUTHORITY CONTINUALLY GOES UP
THE LEVELS OF GOVERNMENT. WHILE
THE OBLIGATION TO PAY FOR
THINGS IS BEING PUSHED DOWN.
THAT'S REALLY A FRUSTRATION I
HAVE, AND I'M GRATEFUL TO SEE
SOME COLLEAGUES NODDING ALONG
HERE, AND I'M STRUGGLING WITH
THAT. AND SO I THINK MAYBE I'D
FEEL DIFFERENTLY ABOUT THIS IF
THIS WAS NOT RIGHT NOW. BECAUSE
WE'RE BROKE. AND I THINK IT'S
IMPORTANT THAT WE JUST SAY THAT.
AND SOME OF MY COLLEAGUES HAVE
TOO. I JUST DON'T KNOW HOW WE
PAY FOR THIS. SO THAT'S WHY I'M
LEANING TOWARDS A NO VOTE. I
WOULD LOVE TO HAVE THIS HAPPEN.
I'M VERY SUPPORTIVE OF IT. I
JUST DON'T KNOW HOW WE GET THE
MONEY TO GO AROUND. I DID WANT
TO FLAG ONE THING FOR LATER.
THIS IS I LEARNED TODAY ABOUT
ANOTHER INTERESTING TIMING
THING ABOUT A NOVEMBER 2024
COMMITMENT MADE BY THE CITY
ADMINISTRATION TO TO THIS
PROJECT, AND I CANNOT. I
UNDERSTAND THAT THE BUSINESS OF
THE CITY DOESN'T PAUSE FOR TWO
MONTHS AFTER AN ELECTION AND
BEFORE PEOPLE TAKE OVER. BUT
THE IDEA THAT AFTER THAT
ELECTION, WE WOULD BE
COMMITTING TO THIS AFTER AN
ELECTION THAT THAT GOT RID OF
4/5 OF THE SITTING CITY COUNCIL,
PUT 11/12 OF THE NEW COUNCIL IN
AND A NEW MAYOR. THE IDEA THAT
WE'D BE MAKING BIG COMMITMENTS
FOR YEARS AND YEARS AND YEARS,
WHICH WE SAW THE DAY AFTER THE
ELECTION, WE EXTENDED DOWNTOWN
CLEAN AND SAFE AS WELL. THERE'S
A LOT OF BIG COMMITMENTS THAT
WERE MADE TO TRY AND TIE OUR
HANDS. AND SO I WOULD HOPE THAT
WE'RE ALL EXERCISING THOUGHT
BASED ON OUR OWN OPINIONS ON IT
AS WE PURSUE THIS, BUT THAT I
JUST WANTED TO FLAG THAT
BECAUSE AT SOME POINT, WE'RE
GOING TO HAVE TO NEED TO WE'RE
GOING TO NEED TO DO OVERSIGHT
ON JUST THAT SEVEN, EIGHT WEEK
PERIOD. AND ALL THE THINGS THAT
THE, THE TRANSITION TRIED TO
TIE OUR HANDS ON, BECAUSE
THAT'S UNACCEPTABLE. GETTING
BACK TO THIS, I WANT TO REALLY
APPRECIATE THE TESTIFIERS FROM
LAST WEEK. IT REALLY HELPED
WITH ME AS I'VE BEEN THINKING
ABOUT IT, AND PARTICULAR THE
FOLKS FROM HALPERN, IN
PARTICULAR THE FOLKS FROM ETSY
AS WELL, AND REALLY
COMPLICATING IT. THERE'S NOT AN
EASY ANSWER TO THIS ONE. SO
THAT'S WHY I KEEP SAYING I'M
LEANING, BUT I'M LOOKING
FORWARD TO HEARING EVERYBODY
ELSE'S BEFORE WE TAKE A VOTE ON
THIS. THANKS.
>> THANK YOU, THANK YOU.
>> COUNCILOR KANAL. COUNCILOR.
PIRTLE-GUINEY. AND THEN IT'LL
BE SMITH AND RYAN. SO.
COUNCILOR. PIRTLE-GUINEY.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT
COLLEAGUES, WE BUILD FOR OUR
FUTURE. WE BUILD THE BIKE
INFRASTRUCTURE FOR THE
RIDERSHIP. WE KNOW FUTURE
PORTLAND MUST HAVE. WE BUILD
TRANSIT ORIENTED HOUSING AND
DENSITY WITH LESS PARKING FOR
THE FUTURE PORTLAND. WE KNOW WE
WILL HAVE. WE ALSO MUST BUILD
OUT OUR ARTS VENUES FOR THE
FUTURE. WE WANT. I WANT A
FUTURE PORTLAND THAT HAS A MORE
PRACTICAL, PRACTICAL, WORKABLE,
LARGE SCALE SEATED VENUE. I
ALSO WANT A FUTURE PORTLAND
WITH VENUES FOR OUR SMALLEST
THEATER COMPANIES, WHERE WE AS
A CITY, SUPPORT ARTS THAT TELL
ALL OF OUR STORIES AND LIFT UP
THE FUTURE. ACTORS AND
PLAYWRIGHTS AND DANCERS AND
MUSICIANS AND SINGERS AND
UNDEFINABLE PERFORMANCE ARTISTS
WHO GOT THEIR START HERE. WE
HAVE TO BUILD THAT FUTURE NOW,
AND WE HAVE TO BUILD IT WHILE
ACKNOWLEDGING THE MONEY WE HAVE
TODAY. AND THAT'S WHY WE'RE
HERE. THAT'S WHY WE HAVE THIS
RESOLUTION BEFORE US. IF WE
WEREN'T KEEPING AN EYE ON OUR
BOTTOM LINE, WE WOULD BE IN
NEGOTIATIONS AS A CITY FOR TWO
LARGE SCALE VENUES. BUT WE
CAN'T WE CAN'T SUPPORT THAT.
INSTEAD, WE HAVE A PROPOSAL
THAT WILL ALLOW US TO ENTER
INTO CONVERSATIONS WITH A
PARTNER, WITH A STATED GOAL OF
CREATING A NEW 3000 SEAT VENUE,
WHILE ALSO USING THE
OPPORTUNITY WE HAVE OF THE
KELLER TO FILL IN THE GAPS IN
OUR THEATER ECOSYSTEM THAT
AREN'T FILLED NOW IN A
REVITALIZED FUTURE. KELLER. WE
CAN DO THIS, AND FRANKLY, WE
CAN DO IT WITH A PLA ALREADY
NEGOTIATED ON THE PROJECT, A
TIMELINE THAT ENSURES FOLKS WHO
WORK IN OUR PERFORMING ARTS
VENUES DON'T LOSE HOURS LOSING
PAY AND POTENTIALLY LOSING
HEALTH CARE WHILE WE DO IT. WE
CAN DO IT WITH A PARTNER WHO'S
COMMITTED TO THOSE THINGS. WE
HAVE COLLECTIVELY AS A BODY. A
LOT OF QUESTIONS WE NEED
ANSWERED. PORTLAND HAS
COLLECTIVELY AS A CITY, A LOT
OF QUESTIONS WE NEED ANSWERED.
I APPRECIATE THE AMENDMENTS TO
STRENGTHEN THIS PROPOSAL, THE
AMENDMENTS THAT STRENGTHEN THE
COMMITMENT TO THE KELLER AND TO
BEING DELIBERATE ABOUT FUNDING
DECISIONS, BECAUSE WE MUST BE
CAREFUL HOW WE BALANCE OUR
FUTURE NEEDS AND OUR CURRENT
ABILITIES THAT WE DEBATED AND
ADOPTED IN COMMITTEE. BUT I
WANT TO TALK ABOUT THE COST OF
A NO VOTE IN ACTION TODAY MEANS
WE ARE TELLING THE
ADMINISTRATION, NO, NO, DON'T
ENTER INTO CONVERSATIONS WITH
PSU COLLEAGUES. THINK ABOUT THE
VISION COUNCILOR DUNPHY PAINTED
FOR US JUST A MOMENT AGO.
PRESIDENT DUNPHY, I APOLOGIZE.
>> ALL GOOD.
>> THINK ABOUT WHAT FUTURE
PORTLAND NEEDS TO OFFER. WHAT
OPPORTUNITIES DO WE WANT
AVAILABLE FOR BUDDING ARTISTS
ACROSS OUR CITY? ARE WE WILLING
TO CLOSE THE DOOR ON THIS? I AM
NOT WILLING TO CLOSE THAT DOOR
TODAY. I THINK WE NEED TO TELL
THE ADMINISTRATION TO START THE
WORK, AND WE NEED TO LAY OUT
OUR CONDITIONS AND COLLEAGUES.
WE HAVE DONE THAT IN THE
CONVERSATIONS WE HAD IN
COMMITTEE, THE AMENDMENTS THAT
WERE ADOPTED THERE, AND THE
CONVERSATIONS WE HAVE HAD ON
THIS DAIS TODAY. WE HAVE MADE
OUR CONDITIONS CLEAR ON THE
RECORD. LET'S TELL THE
ADMINISTRATION TO HAVE THE
CONVERSATION. LET'S TELL THEM
TO DO THE WORK TO ANSWER OUR
QUESTIONS. LET'S TELL THEM TO
FIGURE OUT HOW WE CAN BUILD THE
FUTURE. WE KNOW OUR CITY CAN
AND SHOULD HAVE. AND LET'S TELL
THEM TO FIGURE OUT HOW TO DO
THAT WITHIN OUR MEANS. IF WE
TAKE A YES VOTE TODAY, THAT IS
WHAT WE ARE SAYING. IF WE TAKE
A NO VOTE, WE'RE CLOSING THE
DOOR ON WHAT OUR ARTS ECOSYSTEM
LOOKS LIKE IN FUTURE PORTLAND.
I HOPE WE CAN SUPPORT THIS HERE
TODAY. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU.
>> COUNCILOR PIRTLE-GUINEY
COUNCILOR SMITH, THEN RYAN,
THEN MORILLO. SO COUNCILOR
SMITH.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT.
I AM REALLY TOO CONCERNED ABOUT
WHERE WE GET THE MONEY FROM,
BUT I APPRECIATE YOU LAYING
THIS OUT. COUNCILOR.
PIRTLE-GUINEY. BECAUSE IT IT
REALLY DOES MAKE A DIFFERENCE.
AND I HEAR WHAT YOU'RE SAYING
THAT WE'RE SAYING TO THE ARTS
COMMUNITY THAT WE DON'T CARE.
AND THAT'S NOT SO THAT'S NOT
WHO WE ARE UP HERE. AND SO YOU
ALL HAVE GIVEN ME SOMETHING TO,
TO THINK ABOUT. AND I SUPPORT
COUNCILOR AVALOS AMENDMENT SO
THAT WE'RE MAKING CRYSTAL CLEAR
THAT WE ARE NOT MAKING A
COMMITMENT TO DOLLARS TODAY.
AND COUNCIL PRESIDENT, I KNOW
THAT THIS HAS BEEN A A PRIORITY
OF YOURS FOR A LONG TIME, AND I
GET IT. I WILL EXPECT TO SEE
THOSE APPRENTICESHIPS AND ALL
THE THINGS TO MAKING SURE THAT
PEOPLE IN OUR DISTRICT ARE
BEING ABLE TO TAKE ADVANTAGE OF
THIS OPPORTUNITY, BECAUSE IT
MEANS A LOT FROM PARKROSE, FROM
DAVID DOUGLAS, FROM REYNOLDS. I
WANT THE FOLKS IN OUR NECK OF
THE WOODS, AND WHEN I SAY NECK
OF THE WOODS, IT IS NECK OF THE
WOODS THAT THEY HAVE AN
OPPORTUNITY TO HAVE AN
OPPORTUNITY. SO THANK YOU FOR
BRINGING THIS FORWARD.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR SMITH,
COUNCILOR RYAN, THEN MORILLO,
THEN AVALOS. COUNCILOR RYAN.
>> YEAH. THANK YOU. THANK YOU,
COUNCIL PRESIDENT. FIRST,
CONGRATULATIONS TO PORTLAND
STATE UNIVERSITY ON BUILDING A
NEW STUDENT CENTERED
PERFORMANCE HALL. I WAS SO
HAPPY THAT YOU WERE SUCCESSFUL
IN THE LAST LEGISLATIVE SESSION.
THAT WAS PARTLY WHY WE TOOK THE
PAUSE WAS TO LET THAT GET
WORKED OUT. IT'S REALLY GREAT
NEWS FOR THE STUDENTS AT YOUR
FINE UNIVERSITY. I'M THRILLED
WITH THAT. I RESPECT AND
PERSONALLY KNOW ADVOCATES ON
BOTH SIDES OF THIS CONVERSATION.
IN MY CAREER, I SPENT NINE
YEARS AT PORTLAND STATE'S
DEVELOPMENT FOUNDATION OFFICES.
IN FACT, MY FIRST POSITION WAS
IN THE SCHOOL OF FINE AND
PERFORMING ARTS PERFORMING ARTS.
THE FIRST DEVELOPMENT DIRECTOR
THAT WAS HIRED IS A COUPLE
DECADES AGO AND A COUPLE OF
YEARS RAISING FUNDS AT OREGON
BALLET THEATER. IF I WAS
HOLDING THOSE POSITIONS, I
WOULD PROBABLY ADVOCATE FOR A
YES VOTE TODAY. TODAY, I'M A
MEMBER OF THE PORTLAND CITY
COUNCIL. DURING A TIME OF DE
ESCALATING VALUE OF COMMERCIAL
PROPERTIES, A STRUGGLING
ECONOMY, AND ESCALATING
DEFERRED MAINTENANCE OF OUR
ASSETS, ABANDONING THE KELLER
AND OUR PARTNERS AT THE HALPRIN
SEQUENCE. THANK YOU TO ALL. TO
ALL THE HARD WORKING HALPRIN
SEQUENCE VOLUNTEERS WHO HAVE
BEEN AT THE TABLE LONGER THAN
ANYONE IN THIS ROOM, FIGHTING
FOR THE FUTURE OF OUR
PERFORMING ARTS CENTER, AND WE
WOULD ABANDON THAT AND JUMP
INTO BUILDING A NEW FACILITY
THAT WILL ADD TO OUR DEFERRED
MAINTENANCE. BOTH CHOICES OFFER
A VISION FOR THE FUTURE OF ARTS
IN OUR CITY. I ENVISION A FULL
RESTORATION OF OUR CURRENT
ASSET, KELLER PERFORMANCE HALL,
ACROSS FROM OUR WORLD RENOWNED
PUBLIC ART JEWEL, THE FORECOURT
FOUNTAIN. SOME PEOPLE CALL IT
KELLER, LOCATED IN THE CORE OF
OUR DOWNTOWN THAT HAS PARKING,
HOTELS AND RESTAURANTS. I DON'T
WANT THAT AREA TO GO DARK, AND
KELLER IS IN THE DRIVER OF FOOT
TRAFFIC. ALSO, FOR THAT CORE
PART OF DOWNTOWN, I HAVE FAITH
WE CAN BE CREATIVE SCRAPPING
INNOVATIVE TO BOTH PRODUCE
BROADWAY DURING THAT YEAR OF
CONSTRUCTION AND IN. SO
PORTLAND OPERA WILL CONTINUE TO
BE SUBSIDIZED BY THE TRAVELING
BROADWAY SHOWS. AND I HAVE
CONFIDENCE THAT WE WILL BE TRUE
TO THE LABORERS DURING
CONSTRUCTION. AS SUCH, THE
ORIGIN OF THIS RESOLUTION IS
BASED ON THE FEAR OF US NOT
TAKING CARE OF BUSINESS DURING
CONSTRUCTION, AND THE FANTASY
THAT WE'LL FIND $1 BILLION FOR
TWO NEW LARGE SCALE PERFORMANCE
HALLS THAT ARE NOT NEEDED, AS
CONFIRMED BY STAFF TODAY. TIME
TO BE REASONABLE AND IMPROVE ON
WHAT WE ARE ALREADY RESPONSIBLE
FOR, AND NOT ADD FURTHER
GOVERNMENT INDUCED BLIGHT TO A
CORE AREA OF DOWNTOWN. I WILL
BE VOTING NO ON THIS RESOLUTION.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR RYAN,
COUNCILORS MORILLO AVALOS AND
THEN CLARK. SO. COUNCILOR
MORILLO.
>> HI. THANK YOU SO MUCH. I
HAVE A QUESTION FOR THE CITY
ATTORNEY AND I'LL TRY TO BE
QUICK. COUNCIL PRESIDENT, I
APOLOGIZE. THE FIRE ALARM WENT
OFF IN MY BUILDING DURING THE
EARLIER QUESTION PORTION. I
COULDN'T ASK IT. SO IS THERE A
CITY ATTORNEY THAT'S COMING UP
RIGHT NOW?
>> YEAH.
>> THANK YOU. SO I'LL KEEP
TALKING WHILE THAT PERSON IS
GOING UP. BUT I JUST WANT TO
SAY THAT CONTRARY TO WHAT
COUNCILOR NOVICK STATED IN HIS
INQUIRY, I'M NOT WORRIED THAT
PSU IS GOING TO SUE FOR A
CERTAIN DOLLAR AMOUNT AND
POTENTIALLY WIN. THE QUESTION I
HAVE IS ACTUALLY MORE AROUND
THE EXECUTIVE AUTHORITY,
BECAUSE WE SAW THAT WITH THE
TENNIS CENTER. WE WERE TOLD AS
COUNCIL, THE EXECUTIVE WAS NOT
GOING TO MOVE FORWARD IN A
CERTAIN WAY. AND THEN THEY DID
THAT WITHOUT US, REGARDLESS OF
WHAT WE HAD INTENDED. WHEN WE
APPROVED AN AMENDMENT. SO THE
QUESTION TO ME ON EXECUTIVE
AUTHORITY AND WHETHER WHAT WE
ARE APPROVING TODAY EMPOWERS
THE EXECUTIVE TO TAKE CERTAIN
STEPS WITHOUT COUNCIL
CONSULTING CONSULTATION IS WHAT
I'M ASKING FOR. ARE THERE ANY
STEPS THAT THE EXECUTIVE CAN
TAKE AS A RESULT OF THIS
RESOLUTION BEING APPROVED THAT
WOULD BIND COUNCIL?
>> THE. THE STEPS THAT THE.
THIS IS ROBERT TAYLOR, THE CITY
ATTORNEY. THE STEPS THAT THE
COUNCIL COULD TAKE WOULD BE
CONSTRAINED BY THE TERMS OF
THIS RESOLUTION. THIS
RESOLUTION SAYS EXPLICITLY THAT
THAT NO FUNDING IS BEING
COMMITTED. AND SO THIS IS A
DIFFERENT CIRCUMSTANCE THAN THE
TENNIS CENTER SITUATION. BUT IN
TERMS OF THIS THIS ACTION, IT
REALLY IS AS AS DCA OLIVEIRA
DESCRIBED, IT IS JUST THE
CHOICE OF COUNCIL. DO WE WANT
TO PURSUE MORE DUE DILIGENCE ON
THE PSU PROJECT? BUT IT'S NOT A
COMMITMENT TO ACTUALLY GO
THROUGH WITH IT. IT'S NOT A
COMMITMENT TO FUND IT. IT'S NOT
AN AUTHORIZATION TO DO ANYTHING
MORE THAN THAT.
>> OKAY. I THINK WHEN WE WENT
THROUGH THE TENNIS CENTER
DEBACLE, EVEN THOUGH IT'S NOT
THE SAME, IT'S SIMILAR BECAUSE
THE AMENDMENT WE APPROVED DID
NOT BIND US INTO PRIVATIZING
OUR CITY ASSETS. AND THEN
THAT'S EXACTLY WHAT HAPPENED
WITHOUT REALLY A LOT OF
CONSULTATION OR DISCUSSION FROM
COUNCIL OR, FRANKLY, FROM OUR
CONSTITUENTS. SO THE PAUSE THAT
I HAVE IN THIS ENTIRE
DISCUSSION IS ACTUALLY NOT
BECAUSE OF PSU. I THINK THEY'VE
DONE A REALLY GOOD JOB TRYING
TO GET THE CAPITAL STACK. SHOW
US THAT THEY ARE COMMITTED TO
FINDING THAT FUNDING ELSEWHERE.
AND I SHARE THE CONCERNS THAT
MY OTHER COLLEAGUES HAVE TALKED
ABOUT THE LONGEVITY OF THE ARTS
IN OUR CITY, AND WHAT THIS CAN
DO FOR STUDENTS. I'M MORE
CONCERNED ABOUT HOW OUR
EXECUTIVE IS INTERACTING WITH
THE COUNCIL, THE LEGISLATIVE
BODY. SO I GUESS A FOLLOW UP
QUESTION ON THAT IS, DOES THIS
RESOLUTION ALLOW FOR THE
EXECUTIVE TO TAKE STEPS THAT
ARE GOING TO BIND US
FINANCIALLY IN THE FUTURE,
INCLUDING HOW THE EXECUTIVE IS
ALLOWED TO ENGAGE ON THIS?
>> NOT AGAIN, THE THE THE SCOPE
OF THE EXECUTIVE AUTHORITY
WOULD BE LIMITED BY THE TERMS
OF THE THE RESOLUTION, THE.
UNDER THE CHARTER, THE MAYOR
HAS AUTHORITY TO EXECUTE
CONTRACTS CONSISTENT WITH THE
BUDGET. SO IF FUNDS HAVE BEEN
BEEN BUDGETED, THEY COULD
EXECUTE THOSE CONTRACTS. IF A
CONTRACT IS EXECUTED AND THERE
IS NO BUDGET AUTHORITY FOR IT,
THEN THE CONTRACT NEEDS TO BE
EXPLICIT THAT COUNCIL AT ANY
TIME CAN DECLINE TO FUND THE
COMMITMENTS IN THE CONTRACT. SO
FOR FOR THIS RESOLUTION, IT IS
VERY EXPLICIT IN THE ONE OF THE
BE IT RESOLVED SECTIONS THAT
THIS RESOLUTION DOES NOT COMMIT
ANY FUNDING TO THE TO THE
ULTIMATE DEVELOPMENT. SO I
THINK THIS IS VERY, VERY CLEAR
IN MY MIND AS FAR AS LIMITING
THE EXECUTIVE'S AUTHORITY TO
MAKE ANY FINANCIAL COMMITMENT.
>> OKAY. THANK YOU, CITY
ATTORNEY. I APPRECIATE YOU
PUTTING THAT ON THE RECORD, AND
I THINK WE'LL BE ABLE TO PULL
THAT ON LATER IF WE NEED TO. I.
IT'S NOT LOST ON ME THAT WE'RE
BEING ASKED TO APPROVE THIS.
KELLER MODA. I THINK VERY SOON
WE'RE GOING TO BE ASKED TO MAKE
UPGRADES TO THE TIMBER STADIUM
AS WELL IN THE COMING YEARS.
AND SO WE HAVE A LOT OF MAJOR
INFRASTRUCTURE PROJECTS THAT WE
ARE BEING ASKED TO FIND SUPPORT
FOR THAT WE DON'T REALLY HAVE
FUNDING FOR AT THE CITY. WE
HAVE LAID OFF A TON OF
EMPLOYEES, WE HAVE CUT CORE
SERVICES AND FRANKLY, OUR CITY
IS BEING HACKED UP AND BEING
SOLD FOR PARTS, INCLUDING WHAT
THE TENNIS CENTER. AND SO I
HAVE A LOT OF CONCERNS ABOUT
ALL OF THIS LONG TERM. WHAT I
AM HEARING FROM THE CITY
ATTORNEY IS THAT THIS IS SIMPLY
GOING TO BE A CONVENING TO TRY
TO FIGURE OUT SOME DIFFERENT
OPTIONS FOR THAT. SO WHAT I
WANT TO SAY ON THE RECORD RIGHT
NOW IS THAT I AM OKAY WITH
INVESTIGATING OPTIONS, BUT I AM
NOT OKAY WITH BEING FINANCIALLY
OR POLITICALLY BOUND TO APPROVE
THIS LATER DOWN THE LINE. IF IT
TURNS OUT THE CITY DOES NOT
HAVE THOSE FUNDS BECAUSE I. I
AM VERY WORRIED THAT WE ARE
BEING CONSTANTLY PUT IN THIS
POLITICAL POSITION OF APPROVING
THINGS AND SAYING, DON'T WORRY
ABOUT IT. YOU'RE NOT BOUND TO
IT. BUT REALLY, WE ARE BEING
POLITICALLY BOUND TO IT IN SOME
WAYS. SO I'M STILL QUITE TORN
ON THIS, ACTUALLY. BUT I DO
CARE ABOUT THE FUTURE OF THE
ARTS AND THE WORKERS AT THESE
STADIUMS THAT ARE GOING TO BE
POTENTIALLY PUT OUT OF WORK. SO
THAT'S WHERE I'M AT RIGHT NOW.
BUT I APPRECIATE YOU CLARIFYING
THAT. CITY ATTORNEY ROBERT
TAYLOR, AND I HOPE THE
EXECUTIVE HAS HEARD US LOUD AND
CLEAR ON THIS AS WELL.
>> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU, COUNSELOR MORILLO.
I HAVE AVALOS, THEN CLERK, THEN
GREEN. SO COUNSELOR AVALOS.
>> THANK YOU. IF THIS IF YOU
COULD SAY HI. IF THIS
RESOLUTION DOESN'T PASS, WILL
WHAT AUTHORITY DO YOU THINK THE
CITY HAS. IF THIS DOES NOT PASS?
LIKE. WILL THE WORK TO SCOPE
AND TALK WITH PSU STILL MOVE
FORWARD OR WILL IT END BECAUSE
THEY'RE WAITING FOR THIS
RESOLUTION TO PASS?
>> I THINK THAT'S A GREAT
QUESTION. I THINK THAT THAT
THAT. PERHAPS DCA OLIVEIRA
MIGHT BE BETTER EQUIPPED TO
ANSWER THAT IN THE IN THE SENSE
THAT. THE ADMINISTRATION THEY
CAN STILL HAVE CONVERSATIONS,
THEY CAN STILL ENGAGE IN DUE
DILIGENCE IF THEY CHOOSE TO DO
THAT OR NOT. THE I THINK THE
BIND, THE BIND THAT THEY FEEL
THEMSELVES IN IS THEY DON'T
WANT TO GO TOO FAR DOWN A PATH
IF THEY DON'T FEEL LIKE THERE'S
MAJORITY COUNCIL SUPPORT FOR
SOMETHING, THEY DON'T WANT TO
WASTE THEIR TIME. THEY DON'T
WANT TO WASTE THE COMMUNITY'S
TIME. THEY DON'T WANT TO WASTE
THEIR PARTNER'S TIME. AND, AND,
AND SO THEY, THEY KIND OF JUST
WANT TO KNOW, IS THE GAME WORTH
THE CANDLE HERE? DO WE WANT TO
GO DOWN THIS ROAD OR NOT?
THAT'S WHAT THEY'RE HOPING TO
GET FROM COUNCIL IS A SENSE OF
ARE WE OKAY GOING DOWN THIS
ROAD.
>> AND WHEN.
>> AND IF AND IF AND IF COUNCIL
REJECTS THIS OR DOESN'T APPROVE
IT, THEN I THINK THE
ADMINISTRATION IS, IS, IS WHERE
THEY WERE TWO WEEKS AGO, WHICH
IS WELL, WE DON'T REALLY KNOW.
WE'RE KIND OF STUCK RIGHT NOW
AND THEY'RE NOT SURE WHAT TO DO.
THEY'RE NOT SURE IF THERE'S
SUPPORT. AND I THINK THAT'S
WHAT THEY'RE HOPING TO GET FROM
COUNCIL IS JUST A SENSE OF IS
IT WORTH GOING DOWN THIS PATH
OR NOT?
>> SO THEY'RE LOOKING FOR
COUNCIL SUPPORT, OF GOING DOWN
A PATH OF EXPLORING AND GETTING
THE NUMBERS AND YADA YADA. AND
ALSO, PER THE AMENDMENTS AND
THE WAY THAT IT'S CURRENTLY
WRITTEN, THAT IT WON'T HAVE
FINANCIAL COMMITMENTS. NOW, YOU
KEEP SAYING THAT, YOU KNOW, PER
CHARTER, THE MAYOR AND CITY
ADMINISTRATOR HAVE THE
AUTHORITY TO MOVE FORWARD WITH
FUNDS THAT ARE BUDGETED. SO I
GUESS LET ME EXPLICITLY ASK,
ARE THERE FUNDS BUDGETED FOR
ANYTHING RELATED TO THIS?
BECAUSE I KEEP HEARING ABOUT
THIS 44 MILLION. I GENUINELY
DON'T KNOW WHAT THAT 44 MILLION
IS, WHERE IT IS, WHERE IT'S
COMING FROM. SO I GUESS I WANT
TO UNDERSTAND EXPLICITLY, DO
YOU ALL ALREADY FEEL YOU HAVE
AUTHORITY BASED ON SOME MONEY
THAT'S BUDGETED THAT I'M NOT
AWARE OF?
>> THANK YOU FOR THE QUESTION,
COUNCILOR DONNIE OLIVEIRA. WE
DO NOT HAVE ANY RESOURCES
BUDGETED OTHER THAN THE STAFF
TIME NECESSARY TO POTENTIALLY
DO THE WORK. SO THERE'S NOT 44
MILLION SET ASIDE. THERE'S NOT
A RESERVE FUND. NOTHING'S
NOTHING'S BUDGETED.
>> WHAT IS THE 44 MILLION?
>> I THINK WHAT SARAH CAN SPEAK
TO THAT IS JUST A PORTION OF
THE WHAT WAS NECESSARY TO
COMMIT THE THE STATE DOLLARS.
BUT DO YOU WANT TO SPEAK TO
THAT?
>> SURE. SO AS YOU MAY RECALL,
THERE'S A RANGE OF COSTS FOR
THE TOTAL CITY OWNED VENUE
BETWEEN 358 AND $448 MILLION.
WE WERE SIMPLY TRYING TO
ESTABLISH AN INITIAL TARGET,
WHICH WOULD BE 10% OF THE 448
MILLION OF THE CITY'S OWN VENUE
FOR US TO BEGIN WORK TOWARDS,
TO SHOW COMMITMENT ON THE
CITY'S PART, AND ALSO TO GIVE A
SIGN OF CONFIDENCE TO OTHER
FUNDERS THAT WE WOULD LIKE TO
BE IN CONVERSATION WITH, WHO
ARE COMPLETELY ON HOLD UNTIL
THEY HAVE ANY SENSE THAT THE
CITY MIGHT BE MOVING FORWARD.
>> I GUESS THEN MY QUESTION IS,
DO YOU BELIEVE THAT THE CITY
HAS COMMITTED THE WAY THAT I
HEARD THAT IS THAT YOU BELIEVE
THAT THE CITY HAS ALREADY
COMMITTED 10% OF THE CAPITAL
STACK? AM I NOT UNDERSTANDING?
>> NO. NO COMMITMENTS HAVE BEEN
MADE. AND THE REASON WE PUT
THAT FORWARD WAS JUST AS A
TARGET TO START WORKING FOR AS
WE'RE BUILDING THE CAPITAL
STACK. BUT THERE'S NO
COMMITMENT FROM THE CITY OF ANY
PARTICULAR NUMBER. IT WAS JUST
A PLACE TO START AIMING TOWARDS
IN OUR CONVERSATIONS, WHEN WE
CAN GET TOGETHER IN THE ROOM TO
BEGIN FIGURING OUT THE CAPITAL
STACK IN THE EARLY STAGES OF
FUNDING.
>> AND IT IS, IS IT? I GUESS
BECAUSE YOU'RE SAYING IT'S A
PLACE TO START FROM. SO ARE YOU
ALL. IS IT YOUR DESIRE THAT
THAT THE CITY BE 10%? I GUESS I
JUST FEEL LIKE WE KEEP DANCING
AROUND IT. LIKE, DO YOU WANT
THAT 10% OR NOT? IS IT PART OF
THE CAPITAL STACK? IS IT NOT
THE CAPITAL STACK? I GUESS
MAYBE TRYING TO UNDERSTAND WHAT
THE CAPITAL STACK IS. DOES THAT
INCLUDE THE PREDEVELOPMENT OR
IS THE CAPITAL STACK FOR OKAY.
>> THE 44 MILLION SUBTRACTED
OUT OF THE TOTAL COST OF
WHATEVER THE PROJECT FOR THE
CITY OWNED VENUE WOULD
ULTIMATELY BE?
>> SO THEN IS THERE A SCENARIO,
I GUESS, THAT, YOU KNOW,
BECAUSE AGAIN, I KEEP HEARING
THAT'S LIKE WE HAVE, WE WANT
THIS 10%. THAT'S HOW I'M
HEARING IT. BUT IS THERE A
SCENARIO WHERE YOU ALL, AFTER
WE DO ALL THIS, YOU KNOW, WORK
THAT YOU ALL COME BACK AND SAY,
WE FOUND A BILLIONAIRE WHO'S
GOING TO PAY FOR IT ALL. WE
FOUND ALL THESE OTHER SOURCES
OF MONEY. WE'VE GOT FOUNDATIONS,
WE'VE GOT PRIVATE DOLLARS. LIKE,
I GUESS I'M TRYING TO
UNDERSTAND WHAT YOUR INTENT IS,
BECAUSE IF YOUR INTENT IS THAT
I AM GOING TO GO LOOK FOR MONEY
FOR 90% THINKING THAT I'M GOING
TO GET THAT 10% FROM THE CITY.
THAT'S WHAT PEOPLE ARE
CONCERNED ABOUT BECAUSE EVEN
WE'RE TALKING ABOUT 400 MILLION,
BUT EVEN 44 MILLION IS A LOT,
RIGHT? AND I'M NOT PREPARED TO
GIVE 44 MILLION RIGHT NOW OF
THE CITY'S BUDGET, WHEN WE'RE
LOOKING AT PROBABLY ANOTHER 100
MILLION IN A DEFICIT. SO THAT'S
WHY I JUST, I FEEL LIKE I, I'M
GETTING DANCED AROUND AND I
WANT TO UNDERSTAND WHAT IS
Y'ALL'S INTENT FOR WHAT YOU'RE
LOOKING FOR FROM US AT THIS
PHASE? BECAUSE I KEEP HEARING
THAT THERE'S MONEY THAT WE ARE
SUPPOSED TO PUT UP. LIKE FOR
PREDEVELOPMENT.
>> TOTAL INTENT IS TO GET IN A
ROOM AND START FIGURING OUT
WHAT MONEY THERE MAY BE
AVAILABLE AND HOW WE PUT THE
PACKAGE TOGETHER. THE 44
MILLION WAS SIMPLY A TARGET TO
START WORKING TOWARDS AS AN
INITIAL COMMITMENT. THAT WOULD
SIGNAL THAT THE CITY IS ALL IN
ON THE PROJECT, BUT THAT MAY
NOT BE THE NUMBER. AND WHEN WE
GET IN THE ROOM, WE MAY HAVE A
COMPLETELY DIFFERENT PATH. WHEN
I TALK ABOUT OTHER FUNDING
OPPORTUNITIES, THEY ALMOST
ALWAYS ARE GOING TO ASK FOR
SOME SORT OF MATCH FROM THE
CITY BECAUSE AT THIS POINT IN
TIME, THIS IS THE CITY OWNED
VENUE THAT WE WOULD BE
DEVELOPING WITH YOU AS A
PARTNER. SO I DON'T WANT TO
FEEL LIKE THERE'S ANY DANCING
AROUND. WE WOULD FULLY EXPECT
FOR THE CITY TO POTENTIALLY
FUND THE ENTIRE PROJECT. DO WE
THINK THE CITY WILL HAVE TO DO
THAT? NO, WE THINK THERE ARE A
LOT OF DIFFERENT PARTNERSHIPS
THAT ARE AVAILABLE, BUT AGAIN,
THIS RESOLUTION IS OUR FIRST
CHANCE TO HAVE PERMISSION TO
ACTUALLY SPEAK WITH THE FOLKS
WHO CAN HELP US DEVELOP THAT
AND SEE WHAT THE POSSIBILITIES
ARE TO BRING BACK TO YOU. AND I
KNOW THERE'S A LONG LIST OF
QUESTIONS THAT YOU ALL HAVE IN
ADDITION TO JUST SOME OF THESE
NUMBERS. THAT'S WHAT WE WANT TO
DELIVER TO YOU IN VERY SHORT
ORDER TO SEE IF THIS IS A GO OR
NO GO. FOR ALL OF US WHO ARE
INVOLVED.
>> COUNCILOR WE HAVE NOT
COMMITTED ANY NUMBER. WE
HAVEN'T HAD THE CONVERSATION.
THE 44 CAME FROM PSU FROM A
SORT OF A LOGIC TRAIN. THAT
MAKES SENSE, BUT THAT ISN'T
SOMETHING THAT WE'VE
CONTEMPLATED.
>> AND, YOU KNOW, I'M AWARE IN
GENERAL ABOUT LIKE THE CONCEPT
OF LIKE MATCHING AND HOW THAT
SHOWS CONFIDENCE TO PEOPLE TO
INVEST. I GET THAT, BUT I THINK
WHERE LIKE I'M AT IS I WOULD
MUCH PREFER THAT WE NOT HAVE TO
LIKE, I GUESS THAT'S WHY I'M
LIKE, HOW ARE YOU MOVING PAST
THIS POINT? RIGHT? ARE YOU
SAYING WE'RE GOING TO GET A
MATCH FROM THE CITY AND
THEREFORE, RIGHT. BECAUSE IF
THAT'S HOW YOU'RE SELLING IT,
THEN THAT IS WHAT FEELS TO US
LIKE A COMMITMENT THAT WE'RE
MAKING IN THIS, IN THIS PHASE.
AND SO THAT'S WHAT WE'RE TRYING
TO ASK ABOUT.
>> NO SALES. WE NEED TO GET
WITH THE FOLKS IN THE ROOM AND
FIGURE OUT WHAT THE
POSSIBILITIES ARE. AND THEN WE
WOULD TAKE IT TO EXTERNAL
PARTNERS, BUT ONLY AFTER IT'S
BEEN THOROUGHLY VETTED WITH
CITY PARTNERS AND BROUGHT BACK
TO YOU AS AN OPPORTUNITY.
>> SO THERE'S A SCENARIO WHERE
WE DO ALL OF THIS AND IT COMES
BACK AND WE SAY, THE CITY IS
GOING TO PUT ZERO, AND WE'RE
GOING TO FIND THE 440 FROM
SOMEWHERE ELSE. THERE IS A
SCENARIO WHERE THAT HAPPENS. I
GUESS I WANT TO FIGURE OUT WHAT
THE. I HEAR THAT YOU WANT THE
MONEY OPTIMISM.
>> I WANT TO FIND THAT BILLION
DOLLAR DONOR TOO. SO LET'S GO
DO THAT TOGETHER. I DON'T THINK
THAT'S WHERE WE'RE GOING TO
COME BACK. AND I THINK AS LONG
AS WE CONTINUE TO SAY THAT THIS
IS THE CITY'S OWN VENUE, THERE
WILL ALWAYS BE AN EXPECTATION
FROM ANYONE ELSE WHO MIGHT
PARTICIPATE IN THIS PROJECT
THAT THE CITY WILL HAVE SOME
PORTION OF INVESTMENT INTO THIS
PROJECT, BUT THIS IS THE WORK
THAT WE'RE EXCITED TO DO.
>> THANK YOU. LAST QUESTION FOR
CITY ATTORNEY. WHAT HAPPENS IF
THE CITY THIS. NOW, WHEN I SAY
THE CITY, I MEAN THE
ADMINISTRATION AT ALL, DOES
MOVE FORWARD WITH MAKING SOME
FINANCIAL COMMITMENT, EVEN
THOUGH WE ARE VERY CLEARLY
STATING WE DON'T WANT THAT.
WHAT IS COUNCIL'S RECOURSE IN
THAT SCENARIO?
>> IF IF, FOR EXAMPLE, THE THE
EXECUTIVE TAKES SOME ACTION
SIGNS, SOME CONTRACT, FOR
EXAMPLE, AND COUNCIL BELIEVES
THAT THERE WAS NOT AUTHORITY
FOR THAT, THEN COUNCIL BY
RESOLUTION COULD PASS, COULD
DIRECT THE CITY ATTORNEY TO
FILE WHAT'S CALLED A VALIDATION
PROCEEDING. SO WE WOULD GO TO
COURT AND THEN PUT THAT IN
FRONT OF THE JUDGE AND HAVE THE
JUDGE DECIDE WHETHER THAT
CONTRACT WAS EXECUTED WITH
AUTHORITY OR NOT.
>> OKAY. WELL, YOU OBVIOUSLY
HEAR OUR INTENT. I DON'T I
DON'T THINK ANYBODY WANTS TO GO
DOWN THAT ROAD, BUT I HAD TO
ASK IN CASE WE HAD TO. BUT THE
GOAL IS THAT WE DON'T GO THAT
ROAD BECAUSE YOU DON'T DO THAT.
SO THAT'S MY INTENT. I'M WITH
MY COLLEAGUES AND FEELING VERY
TORN. I DID PUT UP ALL THOSE
AMENDMENTS TO TRY TO GET MYSELF
TO YES AND TO HOPEFULLY BRING
MY COLLEAGUES ALONG TO YES,
BECAUSE IN MY VIEW, WHEN I WAS
IN COMMITTEE, I WAS LIKE, IT
SEEMS LIKE THIS IS MOVING
FORWARD, LIKE AT THAT POINT.
AND SO I WAS LIKE, WHAT CAN I
DO TO PROTECT THE CITY? BECAUSE
I'M SEEING THE TRAIN ROLLING
AND I SO THAT'S HOW I WAS
APPROACHING MY AMENDMENTS. AND
SO THAT'S WHAT I WAS HOPING
WOULD PROVIDE SOME COMFORT. AND
OBVIOUSLY, WE'VE HAD A DYNAMIC
DISCUSSION TODAY, SO I'M GOING
TO WAIT TO HEAR THE FINAL
THINGS. PROBABLY GOING TO BE A
GAME TIME DECISION, BUT I DO
FEEL LIKE I PUT SOME SOME
PROTECTIONS FOR THE CITY, AND I
FEEL GOOD ABOUT THOSE, AT LEAST
AT THIS STATE, KNOWING THAT THE
INTENT IS CLEAR AND THAT WE'RE
GOING TO HAVE SOMETHING COME
BACK TO US BEFORE WE MAKE A
COMMITMENT ON DOLLARS. SO
THAT'S WHERE I'M AT.
>> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. COUNCILOR AVALOS
COLLEAGUES. THERE ARE FIVE MORE
COLLEAGUES IN THE QUEUE. AGAIN,
COUNCILOR CLARK, THEN GREEN,
THEN KANAL COUNCIL.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT.
JUST ONE LITTLE PIECE OF
INFORMATION. I BELIEVE THAT THE
CITY HAS PUT MONEY IN ALREADY.
IT CAME FROM AN OLD TIF
DISTRICT. I THINK THERE'S, WHAT,
$7 MILLION THAT WAS DEDICATED
TO THIS THAT WE HAVEN'T TALKED
ABOUT AT ALL. BUT THAT WAS A
PREVIOUS COUNCIL PREVIOUS
DECISION. BUT THERE THERE IS A
LITTLE OVER $7 MILLION COMING
FROM THE OLD SOUTH WATERFRONT
TIF DISTRICT, I BELIEVE.
>> CORRECT. COUNCILOR VICE
PRESIDENT, EXCUSE ME, BUT THAT
MONEY HAS HAS BEEN SORT OF
AMORPHOUS IN TERMS OF WHERE IT
COULD GO. IT'S IT'S TENTATIVELY
PLACED IF THIS PROJECT WERE TO
GO FORWARD. BUT THERE'S, AGAIN,
A LOT OF WORK TO BE DONE TO
SORT THAT OUT. I WOULD I WOULD
CAUTION ON SAYING THAT THAT'S A
GUARANTEED COMMITTED RESOURCE.
>> OKAY. I JUST KNEW IT WAS
HANGING OUT THERE. I JUST I
JUST WANT TO MAKE A COUPLE OF
COMMENTS. I AND I'VE ALREADY
SPOKEN, BUT WHEN I FIRST SAW
THE PLANS THAT THE KELLER GROUP
CAME UP WITH, WITH MICHAEL
CURRY AND WITH STUFISH, THE
REDESIGN, INCLUDING THE THE
FOUNTAIN AND THE CLOSURE OF
THIRD, I THOUGHT, THIS IS
BRILLIANT. THIS IS FANTASTIC.
IT'S WONDERFUL. AND I I'VE BEEN
TRYING TO THREAD THE NEEDLE
EVER SINCE THEN BECAUSE I'VE
BEEN VERY SUPPORTIVE OF REDOING
THE KELLER. AND UNFORTUNATELY,
I FEEL LIKE THIS HAS BECOME
SORT OF A SOPHIE'S CHOICE AND
IT REALLY SHOULDN'T HAVE BEEN.
WE SHOULD HAVE HAD A BETTER
PARTNERSHIP FROM THE BEGINNING,
BUT NOW WE HAVE THE RESOLUTION.
IT'S BEEN AMENDED GRATEFULLY BY
COUNCILOR AVALOS AND MYSELF TO
INCLUDE THE KELLER AND TO
INCLUDE SOME SIDEBOARDS. SO
IT'S REALLY TO SUPPORT
ADVANCING PLANNING AND
PREDEVELOPMENT GETTING
INFORMATION FOR A POTENTIAL.
AND I EMPHASIZE POTENTIAL
BROADWAY CAPABLE VENUE. I JUST
WANT TO MAKE THAT REALLY CLEAR.
YOU KNOW, UPON REFLECTION, IT'S
BEEN HARD FOR ME BECAUSE I'VE
BEEN SORT OF THE PERSON WHO
TALKS THE MOST ABOUT TAKING
CARE OF WHAT WE HAVE, OUR ASSET
MANAGEMENT. AND WE HAVE WE HAVE
NOT TAKEN CARE OF THE KELLER.
AND IT WOULDN'T COST THAT MUCH
TO REALLY MAKE IT A BETTER
FACILITY. WE CAN STILL DO THAT.
WE'VE AS WE'VE AMENDED THIS
RESOLUTION, BUT I DON'T REALLY
UNDERSTAND WHY WE HAVE TO HAVE
A RESOLUTION TO ANSWER ALL
THESE QUESTIONS, UNFORTUNATELY.
BUT I APPRECIATE THAT IT HELPS
PSU OBTAIN THE LEGISLATIVE
COMMITMENT, CONTINUE THEIR
PHILANTHROPIC ACTIVITY. I, I, I
APPRECIATE THAT, I SUPPORT THAT,
I RESPECT THAT IF ONLY I COULD
CHANNEL BILL NAITO AND I, I
THINK THAT HE WOULD SAY, LET'S
DO BOTH. AS SOMEBODY MENTIONED
EARLIER, BUT HAVING AMENDED THE
RESOLUTION AND HAVING CANDICE
OR COUNCILOR AVALOS AMENDMENTS,
I. I THINK IT'S OKAY TO
INVESTIGATE THE OPTIONS BECAUSE
WE HAVE SIDEBOARDS, WE HAVE
PROTECTIONS. HOWEVER, I WILL
PREDICT THAT WE WILL BE HERE IN
DECEMBER WITH THE ANSWERS TO
OUR QUESTIONS. BUT ABOUT THE
CITY'S POTENTIAL OBLIGATIONS.
BUT THE MATERIAL CIRCUMSTANCES
ARE NOT GOING TO BE DIFFERENT.
WE'RE LOOKING AT MONEY FOR THE
MOTOR. WE'RE LOOKING AT NEW
MANAGEMENT FOR P5. WE'LL BE
STARING DOWN A POTENTIAL $100
MILLION BUDGET DEFICIT.
COUNCILOR MORILLO ACTUALLY
MENTIONED THE PROVIDENCE PARK
UPGRADES THAT NEED TO BE MADE.
SO I THINK WE'RE GOING TO BE
BACK RIGHT IN THE SAME PLACE
THAT WE ARE, BUT WE'LL HAVE
MORE INFORMATION. AND THAT'S
NOT A BAD THING. SO AT THE SAME
TIME, I THINK I AGREE WITH
COUNCILOR RYAN THAT I HESITATE
TO THINK WHAT THE PORTLAND
TAXPAYERS ARE GOING TO THINK
ABOUT THIS RIGHT NOW, FURTHER
OBLIGATING THE POTENTIAL
OBLIGATION OF CITY FUNDS. SO
I'M UNCOMFORTABLE WITH THIS
SITUATION, BUT I'M TRYING TO
THREAD THE NEEDLE. I'VE BEEN
TRYING TO THREAD THE NEEDLE
FROM THE VERY BEGINNING. SO I'M
GOING TO BE IN SUPPORT OF THE
RESOLUTION.
>> THANK YOU, VICE.
>> PRESIDENT CLARK, COUNCILORS
GREEN, KANAL SMITH AND RYAN. SO
COUNCILOR GREEN.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT.
AND I KNOW THAT THIS HAS GONE
ON FAR LONGER THAN YOU. YOU
WANT. AND IN THAT SPIRIT, I'LL
TRY TO BE BRIEF. WHEN WE WENT
THROUGH THE MODE OF
CONVERSATIONS, I HEARD FROM MY
DISTRICT TWO COLLEAGUES A DEEP
FEAR AND ANXIETY OF A
NEIGHBORHOOD GOING DARK, OF A
VENUE BECOMING VACANT, AND SORT
OF THE IMPACT, THE LOCAL, HYPER
LOCALIZED IMPACT OF OF THAT IN
THE KELLER. AND SO I KIND OF
HOLD THAT HERE AT THE SAME TIME
IN THE SAME KIND OF WAY. AND I
THINK THAT'S WHERE A LOT OF MY
APPREHENSION COMES FROM BY SORT
OF TRYING TO GREENLIGHT THIS
RESOLUTION. DCA OLIVEIRA YOU
SAID SOMETHING THAT WAS VERY
POIGNANT, THOUGH, AND I REALLY
APPRECIATE IT, AND I WANT TO
MAKE SURE EVERYONE CAUGHT IT,
WHICH WAS YOU DIDN'T FEEL LIKE
YOU COULD GO OUT AND DO THESE
NEGOTIATIONS UNLESS YOU KNEW
THAT CITY COUNCIL COULD SUPPORT
THAT. AND I ACTUALLY THINK
THAT'S A STRONG SIGNAL. THAT'S
I WANT TO VALIDATE THAT SIGNAL
BECAUSE I WANT FOR SOMETHING OF
THIS MAGNITUDE, I WANT YOU TO
COME TO COUNCIL AND ASK HOW WE
SHOULD PROCEED. THAT'S THAT'S
HOW WE BRING THE DEMOCRACY INTO,
INTO THE BUILDING. SO I DIDN'T
WANT THAT TO GET LOST. AND SO
THERE'S BEEN A PRETTY RICH
CONVERSATION HERE OVER THE LAST
HOUR, ALMOST. I ALREADY RAISED
CONCERNS ABOUT PROCESS AND HOW
HOW ONE DECISION LEADS TO
ANOTHER. AND THEN PRETTY SOON,
YOUR COST CENTERS HAVE GROWN IN
THE CITY OF PORTLAND. AND
THAT'S THAT'S ON THE RECORD.
AND WE HAVE TO DEAL WITH THAT.
AND WE HAVE TO ADDRESS THAT.
AND I THINK, COUNCILOR CLARK,
YOU MADE SOME POINTS JUST A
MOMENT AGO ABOUT WE'VE ALREADY
AMENDED THIS PIECE TO PROVIDE
SOME VERY FIRM GUARDRAILS AND
SOME SIDEBOARDS INTO IT. AND
YOU'RE YOU'RE RIGHT. AND A
COUPLE MONTHS, WE'RE PROBABLY
GOING TO HAVE THE SAME
CONVERSATION AND, AND BE
PRESENTED WITH THE SAME
MATERIAL CONDITIONS, BUT MAYBE
WE'LL HAVE MORE INFORMATION ON
THE ASSET MANAGEMENT PLAN BY
THEN, AND MAYBE WE'LL BE ABLE
TO CONTEXTUALIZE THIS STUFF AND,
AND, AND CONTEMPLATE ASKING
VOTERS WHETHER THEY WANT TO
WANT TO HAVE A SAY IN HOW TO
FUND THIS. BECAUSE I THINK WHAT
WE'VE FOUND WHEN WE PULL THEM
IS IF WE CAN POINT TO VERY
CLEAR BENEFITS, THEY'RE MUCH
MORE SUPPORTIVE OF SAYING YES
TO THINGS, BUT THEY DON'T TRUST
US TO NECESSARILY STEWARD THEIR
FUNDS RIGHT NOW. AND SO THIS
MESSY CONVERSATION IS PART OF
EARNING THAT TRUST BACK TO
STEWARD THOSE THOSE FUNDS. IT'S
ALSO NOT LOST ON ME THAT RIGHT
NOW AS WE SPEAK, I THINK SEIU
503 MEMBERS ARE HAVING A RALLY
AT PORTLAND STATE UNIVERSITY
OVER A CONTRACT. AND, YOU KNOW,
SO IN THE CONTEXT OF WORKERS
AND LABOR STANDARDS, YOU KNOW,
TAKING A DECISION ON THIS
WITHOUT NAMING THAT IS IS
SOMETHING THAT WE MUST DO. I
ALSO HEARD FROM SOME WORKERS
WHO HAVE PINCHED NERVES BECAUSE
THEY, THE WORK THAT THEY
EXPERIENCE AS, AS STAGEHANDS IS
DANGEROUS. IT'S ONEROUS. AND SO
I'M HOLDING A LOT HERE. AND I
THINK THAT COUNCILOR KANAL YOU
HAD SORT OF REALLY BROACHED,
GOT US DOWN THIS PATH WHERE WE
LAID INTO THE RECORD THE CHIEF
CONCERNS ABOUT THIS BALANCE
BETWEEN EXECUTIVE PURVIEW AND
COUNCIL INTENT. AND SO I THINK
IN THE CONTEXT OF THAT, I'M IN
A PLACE NOW WHERE I CAN SUPPORT
THIS RESOLUTION.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR GREEN.
LAST THREE COLLEAGUES. WE HAVE
COUNCILOR KANAL, THEN COUNCILOR
SMITH AND COUNCILOR RYAN
COUNCILOR KANAL.
>> THANKS. I ACTUALLY HAVE
QUESTIONS FOR BOTH OF OUR FOLKS
HERE, BUT ALSO JONAH'S OUR CFO,
BERRY. WE HAD THIS CONVERSATION.
ROBERT TAYLOR MENTIONED THAT
CONTRACTS ARE OKAY IF THEY'RE
WITHIN THE THE SCOPE OF WHAT
MONEY IS BUDGETED IS ANY MONEY
BUDGETED RIGHT NOW DEFINITIVELY,
AND I DON'T JUST MEAN 44
MILLION IS A IS ONE PENNY
BUDGETED RIGHT NOW FOR THIS.
>> COUNCILOR. I'LL. MY
UNDERSTANDING IS NO, I CAN'T
ANSWER WHETHER THERE'S ANY
OPERATIONAL DOLLARS. I BELIEVE
DCA OLIVEIRA MENTIONED THERE IS
SOME STAFF RESOURCES TO
ACCOMMODATE THIS WORK, BUT TO
MY UNDERSTANDING, THERE'S NO
CAPITAL OR PROJECT DOLLARS THAT
ARE COMMITTED SPECIFICALLY TO
THIS PROJECT.
>> WITH THE CAVEAT OF A TIF
ACTION PLAN FOR THE SOUTH
WATERFRONT, WHICH IS A
POTENTIAL USE. BUT THERE'S
STILL STEPS TO TO REALIZE THAT.
>> YEAH, THANK YOU FOR
CLARIFYING THAT. I KNOW
COUNCILOR VICE PRESIDENT CLARK
MENTIONED THAT AS WELL. GIVEN
THAT TO ROBERT, WOULD IT BE
LEGAL IF A MEMBER OF THE
ADMINISTRATION COMMITTED TO
ANYTHING BEYOND STAFF RESOURCES
OR THE TIF DOLLARS? BASED ON
THE ANSWERS WE JUST GOT?
>> I MEAN, IT WOULD DEPEND ON
WHAT THEY WHAT THEY WANTED TO
DO. SO, FOR EXAMPLE, YOU COULD
EXECUTE A CONTRACT THAT SAYS
ALL OF THIS IS SUBJECT TO
COUNCIL APPROVAL. THE FUNDING
WOULD BE SUBJECT TO COUNCIL
APPROVAL. THAT WOULD BE A
CONTRACT THAT COULD BE ENTERED,
BUT IT WOULD STILL PRESERVE
YOUR COUNCIL'S ABILITY TO MAKE
THE FUNDING DECISION.
>> CAN I ASK WOULD, IF THAT
WERE TO HAPPEN, THE EXAMPLE YOU
GAVE, WOULD IT HAVE TO BE
EXPLICITLY MENTIONED IN THE
BUDGET TO DO THAT? BECAUSE I'VE
NOTICED THAT THERE ARE THINGS
WHICH ARE IN DOCUMENTATION THAT
DOES NOT END UP IN THE BUDGET
THAT COMES TO US FOR A VOTE. SO
YOU GET THESE LIKE A THROUGH J
EXHIBITS, RIGHT? AND THEN
THERE'S QUESTIONS THAT WE ASK
THAT ARE DUG INTO IN
SPREADSHEETS THAT EXIST
ELSEWHERE. SO IS IT POSSIBLE
THAT A CONTRACT WITH THAT
CAVEAT WAS PUT INTO PLACE AND
THEN A BUDGET THAT DOESN'T
INCLUDE THAT WAS GIVEN TO US
FOR PROPOSED TO US BY THE MAYOR,
VOTED ON AND APPROVED BY THE
COUNCIL, AND THEN LATER WE FIND
OUT THAT IT WASN'T IN THESE
DOCUMENTS. IT WAS IN THESE
OTHER DOCUMENTS THAT ARE NOT ON
THE COUNCIL ITEM, THAT THERE
WAS MONEY BUDGETED TOWARDS THIS.
>> YEAH, I MEAN, IT'S I THINK
YOU'RE ASKING A QUESTION ABOUT
THE, THE, THE, THE BUDGET
PROCESS THAT WE, WE GO THROUGH
AND THE, THE CONTRACTING
AUTHORITY BASED ON WHAT'S IN
THE BUDGET. I THINK THAT'S A
MUCH BROADER CONVERSATION. AND
I, I'M HESITANT TO, TO GIVE YOU
A BROAD LEGAL RESPONSE TO THAT
BROAD HYPOTHETICAL HERE, BUT
I'D BE HAPPY TO ENGAGE IN MORE
CONVERSATION WITH YOU ABOUT
THAT.
>> YEAH. AND I WOULD LOVE TO
JUST TO PUT ON THE RECORD, THE
CONCERN IS THAT WE EFFECTIVELY
HAVE UNITARY EXECUTIVE THEORY
HERE, WHERE IF IT'S NOT
EXPLICITLY BANNED, IT'S JUST
HAPPENING. THE TENNIS CENTER IS
THE MOST EGREGIOUS OF THESE
THINGS. BUT THAT'S THAT'S MY
CONCERN. AND I BROUGHT THIS UP
IN SEVERAL BUDGET MEETINGS AND
BEEN TOLD IT'S NOT ACTUALLY A
BIG DEAL, THAT THERE'S THINGS
THAT AREN'T IN THE BUDGET THAT
YOU'RE VOTING ON. I THINK
THAT'S A PRETTY BIG DEAL, IN MY
OPINION. THERE WAS A COMMENT
THAT YOU MADE DCA OLIVEIRA,
ABOUT EVALUATING IF THERE'S
MONEY AVAILABLE. WE JUST WENT
THROUGH THIS WITH MODA, WHO
DECIDES IF THERE'S MONEY
AVAILABLE, BECAUSE IT APPEARS
TO ME, LOOKING AT THAT ONE,
THAT 120 MILLION, THAT ALL
THESE DOLLAR AMOUNTS WERE
BASICALLY THREE EXECUTIVES
SITTING IN A ROOM AND SAYING,
WHAT, WHAT, WHAT DO I THINK I
CAN GET OUT OF MY, MY
LEGISLATURE? AND THAT WASN'T
100%. I MEAN, THE GOVERNOR AT
LEAST TALKED TO THE LEGISLATURE
ABOUT IT FIRST, BUT THE COUNTY
CHAIR DOES NOT APPEAR TO HAVE I
DON'T KNOW, MAYOR CERTAINLY
DIDN'T. SO WHO'S DECIDING IF
IT'S AVAILABLE IN THIS BACK
ROOM THAT WE'RE AUTHORIZING?
>> YEAH.
>> THANKS FOR THE FRONT ROOM.
>> THANKS FOR OPPORTUNITY TO
CLARIFY THAT. COUNCILOR. WHAT I
WAS TRYING TO SPEAK TO IS
SITTING DOWN WITH PSU,
EVALUATING THE CAPITAL STACK
AND THE OPTIONS AND SEEING WHAT,
YOU KNOW, WHAT AMOUNT THE CITY
WOULD NEED TO CONTRIBUTE,
WHATEVER THAT NUMBER MAY BE.
BUT GOING BACK TO THE WHAT? THE
LANGUAGE IN THE RESOLUTION,
SURELY WORKING WITH CFO AND HIS
TEAM, WE'D HAVE TO CONTEMPLATE
OPTIONS, BUT I DON'T THINK
WE'RE GOING TO BE DECIDING WHAT
RESOURCES ARE GOING TO THIS
UNTIL WE EVEN UNDERSTAND WHAT
THE CITY CONTRIBUTION MIGHT
EVEN NEED TO BE. WE MIGHT WE
MIGHT GET TO THE THE TABLE WITH
PSU AND COUNCILOR AVALOS
CONCEPT. WE FOUND SOMEBODY TO
FUND THE WHOLE THING. SO THE
CITY CONTRIBUTION IS ZERO.
THAT'S GREAT. OR WE HAVE A
SCENARIO WHERE IT'S IT'S THE
FULL 440. AND WE COME BACK TO
YOU ALL LIKE, HEY, WE HAVE TO
FIND $440 MILLION. THIS IS WHAT
IT LOOKS LIKE. THAT SEEMS LIKE
AN EASY NOTE FOR YOU ALL.
WITHIN THAT PROCESS, WE'RE
ABSOLUTELY GOING TO BE WORKING
WITH OUR FINANCE TEAM ABOUT
SCENARIOS. IS IT BONDING? IS IT
WHATEVER IT MAY BE? RIGHT.
THAT'S IT'S PREMATURE FOR ME TO
EVEN SPECULATE BECAUSE WE
HAVEN'T ACTUALLY SAT DOWN YET.
BUT I THINK WHAT YOU'RE GETTING
AT, IF I CAN JUST BE MORE
EXPLICIT, IS I DON'T THINK IT'S
OUR DECISION TO DECIDE WHAT THE
FUNDING SOURCE IS ON THIS
PARTICULAR CASE. I THINK WE'RE
GOING TO BE COMING TO YOU WITH
THE RANGE OF OF OPTIONS,
IDEALLY WITH A TARGET THAT IS
REASONABLE BECAUSE THERE'S A
SCENARIO WHERE WE WE DON'T COME
BACK ON DECEMBER 1ST BECAUSE
THAT WE COULD, WE COULDN'T GET
TO A NUMBER THAT WE THINK WOULD
REASONABLY DELIVER ON. DOES
THAT MAKE SENSE? THAT'S A REAL
POSSIBILITY. AND MAYBE MY
COLLEAGUES AT PSU ARE ARE KIND
OF CRINGING AT THAT. BUT
THERE'S A SCENARIO WHERE
THERE'S A DECEMBER 1ST
DISCUSSION ABOUT HOW WE
COULDN'T GET TO A DEAL THAT'S
THAT'S FEASIBLE.
>> AND IF I CAN JUST RESPOND TO
THE, THE, THE UNITARY EXECUTIVE
COMMENT, I, I DO THINK, YOU
KNOW, WE'RE TWO YEARS INTO THIS
ALMOST. AND, AND I DO THINK
THAT THAT I DO THINK MANY OF
YOU HAVE NOTED THE TENSION
BETWEEN THE LEGISLATIVE AND THE
EXECUTIVE. I DO THINK THAT
THAT'S A REAL TENSION. I DO
THINK THAT THAT'S SOMETHING
THAT THAT WE NEED TO CONTINUE
TO WORK ON AS A CITY. AND I
THINK IT'S IMPORTANT TO NOTE
THAT BY CHARTER, WE HAVE A
DIVIDED GOVERNMENT. THERE'S A
LEGISLATIVE BODY, AND THERE IS
AN EXECUTIVE BODY, AND THEY ARE
GIVEN SEPARATE AUTHORITIES.
UNDER THE OLD FORM OF
GOVERNMENT. EVERY CONTRACT
WOULD HAVE TO COME BACK TO
COUNCIL FOR APPROVAL, OR MOST
OF THEM WOULD. AND THE THE THE
CHARTER BY, BY ITS TERMS, SAYS
WE DON'T DO THAT ANYMORE, THAT
THE MAYOR CAN EXECUTE CONTRACTS
AS LONG AS IT'S CONSISTENT WITH
THE BUDGET. SO THAT WAS A
CHOICE THAT THE VOTERS MADE.
THE VOTERS ALSO MADE THAT
CHOICE TO HAVE A DIVIDED
LEGISLATIVE AND EXECUTIVE
BRANCH. WE DON'T HAVE A COUNCIL
MANAGER FORM OF GOVERNMENT,
RIGHT? WE DO NOT HAVE THAT. WE
HAVE A DIVIDED FORM OF
GOVERNMENT. AND SO I THINK
THAT'S IMPORTANT. NOW, I THINK
THE OTHER PIECE OF THIS IS WE
HAVE A LONG HISTORY HERE AT THE
CITY OF DOING WHAT'S CALLED
BULK APPROPRIATIONS, WHERE THE
BUDGET DECISIONS ARE MADE AT A
VERY, VERY HIGH LEVEL. AND THEN
THAT GIVES THE EXECUTIVE A LOT
MORE DISCRETION ABOUT MAKING
THOSE SPENDING DECISIONS. AND
THAT'S SOMETHING WE'VE GONE
THROUGH A COUPLE OF TIMES IN
THE BUDGET PROCESS. THERE ARE
WAYS FOR THIS COUNCIL USING
THEIR BUDGET AUTHORITY TO BE
MORE RESTRICTIVE AND SPECIFIC
ABOUT HOW YOU MAKE SPENDING
DECISIONS WITHIN A BULK
APPROPRIATION CONTEXT. YOU CAN
ALSO, IF WE DECIDE TO, WE COULD
GO TO A LINE ITEM BUDGET WHERE
COUNCIL MAKES INDIVIDUAL
SPENDING DECISIONS, AND THEN
THE EXECUTIVE IS BOUND BY THAT.
SO THERE ARE THERE ARE WAYS TO
CHANGE BOTH THE BUDGET PROCESS
AND HONOR THE DIVISION AND
SEPARATION OF POWERS IN OUR
CHARTER.
>> THANKS. MY LAST QUESTION. I
GUESS IT'S FOR ALL THREE. TO
THE BEST OF YOUR KNOWLEDGE, HAS
IT EVER BEEN ASKED ABOUT BY
ANYBODY SUGGESTED FLOATED ANY
REFERENCE TO PORTLAND CLEAN
ENERGY FUNDS BEING USED FOR
THIS?
>> IN THE ORIGINAL RFP THAT
WENT OUT IN 2023? IT MY STAFF
CAN CORRECT THE EXACT DATE THE
PROJECTS WERE ASKED TO KIND OF
CONTEMPLATE CAPITAL STACKS, AND
I THINK IN A COUPLE. CLEAN
ENERGY FUND WAS JUST NOTED AS A
POSSIBILITY. BUT THIS WAS LIKE
A, YOU KNOW, DREAM, YOU KNOW,
DREAM CASTING. THEY WERE JUST
LIKE, YOU KNOW, IDEATING THERE
WAS NO COMMITMENT TO THAT. IT
WAS JUST SORT OF HOW MIGHT IT
LOOK? SO YOU MIGHT FIND SOME
REFERENCE TO IT AND SOME OF THE
PROPOSALS GOING BACK, YOU KNOW,
A COUPLE OF YEARS AGO, A FEW
YEARS AGO AT THIS POINT. WELL,
2026.
>> ANYTHING ELSE SUBSEQUENT.
>> TO THAT? TO THE BEST OF MY
KNOWLEDGE, THAT'S THE THAT'S
THE LAST TIME I CAN THINK ABOUT
IT COMING UP.
>> COUNCIL, I'LL JUST
ACKNOWLEDGE AS WELL. I THINK
YOU'RE LOOKING AT ME FOR AN
ANSWER AS WELL. IF I'M READING
READING THE ROOM, THANK YOU TO
MY AWARENESS. NO, BUT AS WAS
MENTIONED EARLIER, I'VE NOT
INVOLVED IN THE DETAILS OF THIS.
I DO WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE, IN
RESPONSE TO YOUR QUESTION IN
THE CITY ATTORNEY'S RESPONSE,
JUST TO BE VERY CLEAR FOR THE
PUBLIC THAT THE ADMINISTRATION
CANNOT SPEND DOLLARS THAT ARE
NOT APPROPRIATED IN THE BUDGET
AND AUTHORIZED BY COUNCIL. SO I
WANT TO BE VERY CLEAR FOR
ANYBODY WHO'S PAYING ATTENTION
THAT WE FOLLOW STATE BUDGET LAW,
WE FOLLOW THE STATE STATE
CHARTER. I APPRECIATE, AND AS
THE CITY ATTORNEY ACKNOWLEDGED,
THERE'S PROBABLY DIFFERENCES OF
THOUGHT ABOUT THE LEVEL OF
GRADIENT DETAIL. ALSO, JUST
ACKNOWLEDGE WE'RE HAVING A WORK
SESSION TOMORROW AFTERNOON IN
THIS ROOM TO TALK ABOUT BUDGET
PROCESS IMPROVEMENTS, AND I
WOULD WELCOME THAT CONVERSATION
AS PART OF THAT WORK SESSION
TOMORROW. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. I APPRECIATE ALL
THOSE ANSWERS. I DID WANT TO
SAY I'M I'M LOOKING FORWARD TO
HAVING THE CONVERSATION IN A
FEW YEARS ABOUT ABOUT
PROVIDENCE PARK SINCE THAT WAS
REFERENCED BY COUNCILOR MORILLO
AS WELL, AND THAT I'LL BE A NO
ON THIS TODAY, BUT I LOOK
FORWARD TO BEING A YES ON THIS
IF WE GET SOMETHING GOOD BACK
IN DECEMBER. THANKS.
>> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. COUNCILOR KANAL
COLLEAGUES PROGRAMING NOTE IT
IS CURRENTLY 1240. WE ARE
EXTENDING THIS MEETING UNTIL
130 TO TRY AND GET THROUGH AS
MUCH AS WE CAN DO IT, BUT WE
STILL HAVE THE ZENITH ITEM,
FIRST READING AND FIVE
FORECLOSURE ITEMS TO TRY AND
GET THROUGH. I IMAGINE WE WILL
NOT GET THROUGH ALL OF THAT
TODAY, SO I AM LIMITING DEBATE
IN THE QUEUE RIGHT NOW.
COUNCILOR KOYAMA LANE WILL BE
THE FINAL PERSON TO SPEAK ON
THIS ITEM, AND THEN WE'LL MOVE
TO A VOTE. COUNCILOR SMITH,
THEN RYAN, THEN KOYAMA LANE
COUNCILOR SMITH.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT,
I JUST WANT TO REMIND YOU ALL
THAT EXPERIENCE DOES MATTER. I
PUT AN AMENDMENT TO THE BUDGET
FOR THE 2526 YEAR, ASKING THAT
MY COUNCILORS APPROVE AN
AMENDMENT THAT WOULD HAVE ALL
CONTRACTS COME BEFORE COUNCIL
THAT ARE OVER $50,000. AND
SINCE WE DID NOT HAVE THE MAYOR
BREAKS THE TIE RULE, IT DIDN'T
PASS. SO WE'RE COMING BACK
TODAY AND CONSTANTLY SAYING THE
ADMINISTRATION IS DOING THIS.
AND THAT WAS IN THE IT'S IN THE
THE CHARTER THAT THE MAYOR CAN
HE CAN ACTUALLY GO INTO A
BUDGET THAT'S ALREADY BEEN
APPROVED AND REARRANGE THEM AND
SAY, THIS IS NOT WHAT THE
PRIORITY IS. AND HE CAN USE
THOSE FUNDS. AND SO FOR ME,
IT'S, IT'S KIND OF LIKE A MOOT
POINT. WE CAN'T HAVE ONE ONE,
WE CAN'T HAVE OUR CAKE AND EAT
IT TOO. YOU WANT TO YOU WANT TO
LOOK AT EVERYTHING, BUT YOU
DON'T WANT TO GO THROUGH THE
PROCESS TO, TO MAKE SURE THAT
WE CAN LOOK AT EVERYTHING. SO I
WOULD ENCOURAGE AND URGE
BECAUSE I'M NOT DOING IT AGAIN.
AND WE'LL HAVE A SIX SIX VOTE
AGAIN, AND THEN THE MAYOR WILL
BREAK THE TIE AND THEN EVERYONE
WILL BE ALL UPSET AGAIN. SO I
THINK THAT WE NEED TO GET THE
INFORMATION, MAKE SURE THAT WE
KNOW WHAT'S COMING FORWARD,
WHAT THE POSSIBILITY IS. I
WOULD LIKE TO ACTUALLY CHANGE
THE DATE BECAUSE IF WE DON'T
HAVE THOSE NUMBERS OR AN
APPROVED TERM SHEET FOR MODA
CENTER. WE'RE GOING TO WE'RE
GOING TO BE UP. A CREEK. THAT'S
ALL I WANT TO SAY ABOUT THAT
CREEK, BECAUSE I DON'T SEE HOW
WE COME OUT WITH THAT. AND WE
DON'T HAVE AN APPROVED TERM
SHEET BECAUSE WE'RE WHERE WHERE
IS THE MONEY COMING FROM? AND
THE LONGER THAT WE KEEP
DEBATING THIS POINT ABOUT THE
MONEY AND WHERE IT'S COMING
FROM, WE ALL, I THINK I TOOK A
CONSENSUS COUNCILOR NOVICK OF
THE OF THE COUNCIL, AND I THINK
WE ARE ALL CONCERNED ABOUT
WHERE THOSE DOLLARS ARE COMING
FROM. AND SO JUST REMEMBER,
VOTES HAVE CONSEQUENCES. WE CAN
GO BACK AND REDO SOME THINGS
AND WE CAN HAVE EVERYTHING COME
BEFORE US AND WE CAN JUST
CHANGE THIS, OR WE CAN APPROVE
THIS TODAY, WAIT TO SEE WHAT
THE CAPITAL STACK LOOKS LIKE
AND SAY, THIS IS SOMETHING THAT
WE CAN DO. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR SMITH,
COUNCILOR RYAN AND THEN KOYAMA
LANE COUNCILOR RYAN.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT,
JUST A COUPLE LEVEL SETTING
QUESTIONS SINCE WE'RE HERE. AND
THAT IS PLEASE, PLEASE CONFIRM
THAT PORTLAND STATE UNIVERSITY
OWNS THE PROPERTY THAT WE'RE
DISCUSSING AT THE SITE OF THIS
PERFORMANCE.
>> THAT IS CORRECT.
>> THAT'S CORRECT. OKAY. AND
THE SCENARIOS THAT I THINK ARE
MAKING PEOPLE FEEL BETTER TO
VOTE ON THIS IS THAT WE WON'T
BE RESPONSIBLE FOR ANY MONEY TO
BUILD THIS. I AGREE WITH YOU,
SARAH, THAT OF COURSE YOU WANT
10% FROM YOUR PUBLIC PARTNER.
THAT'S WHAT PERSON IN YOUR ROLE
WOULD SAY. AND I APPRECIATE
YOUR HONESTY. SO BUT IF THE
SCENARIO COMES TO FRUITION THAT
WE'RE NOT IN IT FOR EVEN A
PENNY, DOES THAT MEAN THAT
WOULDN'T PSU THEN OWN THE
BUILDING?
>> WELL, I THINK THAT'S A
DECISION TREE FOR ANOTHER DAY.
I WOULD REALLY LOVE FOR US JUST
TO GIVE A GOOD RUN AT FIGURING
OUT WHAT THE PATH FORWARD, IN
PARTNERSHIP WITH THE CITY COULD
LOOK LIKE FOLLOWING THIS
RESOLUTION AND THEN COME BACK
TO YOU COUNCILOR.
>> HAVE TO SURFACE REALITY NOW
AND THEN. SO IF IN FACT, WE'RE
IN THIS AGREEMENT AND WE
PROVIDE ZERO TO YOUR CAPITAL
STACK, I PREDICT THAT YOU WOULD
WANT MAYBE OWN THE BUILDING. I
DON'T KNOW, I'M JUST SAYING.
AND AT LEAST WE WON'T BE
RESPONSIBLE FOR THE DEFERRED
MAINTENANCE. BUT I JUST HAD TO
MAKE SURE WE HIGHLIGHTED THAT
REALITY AND THAT'S ALL. AND WE
DID HAVE CONVERSATIONS FOR
HISTORY'S SAKE ABOUT PCEF MONEY
FOR KELLER. WHY? KELLER?
BECAUSE IT'S A FULL RESTORATION.
AND THE PEOPLE ON THE COMMITTEE
AT THAT TIME SIGNALED THAT'S
PREFERRED THAN NEW OVER NEW
CONSTRUCTION. OKAY. THANKS.
WANTED TO GIVE YOU THAT AND
WE'RE READY TO MAKE A DECISION.
BUT ELECTIONS GOT IN THE WAY,
IF YOU WILL. JUST THOUGHT I'D
SAY THAT. SO WE WE ENDED UP
EXTENDING THIS. THERE WERE TWO
OUTSTANDING CANDIDATES, ONE
THAT WAS INVOLVED A FEW YEARS
BEFORE PSU, AND THEN IT OPENED
UP TO INCLUDE PSU. THAT'S
PROBABLY WHY I LIKE TO MENTION
THE HALPRIN FOLKS, BECAUSE
THEY'VE BEEN WORKING ON THIS,
DEVELOPING THEIR OWN CAPITAL
STACK TO DO A FULL RESTORATION
OF THE KELLER IN A CORE PART OF
OUR DOWNTOWN. THANKS.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR RYAN
COUNCILOR KOYAMA LANE LAST WORD.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT.
I APPRECIATE THE CONVERSATIONS
BEING HAD. I APPRECIATE THE
WORK THAT WAS DONE IN COMMITTEE
AND THE AMENDMENTS THAT
COUNCILOR AVALOS BROUGHT. I
KNOW THERE'S BEEN WORK ON THIS,
AND I LOVE YOU. I LOVE THE ARTS.
I'M VERY SUPPORTIVE AND I'M I
AM LEANING NO ON THIS. AND
THERE ARE MANY DIFFERENT THINGS
THAT MY COLLEAGUES HAVE BROUGHT
UP THAT ARE REASONS FOR THAT.
AND ONE OF THEM ALSO IS I JUST
LEFT FOR A LITTLE BIT TO GO TO
PSU CAMPUS TO SPEAK TO SEIU 501
CLASSIFIED STAFF WHO ARE
GETTING READY TO STRIKE FOR
FAIR WAGES AND JOB SECURITY AND
DIGNITY ON THE JOB. THEY ARE
THE CLASSIFIED STAFF AT PSU.
AND SO WHEN THEY'RE NOT GETTING
THOSE NEEDS MET FROM
ADMINISTRATION, I'M GOING TO
NEED TO HAVE SOME QUESTIONS
ANSWERED BEFORE IT'S FEELING
LIKE THERE'S SPACE TO BE DOING
EXTRA. SO AT THIS POINT I'M A
NO. AND LOOK FORWARD TO FURTHER
CONVERSATIONS THAT MIGHT HAPPEN.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR KOYAMA
LANE KEELAN, CAN WE PLEASE CALL
THE ROLL ON THE RESOLUTION.
>> DOCUMENT NUMBER 2026-270
KOYAMA LANE NO. AYE, MORILLO NO.
NOVICK.
>> AYE, MORILLO.
>> MARK AYE, MORILLO GREEN.
>> HI. ZIMMERMAN I.
>> AVALOS.
>> I. I.
>> KANAL.
>> REGRETTABLY, NO.
>> PIRTLE-GUINEY.
>> I.
>> RYAN. NO. DUNPHY.
>> THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED
WITH A VOTE OF EIGHT EYES AND
FOUR NAYS.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. CAN WE
PLEASE MOVE TO ITEM NUMBER 14?
DOCUMENT 2026-263.
>> CONSENT TO FRANCHISE
TRANSFER FROM ZENITH ENERGY
TERMINAL HOLDINGS, LLC TO ISQ
SPRINGER HOLDINGS, LLC. AMEND
ORDINANCE 188554.
>> COLLEAGUES, WE CONTINUE THIS
AS A FIRST READING. WE HEARD
PUBLIC TESTIMONY AND BEGAN
PUBLIC OR COUNCIL DISCUSSION OF
THE GREEN MORILLO ONE AMENDMENT.
WE ARE STILL IN THAT MOTION AT
THIS TIME. I WANT TO EXTEND A
COURTESY TO COUNCILOR GREEN TO
GIVE US ANY UPDATES ON WHERE WE
ARE.
>> I'M ACTUALLY GOING TO PASS
THAT TO COUNCILOR MORILLO,
WHO'S GOING TO PICK US UP WHERE
WE LEFT OFF.
>> PERFECT. COUNCILOR MORILLO,
PLEASE GO AHEAD.
>> THANK YOU ALL AND THANKS FOR
YOUR PATIENCE OVER THIS
DISCUSSION. I THINK IT'S
SOMETHING THAT'S REALLY
IMPORTANT TO THE PUBLIC. WE
BROUGHT FORWARD AN AMENDMENT.
SO I'M JUST GOING TO SORT OF
LEVEL SET SOME OF THE THINGS
THAT HAD BEEN SAID LAST WEEK SO
THAT WE CAN REMEMBER WHERE WE
ARE. SO OUR AMENDMENT ALLOWS US
TO BRING A CITIZEN SUIT. AND
LAST WEEK WE HEARD THAT CITIZEN
SUITS CAN'T ENFORCE CITY
CONTRACTS. OUR CITIZEN SUIT
PROVISION USES ONE OF THE
OLDEST TOOLS IN CONTRACT LAW,
WHICH IS NAMING A THIRD PARTY
BENEFICIARY HERE. WHO'S GOING
TO BE THE PUBLIC? WHO CAN
ENFORCE THE AGREEMENT. AND
PRIVATE PARTIES DO THIS EVERY
SINGLE DAY. COURTS HAVE CALLED
CITIZENS THE PRINCIPAL
BENEFICIARIES OF CITY
FRANCHISES FOR DECADES, AND
HAVE ALLOWED THEM TO ENFORCE
CONTRACTS BETWEEN A GOVERNMENT
AND FRANCHISEE. WHEN THERE IS
INTENT FOR THAT TO OCCUR. AS
OUR AMENDMENT PROPOSES, IN FACT,
COURTS HAVE HELD THAT THE
COMPANY OPERATING UNDER
FRANCHISE TAKES ON DUTIES TO
THE PUBLIC. BEYOND AN ORDINARY
CONTRACT, A FRANCHISE IS
EXACTLY WHERE PUBLIC
ENFORCEMENT BELONGS. WE ALSO
HEARD THAT CITIZEN SUITS BRING
BELONG TO ENVIRONMENTAL LAW,
NOT TO FRANCHISE LAW. AND WHILE
THAT MIGHT FEEL LIKE A LAWYERLY
DISTINCTION THAT WE WANT TO
MAKE, IT'S NOT BECAUSE THE
TOOLS IN A CONTRACT FOLLOW THE
RISK IN THE CONTRACT, NOT THE
LABEL OF THE COVER. WE PUT
ARBITRATION CLAUSES INTO
EMPLOYMENT AGREEMENTS AND
SEISMIC STANDARDS INTO HOUSING
LEASES, AND NOBODY OBJECTS THAT
WE'VE MIXED UP OUR AREAS OF LAW
WHEN WE DO THAT. SO WHAT IS
INSIDE THIS FRANCHISE THAT I
THINK COUNCIL NEEDS TO CONSIDER
IS THE RISK. PORTLANDERS ARE
NOT GOING TO EXPERIENCE RISK AS
FRANCHISE LAW OR ENVIRONMENTAL
LAW. THEY EXPERIENCE IT AS FUEL
MOVING UNDER THEIR STREETS. AND
THE ONLY THING THAT PROTECTS
THEM IS WHETHER SOMEONE CAN
HOLD THE OPERATOR TO ITS
CONTRACTUAL SAFETY COMMITMENTS.
CONGRESS BUILT CITIZEN SUITS
INTO THE CLEAN AIR OR PIPELINE
SAFETY ACT AND ACT GOVERNING
PIPES LIKE THESE FOR THAT EXACT
SAME REASON. WE ALSO HEARD THAT
CITIZEN SUITS ARE UNNECESSARY
BECAUSE THE FRANCHISE AGREEMENT
ALREADY HAS MECHANISMS TO HOLD
THE FRANCHISEE ACCOUNTABLE. BUT
WHAT WE'VE SEEN IS THAT THESE
MECHANISMS ARE NOT SUFFICIENT.
ZENITH ENFORCEMENT UNDER THE
FRANCHISE AGREEMENT FOUND ZERO
VIOLATIONS. WHILE THE STATE
FOUND MANY VIOLATIONS, AND THEY
FOUND THAT THERE WERE YEARS OF
UNAUTHORIZED OPERATION AT THIS
FACILITY AFTER REPORTS FROM
CITIZENS. WHEN CONGRESS WROTE
THE CLEAN WATER ACT, IT
INCLUDED FULL GOVERNMENT
ENFORCEMENT POWERS AND ADDED
CITIZEN SUITS AS WELL. BECAUSE
REMEDIES ON PAPER DON'T DON'T
ENFORCE THEMSELVES, AND
AGENCIES RUN SHORT ON STAFF
BUDGET. AND SOMETIMES WE ARE
UNABLE OR UNWILLING TO ENFORCE
THEM. WE JUST EXPERIENCED THAT
WITH ZENITH. WE ALSO HEARD THAT
CITIZEN SUIT CONDITION IS NOT
RELATED TO I SQUARED'S
QUALIFICATIONS. THE CLAUSE SAYS
CONDITIONS MUST RELATE TO THE
BUYER'S QUALIFICATIONS TO
PERFORM ACCORDING TO THE TERMS
OF THIS FRANCHISE, AS COUNCIL
DEEMS REASONABLY APPROPRIATE.
SO THE QUESTION IS WHAT
ASSURANCE DO WE HAVE THAT I
SQUARED IS GOING TO PERFORM
WITH ZENITH IN 2018? THE CITY
AT LEAST HAD YEARS OF OPERATING
EXPERIENCE WITH ZENITH, AND
EVEN THAT DID NOT PROTECT US.
THIS BUYER HAS NO EXPERIENCE IN
PORTLAND. ITS QUALIFICATIONS
SUBMISSION IS BASED ON PROMISES
AND ITS PARENT COMPANY FINANCES.
A PROMISE IS ONLY AS GOOD AS
YOUR ABILITY TO HOLD THE MAKER
TO IT. OVERSIGHT IS WHAT TURNS
A PROMISE INTO A QUALIFICATION,
AND FOR A BUYER THAT HAS NO
INTENTION OF BREAKING THE LAW,
THIS PROVISION DOESN'T COST A
DOLLAR TO THEM. WE HEARD THAT I
SQUARED MIGHT REJECT THE
CITIZEN SUIT CONDITION AND THE
SALE COLLAPSES, BUT WE HAVEN'T
EVEN HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO
TALK TO THEM. I EMAILED JULES
BAILEY EARLIER LAST WEEK AND I
DID NOT HEAR BACK FROM THEM.
THIS CONDITION IS NOT GOING TO
KILL THE SALE. ONLY I CAN DO
THAT. AND BY REFUSING A TERM
THAT COSTS A COMPLIANT OPERATOR,
NOTHING. LAST WEEK I SQUARED,
STOOD AT THE DAIS AND
VOLUNTEERED AN ANNUAL PUBLIC
REPORT OF ITS FUELS, ITS AND
ITS EMISSIONS. A COMPANY THAT
VOLUNTEERS TRANSPARENCY SHOULD
NOT FEAR ENFORCEMENT. IF THEY
WOULD WALK AWAY FROM THIS
PURCHASE RATHER THAN BE HELD TO
THEIR CONTRACT. THAT ISN'T A
RISK THAT'S CREATED BY OUR
AMENDMENT. IN FACT, THAT'S THE
MOST IMPORTANT FACT THAT WE
COULD LEARN BEFORE HANDING THEM
THE LIFE AND SAFETY OF
THOUSANDS OF PORTLANDERS. I
SQUID'S REJECTION OF THE
TRANSFER WITH A CITIZEN SUIT
CONDITION STOPS NOTHING. IN
THAT CASE, THE QUESTION OF
TRANSFER CONSENT COMES BACK TO
THIS COUNCIL AND WE CAN ACT ON
IT AGAIN WITHIN WEEKS, OR
WHATEVER TERMS WE CHOOSE,
INCLUDING WITHOUT THE CITIZEN
SUPERVISION. WE GET TO CONTROL
THE AGENDA AS COUNCIL. ENGAGING
IN A GOOD FAITH PUBLIC PROCESS
IS NOT AN UNREASONABLE DELAY.
WE'VE ALSO HEARD FROM SOME OF
OUR COLLEAGUES THAT WE SHOULD
JUST WAIT. APPROVE THE TRANSFER
NOW, AND DO CITIZEN SUITS BY
ORDINANCE LATER. FIRST, WE KNOW
THAT LATER IS LEGALLY WEAKER.
TODAY IS WHEN WE HAVE LEVERAGE.
THE BUYER ACCEPTS THIS TERM AND
IT BECOMES PART OF THE
AGREEMENT LATER. IT'S THE CITY
REWRITING A SIGNED CONTRACT,
WHICH TENDS TO BE THE KIND OF
THING THAT GETS STRUCK DOWN IN
THE COURTS. SO WE'D BE
REJECTING THE STRONG VERSION
NOW FOR A WEAK VERSION LATER,
AND WHEN LATER COMES, WE'LL BE
TOLD WE CAN'T VOTE FOR IT
BECAUSE IT'S WEAK OR UNWORKABLE,
AND WE WILL FOREVER BE IN THE
POSITION OF NEVER DOING
ENFORCEMENT BECAUSE IT'S NEVER
THE RIGHT TIME. SECOND LATER
DOESN'T HAVE ANY LEVERAGE. THE
CITY ATTORNEY TOLD US THAT THE
PATH TO DOING THIS CONDITION,
IF WE WAIT UNTIL AFTER WE
APPROVE THE TRANSFER, IS
MUTUALLY AGREEABLE. AMENDMENT.
WHAT MAKES IT AGREEABLE TO A
COMPANY THAT HAS EVERYTHING IT
NEEDS FROM US FOR THE NEXT
DECADE? THIRD, IF WE APPROVE
THIS TRANSFER, WE CERTIFY THIS
BUYER AS QUALIFIED WITHOUT ANY
ASSURANCE MECHANISM. OUR OWN
VOTE BECOMES THE FIRST PIECE OF
EVIDENCE AGAINST THE FUTURE
ORDINANCE ASKING FOR MORE
CONDITIONS. IF WE DON'T PURSUE
THIS CITIZEN SUIT CONDITION,
WHERE DOES THAT LEAVE US TODAY?
CITIZEN SUITS ARE NOT NEW.
COURTS HAVE LET THE PUBLIC
ENFORCE CITY CONTRACTS FOR A
CENTURY, AND CONGRESS HAS BEEN
WRITING CITIZEN SUITS INTO LAW
FOR DECADES, AND THEY COST
NOTHING TO A COMPANY THAT
INTENDS TO FOLLOW THE LAW. SO,
COLLEAGUES, I AM MOVING THIS
ITEM. I'M MOVING TO CONTINUE
THIS ITEM FOR TWO WEEKS SO THAT
WE CAN HAVE OUR CITY LEADERSHIP,
INCLUDING OUR CITY COUNCIL,
START CONVERSATIONS WITH I
SQUARED PRINCIPLES TO ENCOURAGE
ACCEPTANCE OF THE CITIZEN SUIT
CONDITION AND COMPLETE THIS
TRANSFER IN COMMUNICATION WITH
THE CITY AND OUR BODY. I
SQUARED HAS REPEATEDLY STATED
THAT THEY WILL OPERATE THIS
SITE RESPONSIBLY AND IN
ACCORDANCE WITH THE LAW. AS A
BODY, OUR DUTY IS TO THE
CONSTITUENTS WE REPRESENT AND
OUR CONSTITUENTS ARE STRUGGLING
TO FIND TRUST IN THE GOVERNANCE
OF OUR CITY. WE SHOULD ENGAGE
IN CONVERSATION WITH I SQUARED
TO HELP THEM UNDERSTAND. THIS
CONDITION WE ARE PROPOSING IS
THE BEST WAY TO ENSURE THAT
THEY, AS AN ENTITY SEEKING TO
OPERATE IN PORTLAND AND THE
CITY, ARE SHOWING UP AS
PARTNERS TO PROMOTE THE
PUBLIC'S TRUST. WE HAVE THE
AUTHORITY TO SET THIS CONDITION
AS COUNCIL SETS CONDITIONS IT
DEEMS REASONABLY APPROPRIATE.
BUT AUTHORITIES EXERCISED
THROUGH ENGAGEMENT,
ACCOUNTABILITY AND COMMITMENT
TO PARTNERSHIP. WE CAN BE BUILT.
WE CAN CONTINUE TO REBUILD THE
PUBLIC'S TRUST TODAY. AND SO,
COLLEAGUES, I WOULD REALLY HOPE
THAT THIS AMENDMENT IS
SOMETHING THAT WE CAN DISCUSS
WITH I SQUARED BEFORE WE JUST
VOTE IT DOWN AND DON'T DO ANY
OF OUR DUTIES. THANKS.
>> THANK YOU. COUNCILOR.
MORILLO. SO COLLEAGUES, WE ARE
IN THE MOTION TO THE AMENDMENT.
WE ARE UNABLE TO ENTERTAIN
ADDITIONAL MOTIONS UNTIL WE
MOVE ON FROM THIS AMENDMENT.
AND SO TO THE AMENDMENT,
COUNCILOR RYAN. OKAY. COUNCILOR.
>> NOVICK THANK YOU, MR.
PRESIDENT. I JUST WANT TO FLAG
AGAIN TWO ODDITIES HERE. ONE IS
THAT WE'VE BEEN HEARING FOR
YEARS HOW BAD ZENITH IS, AND
NOW ZENITH WANTS TO LEAVE AND
BE REPLACED BY A COMPANY THAT
IS BOUND BY ITS COMMITMENT TO
ITS FUNDERS TO GO TO 100%
RENEWABLE BY THE END OF 2027.
AND WE'RE TALKING ABOUT PUTTING
UP A POTENTIAL BARRIER TO
ZENITH LEAVING. I WOULD HAVE
THOUGHT THE IDEA OF ZENITH
LEAVING WOULD HAVE LED PEOPLE
TO SAY, DING DONG, THE WITCH IS
DEAD, NANA, NANA, NANA, NANA,
NANA, NANA, HEY HEY, GOODBYE.
SECOND, IT IS THERE IS A
DIFFERENCE BETWEEN A CITIZEN
SUIT CLAUSE AND A STATUTE OF
GENERAL APPLICABILITY AND A
CITIZEN'S CLAUSE. IN THIS
SITUATION. THIS IS WE'RE NOT
TALKING ABOUT A STATUTE OF
GENERAL APPLICABILITY. WE'RE
TALKING ABOUT AN AGREEMENT
BETWEEN TWO PARTIES. AND
NORMALLY THE PEOPLE WHO ENFORCE
AGREEMENTS BETWEEN TWO PARTIES
WITH LAWSUITS ARE THE PARTIES
TO THAT AGREEMENT. YES. THERE
ARE SUCH THINGS AS THIRD PARTY
BENEFICIARIES WHICH HAVE A
RIGHT TO SUE IN CERTAIN
CIRCUMSTANCES, LIKE WHEN
THERE'S A CREDITOR OF THE
PROMISEE IN A CONTRACT AND THE
PROMISEE OWES THEM A FINANCIAL,
EXISTING FINANCIAL OR LEGAL
OBLIGATION THAT THE PROMISOR IS
PAYING OFF. THAT IS NOT THIS
CASE. WHAT IF THE IF ICE IF
THIS AGREEMENT IS VIOLATED BY
ZENITH OR I-SQUARED OR WHAT
HAVE YOU, THEN THE CITY SHOULD
SUE TO ENFORCE IT. IF WE ADOPT
THIS AMENDMENT, WE'RE
ESSENTIALLY SAYING WE, THE CITY
OF PORTLAND, DO NOT TRUST
OURSELVES TO ENFORCE THIS
AGREEMENT. SO WE'RE OUTSOURCING
ENFORCEMENT TO THE GENERAL
PUBLIC. WE ESSENTIALLY
ANNOUNCING WE ARE A
DYSFUNCTIONAL GOVERNMENT.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR NOVICK
COUNCILOR RYAN. COUNCILOR RYAN.
>> YEAH, I DID JUMP IN. I
UNFORTUNATELY COULDN'T ATTEND
THE EXECUTIVE SESSION. SO I
WANT TO TAKE A BREATH HERE TO
MAKE SURE THAT I, I KNOW THAT
YOU ALL RECEIVED SOME
INFORMATION. SO I WILL CONNECT
WITH A STAFFER BEFORE I ASK MY
QUESTION. BUT. YEAH, OKAY.
>> THANK YOU. COUNCILOR
COUNCILOR. PIRTLE-GUINEY.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT.
AS YOU ALL REMEMBER, WE WENT
INTO EXEC SESSION LAST WEEK IN
THE MIDDLE OF TALKING ABOUT
THIS AMENDMENT. AND AT THAT
TIME, I HAD A FEW TECHNICAL
QUESTIONS, THE ANSWERS OF WHICH
I'D HOPED WOULD LEAD ME TO BE
READY TO VOTE YES. BUT COMING
OUT OF THAT SESSION, BASED ON
THE ADVICE OF OUR ATTORNEY, IT
IS MY UNDERSTANDING THAT THIS
AMENDMENT IS NOT LEGALLY
PERMISSIBLE, THAT THIS
AMENDMENT CROSSES THE LINE FROM
A CONDITION OF THE CONTRACT AND
GOES FARTHER THAN WE CAN
LEGALLY GO. THAT MEANS THAT
THIS IS NOT A POLICY CALL, BUT
A MATTER OF WHETHER I TRUST OUR
ATTORNEY'S LEGAL ADVICE. AND
WHILE THERE ARE TIMES WHERE
MANY OF US HAVE DISAGREED WITH
OUR ATTORNEYS GENERALLY FEEL
THAT WE NEED TO LISTEN TO THE
FOLKS WHO ARE GOING TO HAVE TO
REPRESENT US. THERE ARE A
NUMBER OF CHOICES COMING BEFORE
US OVER THE NEXT SIX MONTHS,
WHERE WE WILL BE LOOKING AT THE
FUTURE OF THE CEI HUB, AND
THERE IS MUCH WORK TO DO THERE.
BUT ON THIS AMENDMENT, I FEEL
AS THOUGH I NEED TO FOLLOW THE
ADVICE THAT WAS GIVEN TO ME AND
VOTE NO.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR
PIRTLE-GUINEY. COUNCILOR
MORILLO.
>> YEAH, THANK YOU EVERYONE.
EVERYONE SHOULD HAVE RECEIVED A
LEGAL MEMO IN THEIR INBOXES
FROM OTHER LAND USE ATTORNEYS
ON THIS VERY ISSUE. I RECOMMEND
PEOPLE READ THAT. AND IT'S VERY
CLEAR TO ME THAT PEOPLE HAVE
NOT READ THAT. THAT'S ALSO PART
OF WHY I UNDERSTAND WE'RE IN
THE MOTION FOR THE AMENDMENT
RIGHT NOW, BUT THAT'S ALSO WHY
I RECOMMEND THAT WE ACTUALLY
TABLE THIS DISCUSSION, HAVE THE
TIME TO TALK TO. I SQUARED
ABOUT THIS AND CONTINUE THE
NEGOTIATIONS BECAUSE IT'S CLEAR
THAT WE'RE NOT READY TO HAVE
THIS VOTE. BUT I WILL SAY AGAIN
IN MY SPEECH, I SAID IT BEFORE
AND I'LL SAY IT AGAIN, THERE
ARE THIRD PARTY BENEFICIARY
CONTRACTS IN THE CONTEXT OF
FRANCHISES. AND THAT WAS ALSO
ADDRESSED IN THE LEGAL MEMO
THAT WAS SENT. AND FORD'S
CONTRACT BETWEEN A CITY AND A
FRANCHISE UTILITY. YES. IN
SEVERAL STATES GOING BACK TO
THE 1800S. AND WHEN AN
AGREEMENT'S OWN LANGUAGE SAID
RESIDENTS COULD ENFORCE IT, THE
COURT ENFORCED IT AS WRITTEN.
WHAT WE HAVEN'T FOUND IS A CITY
FRANCHISE THAT ASSEMBLES THE
PACKAGE EXACTLY THE WAY THIS
ONE DOES, WHICH IS THE NOTICE.
FIRST, A CURE WINDOW, RECOVERY
DEFINED, ETC. BUT THOSE
GUARDRAILS AREN'T OURS EITHER.
THAT'S HOW CONGRESS HAS BUILT
ENFORCEMENT INTO ENVIRONMENTAL
LAW FOR 50 YEARS. SO NO, WE
DIDN'T INVENT ANYTHING NEW HERE.
EVERY PIECE IS SETTLED LAW AND
WE PUT IT INTO A CONDITION.
THAT'S HOW CONTRACTS WORK. AND
IF COURTS WILL FIND THAT
CITIZEN ENFORCEMENT AND
CONTRACTS THAT NEVER SAID IT,
THERE'S NOTHING RADICAL ABOUT A
CONTRACT THAT SAYS IT. ALL
WE'RE DOING IS REMOVING THE
DOUBT. THE. IT'S NOT ABOUT
WHETHER OR NOT WE HAVE A
FUNCTIONAL OR DYSFUNCTIONAL
GOVERNMENT. THIS IS AN
ADDITIONAL ENFORCEMENT LAYER.
SO THAT SHOULD OUR EXECUTIVE
FAIL TO ENFORCE THIS CONTRACT,
THEN THE PUBLIC HAS OTHER
RECOURSE. AND AGAIN, THIS HAS
BEEN ESTABLISHED IN LAW FOR A
VERY LONG TIME. SO THE PUBLIC
DESERVES TO HAVE AS MANY
OPTIONS AS POSSIBLE WHEN IT IS
THEIR LIVES THAT ARE GOING TO
BE IMPACTED BY THIS. AND I WILL
ALSO SAY, I'M VERY SURPRISED TO
HEAR THAT PEOPLE ARE JUST
TAKING MY WORD FOR IT FOR HOW
THEY ARE GOING TO RUN THE
FACILITY. YES, ZENITH WAS
RUNNING IT POORLY. YES, THEY
GOT AWAY WITH A LOT OF THINGS.
AND TO THINK THAT A COMPANY IS
JUST GOING TO COME IN AND WE'RE
GOING TO BUY THEIR ADVERTISING
WHEN WE KNOW NEXT TO NOTHING
ABOUT THEM IS EXTREMELY ABSURD
TO ME. WE HAVE TO EXAMINE WHO
THESE COMPANIES ARE, WHAT
THEY'RE GOING TO DO, HOW AND
WHY. BECAUSE THIS IS THE NUMBER
ONE ISSUE THAT'S GOING TO
IMPACT THE CITY. AND IT'S IT'S
SOMETHING THAT PEOPLE ARE ONLY
GOING TO UNDERSTAND ONCE AN
EARTHQUAKE ACTUALLY HAPPENS.
AND THE ENTIRE WILLAMETTE RIVER
IS POISONED AND OUR CITY IS ON
FIRE. THAT IS REALLY WHAT'S AT
STAKE. AND I KNOW SOME OF THE
FOLKS IN THE AUDIENCE LAUGHED
LAST WEEK WHEN I SAID THAT, BUT
THAT IS NOT AN EXAGGERATION.
THAT IS WHAT IS ON THE LINE
HERE. SO I JUST WANT TO SAY,
COLLEAGUES, THAT I REALLY HOPE
THAT WE CAN ACTUALLY TRY TO
PUSH THIS. AS THE MEMO
DISCUSSED, THIS IS A REASONABLE
CONDITION, AND WE ARE EMPOWERED
TO IMPOSE REASONABLE CONDITIONS
ON A FRANCHISE TRANSFER. THANK
YOU.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR MORILLO
COUNCILOR GREEN.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT.
YOU KNOW, COUNCILOR NOVICK, I
JUST WANT TO RESPOND TO THE
COMMENT ON WHETHER PORTLANDERS
THINK THAT THIS IS A FUNCTIONAL
GOVERNMENT OR NOT. IN THE
CONTEXT OF ADOPTING THIS, I
ACTUALLY THINK THERE'S A LOT OF
PORTLANDERS WHO DON'T THINK
THAT WE'RE A FUNCTIONAL
GOVERNMENT BECAUSE WE FAIL TO
DO PROPER OVERSIGHT AND HOLD
OURSELVES ACCOUNTABLE. AND
THAT'S SOMETHING THAT WE ALSO
NEED TO TAKE TO HEART. AND IT'S
IT'S VERY URGENT CONCERN, I
THINK, FOR A LOT OF PORTLANDERS,
THEY DO WANT ZENITH OUT. AND
THE ADVOCATES WHO ARE ASKING
FOR A THIRD PARTY SUPERVISION
ALSO WANT ZENITH OUT. AND THEY
DON'T PROBABLY LOVE THIS
TRANSFER AT ALL, BUT THEY ARE
WILLING TO ACCEPT THAT IF WE
CAN PUT THIS CONDITION ON, THEN
WE CAN BRIDGE THAT GAP AND, YOU
KNOW, SEND A SIGNAL THAT THE
CITY IS WILLING TO. MAKE MAKE
MOVEMENTS TOWARDS, YOU KNOW,
HOLDING ITS OWN SELF
ACCOUNTABLE, FRANKLY. SO I
THINK I THINK THE EYE IS IN THE
BEHOLDER ON THAT ONE ON WHAT IS
A FUNCTIONAL GOVERNMENT OR NOT.
BUT I THINK I WANT TO GO TO
COUNCILOR. PIRTLE-GUINEY. I
THINK YOUR YOUR POSITION IS
WHETHER YOU LIKE IT OR NOT, YOU
JUST DON'T THINK THIS IS
APPROPRIATE CONDITION FOR THE
SCOPE OF THE FRANCHISE. I THINK
IT IS, AND I THINK IT IS
BECAUSE AS I READ THE FRANCHISE
AGREEMENT. IT SAYS, YOU KNOW,
THE CITY MAY MAY CONDITION ANY
TRANSFER OF THIS FRANCHISE UPON
SUCH CONDITIONS RELATED TO
TECHNICAL, LEGAL AND FINANCIAL
QUALIFICATIONS OF THE
PROSPECTIVE PARTY TO PERFORM
ACCORDING TO THE TERMS OF THE
TO TO PERFORM ACCORDING TO THE
TERMS OF THIS AGREEMENT. AND
THAT'S AN IMPORTANT PIECE THERE.
AND THEN IT FINISHES BY SAYING
AS IT DEEMS REASONABLY
APPROPRIATE. SO IT'S THE
COUNCIL ADOPTING AN ORDINANCE.
SO IT'S THE CITY COUNCIL THAT'S
MAKING THE JUDGMENT ON WHAT IS
REASONABLY APPROPRIATE. AS FAR
AS I'M CONCERNED. READING THE
APPLICATION, READING THE
STRUCTURE, THE VERY MANY
LAYERED DEGREES OF SEPARATION
AND HOLDING COMPANIES ON THIS
STRUCTURE. I HAVE OPEN
QUESTIONS ON WHETHER THEY HAVE
THE LEGAL CAPABILITY TO PERFORM.
I HAVE NO DOUBT THAT THEY HAVE
GOOD LAWYERS, AND I KNOW THAT
THEY'RE REGISTERED IN THE STATE
OF OREGON, BUT THAT'S NOT THE
SAME AS BEING ABLE TO PERFORM
TO THE TERMS AND. AND SO I
THINK YES, TO COUNCILOR MORILLO
POINTS, IT'S NOT ENOUGH TO JUST
ACCEPT ASSERTIONS OF SAYING
WE'RE GOING TO BE BETTER. LIKE,
I HOPE THAT'S TRUE. AND I THINK
THIS IS A REASONABLE CONDITION.
I THINK IT'S VALID IN THE
CONTEXT OF FRANCHISE TRANSFER.
AND I THINK IF WE IF WE MOVE
FORWARD WITHOUT PLACING SOME
CONDITIONS ON THIS, I THINK
THAT WE'RE GOING TO DO DAMAGE
TO THE TRUST IN GOVERNMENT THAT
THAT IS, FRANKLY, PRETTY
FRAGILE. SO I AND I THINK IT'S
WORTH TRYING TO GET ICE CORE
CAPITAL TO AGREE TO THIS. I
ACTUALLY DON'T KNOW WHY THEY
WOULDN'T. SO I DON'T KNOW IF
THAT'S THE MOTION ON THE FLOOR.
MORE OF AN APPEAL, BUT I'LL
LEAVE IT AT THAT.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR GREEN.
COUNCILOR ZIMMERMAN.
>> JUST WANTED TO CHECK IN WITH
YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT, IN
TERMS OF WHERE WE'RE AT AND
YOUR INTENT ON HOW LONG THE
COUNCIL GOES TODAY.
>> WE ARE GOING TO WE WE MUST
BE DONE AT 130 TODAY.
>> I'D LIKE TO LIMIT DEBATE TO
THE CURRENT AMENDMENT TO THOSE
THAT ARE IN THE QUEUE. THANK
YOU.
>> I'M GOING TO GO AHEAD AND
LIMIT DEBATE TO THOSE IN THE
QUEUE. THANK YOU VERY MUCH,
COUNSELOR ZIMMERMAN. COUNSELOR
RYAN.
>> YES, THANK YOU, COUNCIL
PRESIDENT, WE'VE BEEN ON THIS
ISSUE, THIS LEGISLATION SINCE
JULY 23RD, AND IT WAS REQUESTED
BY THE STAFF A MONTH EARLIER
THAN THAT. SO THE SLOW WALKING
OF THIS LEGISLATION IS NOTED,
AND CONGRATULATIONS TO THOSE IN
OPPOSITION FOR SUCCESSFULLY
DOING THAT. I WANT TO THANK YOU,
COUNCILOR PIRTLE-GUINEY, FOR
AFFIRMING MY READ. I DID
DISCUSS WITH MY STAFF FURTHER
WHEN THIS AMENDMENT WAS FIRST
PROPOSED, SO I WILL NOT BE
SUPPORTING THIS AMENDMENT. IT'S
TO FINANCIALLY RISKY TIME TO
VOTE UP OR DOWN ON THIS
LEGISLATION. I'M GLAD WE'RE
LIMITING DEBATE. THANKS.
>> THANK YOU. COUNCILOR RYAN
COUNCILOR MORILLO, LAST WORD ON
THE AMENDMENT.
>> COUNCILOR RYAN, I KNOW THAT
YOU ARE CONSTANTLY CENTERING
THE PERSPECTIVE OF OIL
COMPANIES, BECAUSE I REMEMBER
WHEN I WAS CHAIR OF THE.
COUNCILOR CITY.
>> COUNCILOR MORILLO, I FIND
THAT TO BE IMPUGNING THE
CHARACTER OF A COLLEAGUE.
PLEASE.
>> OKAY. WELL, HE IMPUGNED OUR
CHARACTER WHEN HE IMPLIED THAT
WE WERE SPECIFICALLY SLOW
ROLLING THIS. AND THAT IS A
COMMENT THAT PUTS THE CITY AT
LEGAL RISK WHEN THAT IS NOT
TRUE. SO HE WAS IMPUGNING OUR
CHARACTER. I HOPE YOU'LL HOLD
HIM ACCOUNTABLE FOR THAT AS
WELL, BECAUSE IT IS COMMON FOR
AGENDA ITEMS TO BE PUT ON THE
COUNCIL WITHIN 90 DAYS. AND
THERE WERE, AS YOU HAVE SEEN,
EVERYONE IN THE AUDIENCE. AND
RIGHT NOW, A LOT OF DELAYS DUE
TO A LOT OF THE LONG SPEECHES
THAT PEOPLE GIVE. SO TO SAY
THAT THIS WAS INTENTIONALLY
DONE TO PUT THE CITY AT
FINANCIAL RISK, I THINK IS
IMPUGNING OUR CHARACTER, BUT I
WANT TO ADDRESS A FEW OF THE
OTHER MORE TECHNICAL THINGS
THAN WHILE WE'RE AT IT, THE
IDEA THAT I SQUARED IS GOING TO
OPERATE DIFFERENTLY BECAUSE OF
THEIR OWN ADVERTISING DOESN'T
MAKE ANY SENSE. WHEN WE KNOW
THAT A LOT OF THE EMPLOYEES
THAT WORK AT I SQUARED ARE
CARRYOVERS FROM ZENITH, IF NOT
THE VAST MAJORITY OF THEM. SO
WE HAVE AN OPPORTUNITY TO
ACTUALLY ADD ACCOUNTABILITY
INTO THIS FRANCHISE AGREEMENT.
AND I DON'T KNOW WHY WE
WOULDN'T TAKE EVERY ANY STEP
THAT WE CAN TO PROTECT
PORTLANDERS FROM THE POTENTIAL
IMPACTS OF AN OIL TRAIN DURING
AN EARTHQUAKE OR ANY OTHER
ENVIRONMENTAL DISASTER. THE
FRANCHISE AGREEMENT TRANSFERS
ARE LEGISLATIVE DECISIONS THAT
BELONG TO US AS COUNCIL, AND
WHY THIS COUNCIL REPEATEDLY
REFUSES TO USE OUR AUTHORITY,
OR TO SAY THAT THERE IS ALWAYS
A BETTER TIME TO DO SOMETHING
IS EXTREMELY FRUSTRATING.
COUNCIL IS AUTHORIZED TO TO
IMPOSE CONDITIONS ON THIS
FRANCHISE TRANSFER, AND A
CITIZEN SUIT IS A CONDITION,
AND IT'S RELATED TO THE
QUALIFICATIONS OF THE
PROSPECTIVE PARTY TO PERFORM
THE CITIZEN ZOO CONDITION
CHANGES NO TERMS OF THE
FRANCHISE, SO THERE IS NO NEED
TO RENEGOTIATE. IT IS AN
ADDITIONAL CONDITION AND THE
CITIZEN SUIT CONDITION IS
REASONABLY APPROPRIATE. SO
DOING LEGISLATIVE PROCESS,
HAVING PUBLIC PROCESS IS NOT
UNREASONABLE. IT'S NOT AN
UNREASONABLE DELAY AND IT'S NOT
PURPOSEFUL. THIS IS PART OF OUR
DUTIES AS A COUNCIL TO DO
OVERSIGHT AND TO DO OUR DUE
DILIGENCE FOR PORTLANDERS, NOT
FOR AN OIL COMPANY'S EASE OF
TRANSFER. WE HAVE A
RESPONSIBILITY HERE TO
PORTLANDERS TODAY. AND IF OTHER
PEOPLE ARE GOING TO IMPUGN MY
MOTIVES, THEN I HOPE YOU HOLD
THEM ACCOUNTABLE TOO. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR MORILLO
KEELAN, CAN WE PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON GREEN MORILLO ONE.
>> MOVE BY GREEN. SECONDED BY
MORILLO. KOYAMA LANE. AYE,
MORILLO MORILLO.
>> AYE, MORILLO.
>> NOVICK NAY.
>> CLARK. NO.
>> GREEN BY ZIMMERMAN.
>> NO.
>> AVALOS.
>> I.
>> SMITH.
>> NO.
>> KANAL I PIRTLE-GUINEY. NO.
>> RYAN.
>> NO.
>> DUNPHY.
>> I.
>> THE AMENDMENT FAILS WITH A
VOTE OF SIX AYES AND SIX NAYS.
>> COLLEAGUES. I FEEL AS THOUGH
THIS ITEM HAS. THE UNDERLYING
HAS HAD BEEN PRETTY THOROUGHLY
DISCUSSED THROUGH THE PROCESS
OF THIS. DISCUSSING THIS
AMENDMENT. UNLESS THERE IS
OBJECTION, I WOULD LIKE TO MOVE
TO PASS THIS TO SECOND READING
WITHOUT FURTHER DISCUSSION. IS
THERE OBJECTION? OKAY, THIS
ITEM MOVES TO.
>> I OBJECT OKAY.
>> COUNCILOR. MORILLO.
>> I THINK THAT I THINK WE
SHOULD HAVE A MEETING WITH I
SQUARED TO DISCUSS THE UPDATED
AMENDMENT.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR MORILLO
COLLEAGUES, IS THERE FURTHER
DISCUSSION OF THE UNDERLYING.
>> JUST A POINT OF INFORMATION
WHEN YOU SAY THE UPDATED
AMENDMENT, COULD YOU TELL US
MORE WHAT YOU MEAN? COUNCILOR.
MORILLO.
>> I THINK THAT THIS COUNCIL WE
HAVE NOT EVEN HAD THE
OPPORTUNITY TO TALK TO. I
SQUARED ABOUT THESE UPDATED
CONDITIONS. SOME OF THE PEOPLE
WHO OBJECTED HERE WEREN'T ABLE
TO BE AT THE EXECUTIVE SESSION
TO EVEN TALK TO THE ATTORNEYS.
WE WEREN'T ABLE TO HAVE A BACK
AND FORTH. IT DOESN'T MAKE
SENSE FOR US TO MOVE FORWARD ON
THE ASSUMPTIONS OF WHAT A
COMPANY IS GOING TO DO, WITHOUT
ACTUALLY HAVING THAT
CONVERSATION WITH I SQUARED.
LIKE I SAID, I DID TRY TO DO MY
DUE DILIGENCE. I EMAILED JULES
BAILEY LAST WEEK IN THE HOPES
OF TALKING TO HIM BEFORE THIS
CAME BACK TO COUNCIL, SO I
WOULDN'T WASTE EVERYONE'S TIME
AND EXTEND THIS PROCESS ANY
FURTHER. CONTRARY TO THE
ACCUSATIONS MADE BY MY
COLLEAGUES. BUT UNFORTUNATELY I
DID NOT GET A RESPONSE. SO
UNTIL WE HAVE THAT MEETING, I
DON'T REALLY SEE HOW WE CAN
CONTINUE TO MOVE FORWARD ON
THESE THINGS.
>> THANK YOU. COUNCILOR MORILLO
COLLEAGUES, ARE THERE ANY
FURTHER DISCUSSION OF THE
UNDERLYING. SEEING NONE. THIS
ITEM MOVES TO SECOND READING.
THANK YOU. KEELAN CAN WE PLEASE
MOVE TO. ACTUALLY, COUNCILOR
SMITH, YOU WOULD PULL THE
REMAINING ITEMS ON THE AGENDA.
WERE THE FORECLOSURE ITEMS THAT
YOU HAD PULLED. THERE WAS SOME
DISCUSSION WITH MY STAFF AND
YOUR STAFF ABOUT WHETHER TO
PULL THEM INDIVIDUALLY AT THIS
POINT, OR READ THEM THE LAST
FIVE TOGETHER. DO YOU HAVE A
PREFERENCE?
>> WE COULD ACTUALLY DO THEM
TOGETHER, BECAUSE THERE'S ONE
IN PARTICULAR THAT I'M REALLY
CONCERNED ABOUT, THAT I WANTED
TO MOVE OFF THE CONSENT AGENDA
INTO THE REGULAR AGENDA, BUT
YOU CAN MOVE THEM TOGETHER.
>> OKAY. THANK YOU. KEELAN CAN
WE PLEASE CALL ITEM 2026 247
2026 248, 2026 250 2026, 253,
2026 260 AND 2026 261 TOGETHER.
>> YES. THANK YOU. FIRST UP
2026-247. INITIATE FORECLOSURE
ACTION ON 7545 NORTHEAST SANDY
BOULEVARD FOR THE COLLECTION OF
DELINQUENT CITY LIENS AGAINST
THE PROPERTY. DOCUMENT 2026-248
INITIATE FORECLOSURE ACTION ON
7545 WITHIN NORTHEAST SANDY
BOULEVARD FOR THE COLLECTION OF
DELINQUENT CITY LIENS PLACED
AGAINST THE PROPERTY. DOCUMENT
2026-250 INITIATE FORECLOSURE
ACTION ON NORTH COLUMBIA
BOULEVARD FOR THE COLLECTION OF
DELINQUENT CITY LIENS PLACED
AGAINST THE PROPERTY. DOCUMENT
2026-253 INITIATE FORECLOSURE
ACTION ON 7101 THROUGH 7103
SOUTHEAST DIVISION STREET FOR
THE COLLECTION OF DELINQUENT
CITY LIENS PLACED AGAINST THE
PROPERTY. DOCUMENT 2026-260
INITIATE FORECLOSURE ACTION ON
5706 SOUTHEAST LAMBERT STREET
FOR THE COLLECTION OF
DELINQUENT CITY LIENS PLACED
AGAINST THE PROPERTY. DOCUMENT
2026-261 INITIATE FORECLOSURE
ACTION ON 855 NORTHEAST CHURCH
STREET FOR THE COLLECTION OF
DELINQUENT CITY LIENS PLACED
AGAINST THE PROPERTY.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH,
COLLEAGUES. ITEMS THAT ARE
PULLED FROM CONSENT AGENDA DO
NOT HAVE STAFF SUMMARIES, BUT
WE DO HAVE STAFF AVAILABLE TO
ANSWER QUESTIONS. COUNSELOR
SMITH.
>> THANK YOU. THE QUESTION THAT
I HAD ABOUT MANY OF THESE WERE
IN REGARDS TO, ARE THERE PEOPLE
ACTUALLY LIVING IN THE
RESIDENTIAL FORECLOSURES THAT
YOU HAVE ON THE AGENDA ITEM?
>> FOR THE RECORD, I'LL STATE
MY NAME. MY NAME IS KEVIN
FOSTER, FORECLOSURE PREVENTION
MANAGER. ALL OF THE PROPERTIES
ARE VACANT.
>> OKAY. AND I WANT TO GO TO
SPECIFIC ITEM 20. AND I BELIEVE
THAT'S AT 855 NORTHEAST CHURCH.
AND IT IS MY UNDERSTANDING THAT
THE OWNER OF THAT PROPERTY, WHO
HAPPENS TO LIVE IN MY DISTRICT
IN OUR GATE TERRACE, THAT THAT
IS A, A RENTAL PROPERTY AND
THAT THE OWNER HAS BEEN ILL AND
HAS NOT BEEN ABLE TO HAVE
CONVERSATIONS WITH THE
DEPARTMENT. AND I WANTED TO SEE
IF, IF THIS COULD BE MOVED TO
THE NEXT IN THE NEXT THREE
MONTHS.
>> SO I'VE ACTUALLY SPOKEN WITH
THE OWNER AS RECENTLY AS TWO
WEEKS AGO. REALLY? YES. AND
PRIOR TO THAT, I SPOKE TO HER
TWO WEEKS BEFORE THAT, AND SHE
WAS TRYING TO, TO WORK TO GET
THE THE ISSUES AT THE PROPERTY
RESOLVED. HER PLAN IS TO
EVENTUALLY REHAB THE ENTIRE
PROPERTY AND MAKE IT INTO ADULT
CARE FACILITY. AND THE REASON
WHY WE'RE PROCEEDING FORWARD IS
JUST BECAUSE OF THE IMPACT THAT
IT'S HAVING ON THE COMMUNITY,
THAT PROPERTY SPECIFICALLY. AND
RIGHT NOW, WE DON'T HAVE A
SOLID PLAN FORWARD FOR
RESOLUTION. OVER THE LAST
COUPLE OF DAYS, I'VE GOTTEN
SEVERAL COMPLAINTS FROM THE
NEIGHBORS THAT LIVE IN THAT
NEIGHBORHOOD AND WITH NO
RESOLUTION.
>> I UNDERSTAND, BUT I WOULD
LIKE TO PUT A MOTION ON THE
FLOOR BECAUSE AS OF THIS LAST
WEEKEND, I UNDERSTAND SHE WAS
IN THE HOSPITAL. AND MY CONCERN
IS THAT WITH HER CURRENT
MEDICAL SITUATION, THAT IT'S
GOING TO PUT A REAL STRAIN ON
HER ABILITY TO BE ABLE TO
NEGOTIATE WITH YOU ALL. IF WE
PUT THIS ON, THE NEXT 30 DAY
FORECLOSURE LIST, IS WOULD THAT
BE A PROBLEM IN THREE MONTHS
THAT WE BRING THIS BACK?
>> COUNCILOR. THANKS. I'LL JUMP
IN. THANK YOU. I'LL JUMP IN AND
ANSWER THE QUESTION FOR THE
RECORD. CFO JONAS BIERY. SO I
THINK THERE'S TWO A COUPLE OF
COUPLE OF PATHWAYS. ONE IS THIS
REMAINS ON THE LIST PASSED BY
COUNCIL TODAY. IT THEN MOVES ON
TO THE FORECLOSURE LIST. AND
THERE'S A WINDOW, I THINK 60
DAYS BEFORE THIS WILL GO TO THE
ACTUAL SALE. SO THAT'S
ADDITIONAL TIME FOR ANY
PROPERTY TO CONTINUE TO RESOLVE
THE ISSUES AND AVOID THAT
FORECLOSURE ACTION. A SECOND
PATHWAY WOULD BE SIMPLY TO
REMOVE IT FROM THIS INVENTORY.
TODAY. IT WOULD REMAIN OUT
THERE, CONTINUE TO STILL DIALOG
WITH THE WITH THE PROPERTY
OWNER, WITH THE OPTION TO BRING
IT BACK AT THE NEXT BATCH. I
JUST WANT TO BE CLEAR THAT WE
DON'T KNOW WHAT THE TIMING OF
THAT WILL BE. WE SORT OF HAVE
ASPIRATION TO COME EVERY 90 TO
120 DAYS. THAT'S SOMEWHAT
SUBJECT TO COUNCIL AGENDAS AND
OTHER ISSUES. BUT I JUST WANT
TO BE CLEAR, WE DON'T KNOW WHAT
THAT NEXT ITERATION WOULD BE TO
BRING IT BACK, BUT THAT WOULD
CERTAINLY BE A PATHWAY THAT'S
OPEN TO COUNCIL.
>> YES. CFO BIERY, I LIKE YOUR
SECOND IDEA BECAUSE IT WOULD
PUT IT GENERALLY WE HAVE THESE
EVERY 90 DAYS, AND IT WOULD
STILL GIVE HER THE OPPORTUNITY
TO WORK WITH THE DEPARTMENT
WITH REGARDLESS OF WHAT HER
PLANS ARE. BUT I THINK THERE'S
SOME THERE'S SOME REALLY
SERIOUS CRITICAL MEDICAL THINGS
THAT SHE NEEDS TO GET CONTROL
OF BEFORE SHE CAN HAVE A GOOD
CONVERSATION WITH YOU ABOUT
WHAT'S REALLY GOING ON. SO I
WOULD LIKE TO BE ABLE TO PUT A
MOTION ON THE FLOOR TO POSTPONE
THIS FORECLOSURE FORECLOSURE
ACTION FOR ANOTHER FOR THE NEXT
FORECLOSURE ACTION IN THE NEXT
90 DAYS.
>> BEFORE WE DO THAT, CAN I
HAVE MIKE JUST GIVE SOME
TESTIMONY ABOUT THE PROPERTY
AND ABOUT WHAT'S BEEN GOING ON
AT THE PROPERTY AND THE
NEIGHBORHOOD?
>> SURE. MIKE LIEFELD, PORTLAND
PERMITTING AND DEVELOPMENT,
NOTWITHSTANDING THE UPDATED
INFORMATION THAT YOU'RE SHARING,
I JUST WANT TO SHARE SOME
BACKGROUND ON THIS PROPERTY.
THE LISTED OWNER WAS A CONTRACT
PURCHASER IN 2016, WAS AWARE OF
THE VIOLATIONS WHEN THEY TOOK
OVER THE PROPERTY AROUND 2022
TO 2023. THEY INDICATED TO
STAFF THAT THEY WERE GOING TO
EVICT THE TENANTS TO REGAIN
CONTROL OF THE PROPERTY, WERE
UNABLE TO SECURE THAT LEGAL
AUTHORITY. THE CITY HAD TO
UNDERTAKE A CODE HEARING TO
SECURE A VACATE ORDER, WHICH WE
HAVE NOW EXECUTED. WE PERFORMED
TWO CONTRACTOR ABATEMENTS SINCE
THAT TIME. THERE IS A LARGE
VECTOR ISSUE THAT IS UNRESOLVED.
WE'RE NOT SEEING A LOT OF
MAINTENANCE FOR THE LOWEST
LEVEL NUISANCE ISSUES AT THE
PROPERTY BEING DEMONSTRATED BY
CURRENT OWNERSHIP. SO OUR TRACK
RECORD WOULD INDICATE THAT MORE
TIME MAY NOT PRODUCE THE RESULT
WE'RE ALL LOOKING FOR.
>> CAN I RESPOND? I THINK THAT
IF YOU'VE HAD SOME LATEST
CONVERSATIONS AND WITH ME
KNOWING ABOUT HER HEALTH
SITUATION, I THINK SHE PROBABLY
UNDERSTANDS THAT THIS IS
SERIOUS AT THIS POINT. I
WOULDN'T ASK FOR THIS UNLESS I
FELT LIKE THAT THERE WAS SOME
SERIOUS MEDICAL ISSUES THAT ARE
GOING ON THAT I THINK THAT SHE
NEEDS TO BE FULLY AWARE OF
WHAT'S GOING ON WITH WITH THE
PROPERTIES AND TO BE ABLE TO
GIVE YOU SOME FLUID, CONCRETE
ACTIONS WITHIN THE INTERIM. IT
WOULD BE GREAT IF WE COULD
ACTUALLY, ONCE SHE GETS TO A
POINT THAT SHE'S HEALTHY ENOUGH
TO HAVE THOSE KIND OF
CONVERSATIONS, AND I'M NOT
CONVINCED YET THAT SHE IS,
BECAUSE OF WHAT I'VE LEARNED
THIS WEEKEND, AND I UNDERSTAND
ABOUT THE 2016. BUT ALSO I ALSO
WANT TO SAY DURING THAT TIME,
HER HUSBAND WAS IN A COMA AND
HE GENERALLY HELPED WITH THE
MAINTENANCE OF HER RENTAL
PROPERTIES. AND HE IS NOW GONE.
HE'S PASSED AWAY BECAUSE OF
COVID. AND SO I'M ASKING YOU TO
LET US PUT IT ON THE NEXT THREE
MONTHS AND TRY TO TO MAKE SURE
THAT WE'RE GIVING HER THE
PROPER DUE DILIGENCE. I DON'T
WANT THE PUBLIC TO COME BACK TO
SAY THAT, YOU KNOW, WE KNEW
THAT SHE WAS UNDER DURESS,
UNDER A HUGE MEDICAL STRAIN,
JUST, YOU KNOW, GOING THROUGH A
LOT OF STUFF. I THINK IT'S
WORTH HAVING ANOTHER THREE
MONTHS PUSHING IT OFF TO THE
NEXT THREE MONTHS. AND, YOU
KNOW, LIKE I SAID, SHE LIVES IN
DISTRICT ONE AND HAS LIVED
THERE A LONG TIME COMMUNITY
MEMBER. AND IT IS IT IS REALLY.
STRESSFUL FOR ME TO KNOW THAT
SHE'S IN A PARTICULAR HEALTH
SITUATION RIGHT NOW, THAT I'M
NOT SURE THAT SHE'S ABLE TO
HAVE THESE VERY SERIOUS
CONVERSATIONS WITH YOU ABOUT
WHAT SHE'S GOING TO DO BECAUSE
SHE I DON'T KNOW THAT SHE'S IN
THAT POSITION RIGHT NOW, AND
SHE NEEDS TO GET SOME EXTRA
HELP. AND I HAVE ALSO REACHED
OUT TO SOME OF HER CLOSE
FRIENDS TO SEE WHAT WHAT HELP
THEY CAN GIVE HER, BECAUSE I
DON'T THINK SHE'S IN A POSITION
TO TELL YOU EXACTLY WHAT SHE'S
GOING TO DO, BECAUSE SHE HAS TO
FIGURE OUT WHAT HOW IS SHE
GOING TO MAINTAIN HER CURRENT
HEALTH SITUATION. SHE'S NOT
HEALTHY ENOUGH TO HAVE THESE
CONVERSATIONS AND TO ADD A
EXTRA PRESSURE OF A FORECLOSURE.
I'M NOT SURE WHAT JUST I WOULD
LIKE TO JUST HAVE SOME, SOME
COURTESY TO, TO HAVE THIS
POSTPONED FOR ANOTHER COUPLE OF
MONTHS.
>> COUNCILOR, IF I MAY, IF
COUNCIL PRESIDENT, IF IT'S ALL
RIGHT. A THIRD PATH THAT DAWNS
ON ME IS THAT PERHAPS THESE ARE
FIRST READINGS TODAY. THESE
WILL MOVE FORWARD TO SECOND
READING, ASSUMING THAT
DIRECTION FROM COUNCIL
PRESIDENT, PERHAPS AN OPTION
JUST TO EXPEDIATE TODAY IS MOVE
IT FORWARD. BUT WE'LL
ACKNOWLEDGE THAT WE'LL CONTINUE
TO DIALOG WITH THE PROPERTY
OWNER TO THE EXTENT WE'RE ABLE,
PERHAPS TO A LITTLE ADDITIONAL
OUTREACH, AND THEN I CAN WORK
WITH THE MAYOR'S OFFICE. I'LL
COMMIT TO DO THAT, THAT IF WE
NEED TO PULL IT OFF OF NEXT
WEEK'S AGENDA OR THE WEEK THAT
IT COMES TO VOTE SO THAT IT
DOESN'T GO FORWARD, THEN I'M
HAPPY TO HELP FACILITATE THAT
AND WORK WITH YOUR OFFICE.
>> NO, SIR. I THINK WE NEED TO
DO IT NOW. WE NEED TO JUST GIVE
THE TIME NOW ON THE FRONT END
BECAUSE LIKE I SAID, THAT I
THINK IT'S WORTH HAVING THE
TIME SPECIFICALLY BECAUSE OF
HER CURRENT HEALTH SITUATION.
THIS IS NOT AN ISSUE OF I'M
JUST NOT FEELING GOOD TODAY.
>> AND WE'VE GOT ABOUT TEN,
NINE MINUTES LEFT BEFORE WE
ABSOLUTELY TURN INTO PUMPKINS.
COUNCILOR IS THERE ARE YOU
MAKING A SPECIFIC MOTION AT
THIS POINT?
>> YEAH, I'D LIKE TO MAKE A
MOTION TO TO MOVE THIS TO THE
NEXT. DID YOU.
>> ROBERT TAYLOR, CITY ATTORNEY
YOU HAVE A COUPLE OF DIFFERENT
OPTIONS. YOU COULD MAKE A
MOTION TO POSTPONE IT TO A DATE
CERTAIN. AND THEN IF WE GET TO
THAT DATE CERTAIN AND WE'RE
STILL NOT READY TO ACT, YOU CAN
POSTPONE IT AGAIN. YOU COULD
LAY IT ON THE TABLE. AT WHICH
POINT AT A FUTURE COUNCIL
MEETING, YOU COULD TAKE IT OFF
THE TABLE. ANOTHER THING YOU
COULD DO IS MAKE A MOTION TO
REFER THIS TO COMMITTEE, MAYBE
REFER IT TO THE COMMITTEE OF
THE WHOLE THERE. IT WOULD REST
IN THAT COMMITTEE UNTIL THERE'S
SOME ACTION. WHAT I WOULD
CAUTION.
>> WHAT YOU SAID. I, I JUST
NEED A COUPLE OF MONTHS FOR.
THAT'S WHAT SHE NEEDS IS A
COUPLE OF MONTHS TO, TO, TO, TO
REALIZE WHERE SHE'S AT IN TERMS
OF HER CURRENT HEALTH SITUATION.
LIKE I SAID, THIS IS NOT, YOU
KNOW, I JUST SCRAPED MY KNEE
KIND OF THING. AND SHE HAS A, A
NUMBER OF, OF PRESSURES ON HER
RIGHT NOW AND SHE DOESN'T HAVE
THE HELP. AND I'M JUST TRYING
TO EASE SOME OF THIS, SOME OF
THIS PRESSURE AND POSTPONE THIS
FOR A COUPLE OF MONTHS. AND
THEN IF IT GOES BACK ON OUR
NEXT LIST AND YOU CAN PROCEED.
BUT I DIDN'T KNOW ABOUT THIS
SITUATION UNTIL I, ME AND MY
STAFF WERE LOOKING AT IT. AND I
ALWAYS LOOK UP ALL THE
ADDRESSES AND OWNERS AND SEE.
AND I, AND I KNOW I RECOGNIZE
THAT SHE WAS A PERSON WHO LIVES
IN OUR GAY THAT I'VE KNOWN FOR
A LONG TIME. SHE WAS A LONGTIME
MULTNOMAH COUNTY. EMPLOYEE. AND
SHE'S HAVING SOME REALLY
DIFFICULT TIMES. AND SO I JUST,
I DIDN'T KNOW IF YOU ALL KNEW
THAT. AND YOU SAID THAT YOU'VE
TALKED TO HER, BUT IF YOU'VE
TALKED TO HER, YOU'VE PROBABLY
HAVE RECOGNIZED THAT SHE IS NOT
IN THE BEST OF HEALTH.
>> SO, COUNCILOR, IN THE
INTEREST OF TIME, IS THERE A
SPECIFIC MOTION?
>> I'D LIKE TO DO A MOTION TO
POSTPONE THIS FOR THE NEXT
FORECLOSURE LIST THAT COMES OUT
IN THE NEXT COUPLE OF MONTHS.
>> OKAY. THE MOTION IS TO
POSTPONE THIS. IS THAT
SUFFICIENT FOR A MOTION TO
POSTPONE TO THE ITEM, OR IS IT
A DATE? IS A DATE REQUIRED?
>> I THINK THE INTENT OF THAT
IS IS CLEAR. YEAH.
>> POINT OF INFORMATION.
>> COUNCILOR AVALOS.
>> SO BECAUSE IN COMMITTEE,
WHEN WE HAD ALL THESE, WE DID A
SIMILAR THING WITH ONE WHERE IT
WAS LIKE MOVED TO ANOTHER TIME.
LIKE, DOES IT JUST GET PUT IN
THAT SAME QUEUE, I GUESS, OR
LIKE, IS THERE A RELATIONSHIP
BETWEEN THE ONES THAT ARE THE
OTHER ONES THAT ARE BEING
STALLED? JUST TRYING TO
UNDERSTAND PROCESS.
>> WE CAN WE CAN LOOK AT ADDING
IT TO THE. SO LIKE RIGHT NOW,
I'VE ALREADY RECEIVED THE LIST
OF PROPERTIES THAT I'M WORKING
ON FOR THE NEXT LIST, SO IT MAY
PUSH IT DOWN THE ROAD TO. AFTER
THAT LIST IS I COMPLETED AND.
>> AND DID THESE GO THROUGH THE
WATCH COMMITTEE? DID THESE GO
THROUGH.
>> THEY ORIGINALLY WENT THROUGH
THE HOUSING COMMITTEE. WE'VE
BEEN DISCUSSING THAT IN THE
FUTURE. THEY SHOULD GO TO THE
COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE. BUT
THESE ALL WENT TO HOUSING.
>> YEAH. IF YOU KNOW, THE
SECOND BATCH IS GOING TO GO
THROUGH A PARTICULAR COMMITTEE,
THEN YOU COULD REFER THIS ONE
TO THAT COMMITTEE SO THAT THEN
THEY COULD ALL JUST TRACK.
>> AND THEY WILL BE GOING
THROUGH THE COMMITTEE THE WHOLE
TIME. AND THERE IS A MOTION ON
THE FLOOR. THERE IS A MOTION ON
SECONDED YET.
>> OKAY.
>> SECOND.
>> THERE YOU GO, COUNSELOR
SMITH MOVES TO POSTPONE THIS
ITEM TO ALIGN WITH THE NEXT
BATCH OF FORECLOSURE ITEMS.
COUNCILOR NOVICK SECONDS.
COLLEAGUES. DISCUSSION OF THE
AMENDMENT. COUNCILOR KANAL.
>> THANK YOU. I HAD A QUESTION
IN THE TIMELINE. YOU MENTIONED
2016. YOU MENTIONED 2022, 2023.
I SEE THAT THERE'S AN ORDINANCE
THAT WAS FILED FOR THE FEBRUARY
7TH, 2024 CITY COUNCIL AGENDA
ABOUT THIS PROPERTY. AND I'M
JUST CURIOUS IF YOU COULD. IT'S
A IT'S A FORECLOSURE ACTION
THERE. IF THAT WASN'T MENTIONED
HERE, CAN YOU SPEAK TO EXACTLY
WHAT HAPPENED? IT SHOWS THAT IT
WAS REFERRED TO COMMISSIONER OF
FINANCE AND ADMINISTRATION,
WHICH IS, I'M ASSUMING
WHICHEVER COMMISSIONER WAS OVER
THE BUREAU AT THE TIME. BUT CAN
YOU GIVE A LITTLE BIT MORE ON
THAT?
>> SURE. THAT PARTICULAR TIME
WE WERE ABLE TO I WAS ABLE TO
WORK OUT AN ARRANGEMENT WITH
THE PROPERTY OWNER, AND SO WE
REMOVED IT FROM THE LIST. AND
AT THAT POINT, THE TENANTS HAD
VACATED THE PROPERTY. THANK YOU.
AND AT THAT POINT, THE TENANTS
WERE NO LONGER IN THE PROPERTY.
IT WAS VACANT AND WE REMOVED IT
FROM THE LIST AT THAT TIME TO
ALLOW TIME FOR HER TO DO THE
THE REMEDIATION WORK ON THE
PROPERTY TO BRING IT INTO
COMPLIANCE.
>> OKAY. AND IS THAT THE ISSUE
THAT REMAINS UNRESOLVED NOW, OR
IS IT A NEW SET OF ISSUES THAT
GOT IT BACK ON THIS LIST?
>> I'LL ANSWER THAT ONE.
>> THERE ARE UNRESOLVED
PROPERTY MAINTENANCE VIOLATIONS
FROM THE ORIGINAL CASE BACK IN
2016 REGARDING THE INTERIOR
CONDITION OF THE PROPERTY,
ALONG WITH EXTERIOR NUISANCE
CONDITIONS INCLUDING RAT
HARBORAGE, WHICH ARE UNABATED.
>> AND ALL OF THOSE PREDATE THE
2024 SET OF OR WERE INCLUDED OR
PREDATE THE 2024 LIST. IS ANY
OF THAT NEW? SUBSEQUENT TO 2024?
>> IT'S POSSIBLE DURING
RE-INSPECTIONS, THEY MAY DO A
REINSPECTION AND FIND THAT SOME
VIOLATIONS WERE CORRECTED. SOME
NEW VIOLATIONS HAVE APPEARED,
SO I DON'T WANT TO SAY THAT
THEY'RE ALL REMAINING. THERE
COULD BE SOME NEW VIOLATIONS
THAT WERE NOTED FOR
DETERIORATING CONDITIONS AFTER
2024 IF RE-INSPECTIONS WERE
DONE, BUT PREDOMINANTLY, I
THINK THESE CONDITIONS WERE ALL
CITED IN 2016.
>> OKAY. YEAH, I APPRECIATE
THAT. AND YOU KNOW, THIS I
DON'T KNOW THE THE OWNER OR
REALLY THE SITUATION
SPECIFICALLY. I DO KNOW THIS
AREA. IT'S IN OBVIOUSLY IN OUR
DISTRICT. AND SO DRIVEN BY THIS,
THIS PARTICULAR LOCATION. SO I,
I'M INTERESTED IN RESOLVING
THAT TOO, IN ADDITION TO
ENSURING THAT WE'RE DOING RIGHT
BY, BY THE FOLKS WHO LIVE HERE
AND, AND OWN IT. THANKS.
>> THANK YOU. COUNCILOR KANAL.
COUNCILOR. PIRTLE-GUINEY.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCIL PRESIDENT,
DO WE HAVE A SPECIFIC DO WE
KNOW WHEN THE NEXT BATCH OF
FORECLOSURES WILL BE COMING
FORWARD? WE HEARD CFO SAY THAT
WE TRY TO DO BETWEEN 90 AND 100
DAYS. I KNOW WHEN I WAS COUNCIL
PRESIDENT, WE HAD TALKED ABOUT
TRYING TO MOVE TO A QUARTERLY
CADENCE. AND IF THIS IS
SOMETHING WHERE WE ARE ASKING
NEIGHBORS TO WAIT AN ADDITIONAL
2 TO 3 MONTHS TO GET THIS
RESOLVED, THAT FEELS VERY
DIFFERENT TO ME THAN IF WE ARE
ASKING NEIGHBORS TO WAIT AN
INDEFINITE AMOUNT OF TIME,
BECAUSE WE DON'T KNOW WHEN THE
NEXT BATCH IS COMING.
>> YEAH. COUNCILOR, THANK YOU
FOR THE QUESTION. OUR OBJECTIVE,
OUR ASPIRATION, IS TO PUT ABOUT
90 TO 120 DAYS BETWEEN THESE
KIND OF BATCHING OF FORECLOSURE
ITEMS. THE TWO CHALLENGES WITH
THAT ONE IS GETTING SPACE ON A
COUNCIL AND COMMITTEE AGENDA.
ACKNOWLEDGING THAT WE STARTED
THIS CONVERSATION AT COMMITTEE
ALMOST TWO MONTHS AGO. AND JUST
TO GET TO THIS DATE, THE OTHER
ISSUE WE HAVE IS JUST STAFFING
CONSTRAINTS THAT WE DON'T
ALWAYS HAVE STAFF CAPACITY TO
CATCH THESE AS OFTEN AS THE
NUISANCE PROPERTY REQUESTS COME
UP. AND SO WE HAVE TO KIND OF
NAVIGATE BOTH OF THOSE
CHALLENGES.
>> COUNCIL PRESIDENT, YOUR
INTENT IS TO MOVE FORECLOSURES.
>> THROUGH.
>> COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE.
>> IN THE FUTURE. IS THAT
CORRECT?
>> THAT IS CORRECT.
>> AND. COUNCILOR KANAL, HOW
WOULD SCHEDULING LOOK A FEW
MONTHS FROM NOW FOR THE NEXT
BATCH OF FORECLOSURES AND
COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE?
>> MAY I RESPOND TO THAT
COUNCIL PRESIDENT? AND I'M ALSO
USING THAT QUESTION TO PULL UP
MY NOTES. YOU KNOW, WE HAVEN'T
SCHEDULED PAST THANKSGIVING.
WE'VE GOT PENCILED IN THROUGH
THAT FAR. BUT SO I NOTHING ELSE
IS ON THE RADAR FOR AFTER THAT,
EXCEPT ONE MEETING OF AN
OVERSIGHT HEARING. SO AND I
THINK WE HAVE FOUR MEETINGS
AFTER THAT MIGHT JUST BE THREE
ACTUALLY. SO LET ME SAY THREE
TO BE SAFE. SO I DON'T
ANTICIPATE THERE BEING A
CHALLENGE. THERE'S THE OTHER
THINGS THAT I KNOW ARE COMING
ARE SOME APPOINTMENTS TO
VOLUNTEER BODIES.
>> SO PRESUMABLY A 90 DAY
CADENCE FROM WHEN THIS FIRST
CAME TO COMMITTEE, WHICH WAS, I
BELIEVE SOMETIME IN AUGUST,
WOULD PUT US AT SOMETIME IN
NOVEMBER. YOU'RE SAYING THAT
YOU COULD LIKELY GET THINGS ON
THE SCHEDULE THE BEGINNING OF
DECEMBER?
>> I SORRY, I WAS GOING OFF OF
THREE MONTHS FROM NOW, GOING
OFF OF THREE MONTHS FROM THEN.
THERE'S THERE'S GAPS IN THERE.
I'M NOT 100% SURE HOW WE'RE
HANDLING A COUPLE SPECIFIC
DATES. I JUST HEARD ABOUT THE
WEEK OF THE FIRST FULL WEEK OF
NOVEMBER, HAVING SOME ISSUES
WITH THE BUILDING. SO GOING
VIRTUAL, I THINK FOR THAT ONE.
OKAY, SO THAT SINCE WE STILL
HAVE THAT DATE, THEN I THINK
IT'S POSSIBLE. I DON'T WANT TO
GIVE YOU 100%, BUT I'M NOT
PARTICULARLY WORRIED ABOUT IT
RIGHT NOW.
>> COLLEAGUES, WE ARE AT 130,
THE TIME THAT I TOLD STAFF WE
WOULD BE DONE. SO COUNCILOR
SMITH, PLEASE, BRIEFLY LAST
WORD.
>> THANK YOU. I JUST WANT TO
SAY THIS LAST THING. SHE'S AN
ELDERLY WOMAN WHO'S IN POOR
HEALTH, WHO HAS BEEN A LONGTIME
ADVOCATE FOR FOLKS IN THE
AFRICAN AMERICAN COMMUNITY. AND
I JUST FELT LIKE SHE'S ALWAYS
SPEAKING UP FOR OTHERS AND
TRYING TO HELP OTHERS, THAT
THERE'S NO ONE TO SPEAK UP FOR
HER. AND I WANT TO MAKE SURE
THAT SHE'S IN HER RIGHT MIND.
THIS IS MIND YOU, THIS IS PRIME
PROPERTY IN INNER NORTHEAST
PORTLAND, AND I DON'T WANT HER
TO BE A VICTIM OF SOMEONE
TRYING TO GET THAT PROPERTY.
AND SHE DOESN'T HAVE A CHANCE
TO HELP HER OWN SELF OUT.
THAT'S, THAT'S, THAT'S MY OTHER
CONCERN WITH THIS IS SOMEONE
WILL TRY TO TAKE ADVANTAGE OF
HER IN THIS CURRENT STATE. AND
I'VE SEEN IT HAPPEN SO MANY
TIMES TO ELDERLY FOLKS IN OUR
COMMUNITY. AND I JUST DON'T
WANT HER TO BE A VICTIM OF THAT.
>> THANK YOU. COUNCILOR SMITH.
SEEING NO ONE ELSE IN THE QUEUE,
KEELAN CAN WE PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON SMITH ONE.
>> MOVE BY SMITH. SECONDED BY
NOVICK KOYAMA LANE. I AYE,
MORILLO.
>> THANK YOU, COUNCILOR SMITH.
I THINK THIS IS A REALLY NOBLE
WAY TO USE GOVERNMENT. AYE,
MORILLO.
>> NOVICK. I CLARK. I GREEN. I
ZIMMERMAN. I SMITH.
>> I I. PIRTLE-GUINEY I.
>> RYAN I.
>> DUNPHY I.
>> THE MOTION CARRIES WITH A
VOTE OF 12 AYES.
>> THANK YOU. ALL THE REMAINING
ITEMS MOVE TO SECOND READING.
WE ARE IN RECESS UNTIL TOMORROW.
WE DON'T HAVE TOMORROW. WE'RE
ADJOURNED. WE GOT A WORK
SESSION. WE'RE ADJOURNED. THANK
YOU EVERYBODY.